Are you fed up with console spam?
Sick of browser messages that tell you problems but
not how to fix them?
Well, the Issues tab is a new way for Chrome
DevTools to help you find and fix problems with your web
site. Problems detected by the browser are
presented in a structured format, separate
from the console.
And that also means your own console messages don't get
drowned out by browser warnings.
The Issues tab aggregates different types of problems.
It describes problems using clear and simple language,
explains how to fix them, and links to affected resources
within DevTools.
And shows you where to find further guidance.
So let's run through that from start to finish.
First, you need a page with problems.
Well, for this example, we have a page with lots of
problems.
Open the page in Chrome and then open Chrome DevTools.
As you can see, issues were detected.
Click the 'go to issues' button in the yellow warning bar.
You can also select the Issues tab from the 'More Tools'
menu or click on the blue icon at the
top of DevTools.
Now you might need to click the 'reload page' button
since DevTools can't collect requests while it's closed.
You'll notice that for the moment, warnings that used to
show up in the console still do as well as in the
Issues tab.
The initial version of the Issues tab checks for three
types of issue: cookie problems, mixed content,
cross-origin embedder policy - that's COEP - issues
as well. Future versions will support more
issue types.
So click an item in the Issues tab and you'll see that
each item has four components.
A headline, describing the issue, a description
providing the context and the solution, and
an 'affected resources' section that links to the resources
within the appropriate DevTools contexts such as the
Network panel, and also links to further guidance.
Click on items within affected resources to view details.
In this example, there is one cookie and one request.
Now the Issues tab explains problems
and tells you how to fix them.
But it can also show your resources in the appropriate
context within the DevTools themselves.
So click on a resource link to view the item in context.
In this example, click samesite-sandbox.glitch.me
to show the cookies attached to that request.
Scroll to view the item with a problem; in this case, the
cookie ck02.
Hover over the Information icon on the right to see the
problem and how to fix it.
You can also go the other way. Right-click on an item
within DevTools to show issues associated with
it. We'll be adding more features to the Issues tab in the
future. So let us know what you think, how we could improve
the Issues tab and what features you'd like to see.
You can comment on this video or file bug reports in
Crbug, which is the engineering team's bug tracker,
or send a tweet to @ChromeDevTools.
As ever, we really appreciate your feedback.