[Music]
[Applause]
hello rim thank you for joining us today
my name is sebastian benz I'm part of
the amp developer relations team and my
name is Nana rising honey and I'm a
product manager on the amp project we
want to talk about the work we are doing
on amp to make better women less painful
and developers more productive yeah I'm
incredibly excited so let's dive right
into it so now we would be remiss if we
talked about em and didn't talk about
the impact of Google's recent
announcement around the page experience
ranking signal absolutely so even before
we can actually start talking about amp
and page experience first let's just
talk about what the announcement is in
May the Google search team announced
that they're going to measure how the
page is experienced by the user in
addition to price signals such as a
pages usefulness and this whole suite of
X measurements is called page experience
it uses core web vitals which the chrome
team announced earlier that month and
adds other pre-existing signals such as
mobile friendliness safe browsing and
HTTPS on top of it and the great thing
is that these metrics line up really
well with amps design goals of making
sure that users are getting a content
forward experience on a rig and are able
to consume content without having to
download unnecessary resources or wait
for unnecessary processing okay so how
does amp do against page experience good
catch actually we did some analysis and
we saw that a majority of amp pages
actually already do pretty well against
this criteria this means that amp is
really living up to the intention of
being a well lit path to creating a
great page experience so you said that a
majority of amp pages meet the criteria
but not all yep
so in the cases where the amp page
doesn't perform well against the page
experience criteria we saw that they
failed for reasons that were outside of
amps control such as overly large images
being served on mobile devices or the
server response time being too slow
that's a really interesting key aspect
of page experience that the core web
battles are mash up from real user data
this means to improve your cover battles
for example it's a good idea to use a
CDN to ensure that users
the world get your conduct delivered
quickly yeah and just like other
libraries and frameworks the amp project
will be monitoring these metrics closely
and continue investing in amps
performance by our performance working
group but more generally it's really
important to note that amp will intends
to reduce the ongoing effort needed to
create pages that offer a great user
experience and we intend to do so by
helping offload tasks and worries such
as browser compatibility accessibility
javascript budgets etc at its core and
as a UI component library before using
amp often struggled with too much choice
when it came to adding a new feature to
a site having to decide whether I should
bid my own carousel which is a bad idea
or finding a suitable existing
implementation could take a lot of time
and energy with amp you get a flexible
high quality or high component out of
the box and you can be sure that these
perform well are accessible and play
along well with each other recently I
talked to a developer from an agency
which uses am for building most of their
clients websites they told me that one
of their two side in terms had been able
to build a fully interactive website
from one of their clients without any
JavaScript knowledge I think that's
fantastic and a great example for the
value of a good UI component library it
makes it easy to get started for
beginners and then also experienced
developers to focus on creating new user
experiences instead of bike sharing
technical details and that's exactly
what we're focusing on in 2020 we want
amp to be a cost-effective and simple
solution that allows developers to focus
on their product and not worry about
other things like performance
infrastructure etc and this is an effort
that we're calling amp as a service the
idea here is to use em as a turnkey
solution to easily create and then
maintain a great page experience and
make developers more productive
simultaneously so what exactly do you
intend to do so the first thing that we
really want to do is address the
feedback that app developers have and
some of the top complaints that we've
seen with amp is first the need for
custom JavaScript and second the fact
that the inline CSS limit is too small
at 50 kilobytes
now we address the need for
javascript by adding amp script a
component that allows you to add custom
JavaScript to amp to help fulfill any
business specific need that amp doesn't
solve and if you want to hear more here
you should stay tuned because our
colleagues Ben Morse and crystal Lambert
will be talking you through this in
their talk titled where Christ GS
now with our CSS limit the intention was
to promote CSS hygiene but we got
feedback that the limit was too tight at
50 kilobytes so we worked with the amp
community to understand what a
reasonable CSS limit could be and after
working with plugin developers news
publishers and e-commerce site creators
we realized that most interactive
experiences could actually fit me within
75 kilobytes of CSS and so that's what
we made our new limit 75 kilobytes and
this really seems to have hit the sweet
spot with a vibe to kill my limit I have
from many developers that they've been
strongly was keeping this yes as below
the limit but I still have to hear from
someone starting with the 75 Caleb
element yeah fingers crossed that this
limit works now aside from addressing
feedback we wanted to we want to make
developers more productive we want to
help them create and maintain
performance sites as well the problem
usually wasn't with Ambit self but then
they had to maintain two versions of the
pages the canonical one and an
additional one and one yep that's far
that's by far the largest problem that
amp developers have the problem is even
more acute if you have separate teams
that are working on the amp and mobile
web experience especially if they're in
separate parts of the organization to be
honest the amp team itself advocated for
paired amp experiences when we got
started we saw it as an easy way to
create amp pages with the least amount
of effort but talking to developers over
time has made us realise the amount of
pain that can be associated with
maintaining this dual code base and that
this outweighs the initial games of
actually creating the amp page quickly
and Google's page experience
announcement is a great move for amp
developers in this regard it allows
development teams to really think about
how they want to continue investing in
amp going forward ok so say I'm I'm
publishing paired-end pages because I
want to be in the Google top stories
accountable should I continue doing this
so in that case I would ask for you
consider the maintenance costs that you
are incurring by having to maintain an
amp version of your code and a non
immersion of your code now that you have
the option to be flexible with your tech
stack you should be looking to pick a
setup that allows all your web
developers to be productive from day one
so you're telling those we're going the
paired-end route to completely drop and
support know what we're telling them is
to pick something that makes them the
most productive and this could be a
number of things developers could pick
experiences on their site that could
actually benefit from amp and only
invest in amp for those experiences or
they could go fully am first across all
their site if they actually believe that
amp is able to meet their needs and
we've gotten pretty positive feedback
from developers who use amp as their
main library because they think that amp
makes them more productive and this is
what we see amps future as a component
library that helps developers be more
productive and this is why we're
investing in allowing everyone to use
amp components even outside of amp pages
it's an effort that we're calling bento
app and we look forward to releasing it
later this year I'm really excited about
this focusing on amp as your I component
library isn't much healthier direction
in my opinion and I'm very happy that
we're making this move another we were
taking or learnings from and/or making
them available to provide your audience
our server side optimizations fan pages
at the beginning amp pages we're mostly
short from our caches and these perform
additional optimizations enabling
amstrong user experience however many
developers started using and forbidding
their whole website in these cases and
pages are not stopped from a cache and
there has been room for improving amps
loading performance to address this we
created app optimizer
a tool to bring em cache optimizations
to publishers for example we use an
optimized for the official app website
after death and by using I'm optimizing
achieves the same performance as when
the page is served from an app cache and
what I really like and optimizer fits
really well into your idea of a bizarre
service it enables us to automate bet
development best practices for example
the latest of optimizer with these added
support for image source a generation to
make it easier to serve optimized images
another example is JavaScript modules
the amp project is soon going to start
serving them run to them of components
as JavaScript modules and if you're
using amp optimizer you will
automatically get the benefit of smaller
runtime modules once this becomes
available and that sounds so great and
I'm really excited about all the
improvements that are coming to
optimizer but what's the best way for
developers to actually include amp
optimizer
I mean of course you could include it
normally in your build pipeline or your
rendering pipeline but ideally you
shouldn't have to think about how to do
get M optimizer our goal is to make the
integration seamless by integrating an
optimizer
into existing frameworks and single
sensors the next is integration is a
great example for what a good ahmedabad
experience can look like next is has a
special amp mode that you enable your
flag and this will result in the
generated page being ballot app the cool
thing is that you can start using amp
component straight out of the box and
you don't need to worry about the EM
boilerplate or importing M components
all of this is automatically added in
the background band optimizer
which is integrated directly into next
earnest and the resulting editing
experience was really nice and it feels
like that development from 30 years ago
and a great example for this is as Axios
they recently launched the new site and
it's completely built on am using these
days and they've been really happy with
the experience another example for a CMS
that has these features integrated is
WordPress recently the official and
breakfast plug-in start the publishing
optimized amp by default so this means
if you built an amp age using WordPress
you get the best serving performance for
Wow it's it's really exciting to see so
many new experiences that are being
built using amp and in fact amp
optimizer and I'm really hoping to see
more but that's it that's our time and
that's our vision for 2020 the Google
Page experience announcement allows amp
to focus on what it does best
be a UI component library that helps
developers be more productive by helping
them deploy web development best
practices at scale and if you want to
read more about Em's plans for 2020
please read our blog post and gilded amp
a definite service and with that thank
you for joining us if you want to learn
more about amp in general you can visit
amp death today thanks everyone and we
will spend on the chat I'll answer your
questions for bit
[Music]
[Applause]