[Music]
[Applause]
hi I'm Damian a well because he's thing
consultant at Google in this talk you
will learn how to define an install
strategy across all your mobile
experiences letting your users install
your app is one of the best ways to keep
them engaged today you can achieve that
in different ways let's start with
native app installs if you have a native
application you might think that this
might be the best platform to promote to
all your users and for some of them this
might be true but for some users native
apps can have some disadvantages too
the most common one is storage
constraints making space for a new app
may mean removing valuable content
freeing up storage is also the number
one reason users remove apps from their
devices there's also the issue of
available bandwidth especially for users
on slow connections and expensive data
plans finally moving to a store creates
additional friction and delays a user
action that could be performed directly
in the web a great alternative to this
is allowing users to install your
progress he web app from the browser
through another home screen prompt you
can also upload your PWA to the play
store using trusted web activity in this
example came to under a real estate
company from Brazil was able to reuse
the same codebase in the world and the
Play Store while offering a great
experience to users let's take a look at
another example all your rooms is one of
the largest hospitality companies in
India they have a very large user base
coming from a variety of devices and
networks they have built different
versions of their mobile experience to
satisfy the needs of all their users
first I created a native application for
the Play Store for the most
sophisticated users this could be the
best choice all you light is a
progressive web app uploaded to Play
Store be a trusted web activity it
provides the same functionality of the
nav bar well occupying only 7% of the
space finally for users that visit the
site directly by typing the URL or
clicking on a link or offers the chance
of installing the pedo
directly from the home screen having all
these ways to achieve app installs is
great but how can you combine all these
offerings to increase installation rates
well I Bodi make your apps compete with
each other let's discuss some strategies
to combine different install offerings
the first strategy is to show the
different options in the same screen
this is a simple approach that might
just work for many users the challenge
is to be able to communicate the value
proposition to distinguish clearly one
from the other but instead of delegating
the choice completely to users we can
make the life easier the idea of the
following strategies is to make some
inferences for example by tracking users
behavior and device characteristics we
call this heuristic based approaches the
first one is web installed as fallback
in this strategy you can start showing
the native app installed prompt if the
user doesn't install the app and keeps
visiting to your website chances are
that the web is their platform of choice
after a while you can start promoting
your pillow EA to these users this
strategy can be implemented very easily
for example by using cookies to drag
user behavior the group of users that
this means the abun huh
keep coming several times to the side
might be good candidates for a web
install offering but before showing the
web install call-to-action there are two
more things to take into account the
first one make sure that the user hasn't
already installed your native app or
your PDA by other means the Getty store
related apps API can help you check that
the second is actually a UX best
practice to maximize the opt-in rate for
your web install prompts you might want
to use the double permission pattern in
this example shows AG web install icon
after capturing the before installed
prompt event when the user clicks on it
they trigger the standard Add to Home
screen prompt if you want to learn about
UX patterns for web permissions like
this one check
Deshea stock safe permissions for the
capable web at crontab Sammy 2019 let's
move now to the second strategy
intuitively users on slow networks or
low-end devices might be more inclined
to download light apps
therefore if it's possible to identify a
user's device one could prioritize the
light up over the heavier native app
installed version you can implement this
by writing a function checking for
device characteristics to decide which
prompt to show if it's a low-end device
a light up if it's a high-end device you
can offer the core native app inside the
function the by signals can be obtained
in two ways the first one is by using
javascript api s-- like device memory
hard work on currency or the network
information API the second one is by
using client hints which can be inferred
from the header of the HTTP request to
use them you need to send an asset CH
gathering your response indicating the
type of hints you want to receive for
example device memory after that you
will start receiving these hints in the
header of the HCP request finally you
can use this information to map to a
device category and use that later to
decide which prompt to show if you want
to learn techniques on how to map the
buy signals to device categories
check out adaptive loading a talk that
was given at random Sammy 2019 prepping
us today you can offer different
channels to users to install your model
experiences for example you could offer
an ad but ap delay available in the Play
Store and iWeb installed from the user
screen then you can define a heuristic
to show the most suitable install
offering to a particular user you can
create a very simple one based on the
user behavior on your site for example
by tracking how often they come to it or
you can go for a more sophisticated
approach when mapping the buy signals to
device categories and show different
install offerings depending if the
device is low mid or high end we
encourage you to experiment with these
techniques for example by running a be
test and to reach out to us on Twitter
to share your experiences
I hope you continue enjoying what the
Bligh's thanks for watching
[Music]
[Applause]