[Music]
hey everybody
Paulo is here just gonna show you some
features that have been landing inside
of dev tools recently and a half as
always so Moe with me and we're just
going to talk those through navigate
around I've got a few demos and things
to show you hey doing some I'm good good
good I thought we could start with I
know you've been working on on the
performance tab yes in in some ways and
that's one something that people aren't
within why don't we start with that
let's deal with that then okay so if
you've not seen it if I let's just go
there right now
web dev slash metrics helps if I can
type as always my typing is waffle but
nothing has changed things changed web
dev slash metrics okay so here you can
see we've got a important metrics to
measure first content for paint largest
content for paint first input delay time
to interactive total blocking time and
cumulative layout shift now some of
these metrics it's worth saying from the
off these are all designed to help you
improve the user experience in your
sites and your apps but not all of them
are suitable for what we'd call a lab
setting some of them are we call field
setting metrics so for example first
input delay it's not really something
you typically test in a lab setting
something you do more with the field
with like rum and sort of live data so
not all of these make sense in in the
lab but the ones that do we've been
trying to get into the performance panel
inside of dev tools so because once your
death thoughts you are in a lab setting
exactly you're not you can never require
a real user after mechanically so from
dev tools and quickly do with the
measurement the second you need EV tools
to measure something you're in a lab
yeah and so our assumption is
predominately if your local host on your
machine we tend to refer to that as the
lab setting so let me just run you
through very quickly the kinds of things
we've got so if I just if I go to the
web dev home page and I've got the
performance tab open here in chrome this
is Ernie in canary so
some of these features are very kind of
hot off the press they're subject to
change so just bear that in mind if
these things look a little bit different
over the coming weeks and months it's
because we're working on them we just
wanted to share them with you because
we're kind of excited about some of them
and all them we want to show them to you
so if I take a recording so I've been
about to record I'm going to hit in my
case command shift R which will do a
reload without any caching just wait for
a little while for thing all service
worker sorry say again all service
worker like it's literally as if you hit
the network yeah exactly so I'm gonna
stop that profile I left it running for
quite some time there and it's gonna
process that okay so let me bring that
down so this I mean this is actually a
really good trace recording like a
performance recording if you've got
something like this in the lab setting
you can be super happy and the reason is
if I just zoom in a little bit here you
can see that most of the tasks in all of
these top-level tasks here the tasks
they're all really really short and
that's really good because it means
they're super short it means that the
main thread is remaining responsive so
let me just zoom back out but let's talk
about some of these metrics so for
example dunk content loaded that's been
around since forever really
um and that continues to be shown here
but you see this timings row contains
some new ones like first paint first
content full paint first meaningful
paint and largest content for painting
you actually see on my screen here when
I roll over largest content for paint
the element that is the largest content
for paint highlights we put an overlay
on that one so you can see so
immediately some of these metrics that
you're going to see in web dev slash
metrics are showing up inside of the dev
tools timeline so that's the high level
metrics what we can also do though is we
can show long tasks now as I said all
these tasks are pretty pretty quick but
I'm running on decent hardware here this
one here is 18 milliseconds and I think
we could probably do another recording
and actually show it slowed down so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to go to
the settings here and I'm going to
switch on CPU throttling I'm gonna
switch it to 6 times slow down there
isn't going to do that it's just so that
we can see what it would look like on
slower hardware so
of a MacBook now yeah exactly so I'm
going to record a refresh as I did
before as I say I'm going to give it
time to actually settle down some of our
metrics they do need to wait until
there's only a couple of requests
running on the network and so on so I'm
gonna stop that recording and what we
start to see is we start to see these
red triangles so again let me zoom in on
what's going on here so there's a couple
of things to notice one is that the task
six times slow down in this particular
case is one hundred and sixty eight
point five four milliseconds what we're
trying to do is we're going to try and
keep all our tasks under fifty
milliseconds and the reason for that is
that we can may make their main thread
responsive when we do that to use
interactions because most of the
JavaScript that people are running like
touch handlers and mouse click handlers
and all those kinds of things
all run on the main thread and so what
we want to make sure is that we're not
blocking the main thread with work and
so keeping tasks under 50 milliseconds
is the goal so the the blocking time and
I mean let's be honest year that I mean
50 milliseconds is somewhat lenient if
we went to the good old goal of like 60
frames a second it would be even less
but during the first load we can be a
bit more lenient because nobody expects
to interact with the website during the
first second of loading and so we can be
have a little bit of a higher threshold
there but about 50 milliseconds it can
become very noticeable if the mate was
blocked yeah absolutely great point in
the context of page load absolutely this
is more about the 50 millisecond thing
if you're animating yeah absolutely to
just repeat that you'd be going for 60
frames a second and your tasks would
need to be a lot lot shorter so if
you're wondering how much of your
recording is actually blocking so how
much it can be striping overall do you
have going on in here well we actually
have this new metric at the bottom which
says total blocking time which you can
think of is like the amount of candy
striping that's in this recording as a
whole
in this particular case it's two hundred
and thirty point zero five milliseconds
and we have a link to explain what's
going on and you can see that that would
take you over to the total blocking time
metric information so that's so I find
it quite interesting because we have the
the total blocking time is actually not
necessarily the amount of time that
Maine has been blocked because you have
a fifty milliseconds budget per task if
you're allowed to block but everything
gets over counts into that total
blocking time so that is the amount of
time that you went over the 50
millisecond budget exactly I should say
the the total blocking time we tend to
stop it at one metric that is not shown
here which is the time to interactive so
when we hit an interactive time and the
back end and blink actually notifies us
that we've hit hit interactive time if
it can will actually stop tracking total
blocking time for that value at the
bottom but the candy striping here would
tally pretty much entirely with that
total blocking time at the bottom you've
got this number 230 point zero five in
this case it's that if a number starts
to creep open up that's something you're
going to want to take a look at because
that means that you're spending quite a
lot of time with long running tasks on
the main thread and the chances are it's
it's negatively impacting the user
experience in this case web dev is
actually really good it's just I had to
introduce some slowdown which is a good
feature to know about that you can
introduce slowdown both in terms of the
CPU but also the network as well you can
do that if you so desire so that's
that's the total blocking time that's
long running tasks as well we we mark
that at 50 milliseconds plus with the
candy striping and the little red
triangle in the corner now the other
thing we've also introduced is a thing
called layout shifting so if I just even
go to the Google homepage and I do a
recording here and I just refreshed like
so I hit stop okay what you're gonna see
is you're going to see a new track if we
find any layout shifts and the layout
track so the expense is the new track
it's called experience and one inside
here we've got a layout shift and if we
click on this let me just bring this up
so you can see a bit more you get
information on the layer shift so the
idea of the layout shift is I think most
people have experienced this you're
browsing the web and you're about to tap
on a button and it moves to somewhere
else on the screen and it's really
frustrating and so we're starting to
give you the ways and the means of
tracking those layout shifts in the
course of you know interacting with your
page and so on and we put them into this
experience track so there's some stuff
about
boring which if you read the
documentation on cumulative layout
shifts I will explain the scoring a
little bit more to you and you can also
see whether or not it was in response to
some recent user input we also include
some location information where you went
from and you can see this here is this
so it's come from here this element has
shifted to here you can see that overlay
so I'm pretty confident I know what it
is it's probably this privacy reminder
here that is coming on here now one of
the things that we probably need to add
is which elements it is specifically and
there is that information in the trace
it's just a case of plumbing it through
so that's actually something that I'm
going to hopefully look at so maybe by
the time you see this video go and have
a look in Chrome Canary possibly we've
got the elements there if if not what's
doing the time are recording with
screenshots help so you can go through
the film strip and actually see
something shipped and that might be a
good way to work around that until dev
tools can yeah that's a great way of
doing it often I think when it's your
own code you have a fair sense of what's
likely to be moving around and the thing
to bear in mind is layout shifts do
cause problem are problematic UX and so
it's a good thing to try and get those
down and ideally removed if at all
possible and the way to do that normally
is to reserve space for your content
ahead of time in your style so that
you're not just leaving content to just
move other content of the way if
sometimes it's not possible but where
you can if you can mark certain areas as
being the correct size ahead of time
that should help
an awful lot so that's that's the layout
shift information so that's added in so
those are the main bits of performance
in summary we had the timings which are
here I've got the layout shifts and we
also had long-running tests which we
show on the main thread with the candy
striping and the red triangle so in dev
tools we have also been working on web
assembly and the debugging experience
that it gives you because your write
your code in whatever language then you
compile it to this vm bytecode and you
kind of don't want to step through the
bytecode you want to step through your
original code that you wrote and for the
longest time
webassembly in dev tools use source map
source maps to define that mapping from
the compiled webassembly binary code to
the original source code and source maps
were kind of built for JavaScript and
minifiers and transpilers and so that
worked quite well but it's also lacking
some capabilities that are quite
important and so I have little example
secret it's actually a sample from M
script that I just simplified a little
bit it just draws little gradient it
doesn't really matter what it does but
this is C code and I have compiled this
to webassembly with our new debugging
experience because in native lands in
binary land there has been a toboggan
format called dwarf for a very long time
that has all these capabilities but
until recently dev tools didn't
understand it so now we have compiled
this to represent Li this is what the
output looks like it just draws this
little nice gradient that you see on
screen here but what's cool about is
that now if you go to the source panel
in dev tools over here we have our usual
Java Script files we have a weapon
simply byte code which you know that's
not the kind of code you want to step
through I mean that's not because that
is base it's basically assembly well
that sometimes can be useful it doesn't
read that well let's be honest and what
you can now find with dwarf support in
dev tools is that we actually have a
mapping to the original C++ file again
this also worked with source maps but
this has some more capabilities so I can
now set a breakpoint here in the C code
actually I said let's let's set two code
as breakpoints why not and so if I
reload the program will be halted once
we reach that breakpoint and then we can
continue going through it as we're used
to and you can see the UI updating so if
I now step over this SDL unlock surface
the gradient shows up because we're
actually stopping the program and
updating the UI as we go along and I
think that's pretty cool
so now the question I have for you guys
is are you able to inspect say the
values of like I or J or alpha and those
kind of writers of your loop so for
example if I hover over this nothing
shows up and
that's exactly the capability that goes
for example I was also missing with
source maps because source maps can't
really handle renaming of variables very
well
dois forever can so while we are using
dwarf to have a more efficient debugging
experience and the capabilities our
potential but we haven't quite built
that part yet so we are using dwarf to
allow you the old experience of stepping
through and brake pointing and all these
things but you can try to expect inspect
variables yet but we are working on that
and only now is it even possible to
build so that's really the exciting part
here the other part is that we are no
longer using a web assembly interpreter
during debugging but actually our
baseline compiler so usually in the
olden days when you will start debugging
your weapon sembly with source maps you
will actually experience a much much
slower webassembly execution so if you
had a long loop and you want to break
through it you would actually have to
wait longer until it is done now we are
at the baseline compiler which generates
much more performant code under the hood
and so you can do debug with higher
performance and if that isn't the great
tagline I I don't know what is to be
honest so you've kind of pointed at this
I think a little bit this is
experimental it's still a work in
progress if somebody wanted to actually
try this out for themselves in Canary
what would they do where would they go
so it is currently in Canary and it is
still being worked on so in the last
couple days it kind of oscillated
between working and not working
sometimes I could set breakpoints
sometimes I couldn't but we are on track
for getting this ready for stable I
don't know if we've set a milestone yet
if so I will update the description of
this talk accordingly and but you're
gonna play around with it please do I'm
stripping if you just Google for M
scripting and dwarf the most recent
release now has support by default for
these Dwarfs of bugging symbols so if
you just update your engine to the most
recent release this shows just work out
of the box just to be clear there is no
source map file and the fourth that I'm
serving so source Maps cannot have
provided this debugging experience so
this is definitely using the dwarf
symbols that are in the web assembly
binary cool well with that
I think we have covered what is
important and new in Devil's Den we know
I've got more stuff to show you I've got
the issues you have more stuff to show
yeah
switch back well alright so the next
thing I want to show you is the issues
tab now you use similar your a similar
sameer thing when you see lots of
warnings and messages in the console
over here you can ago
sure and you start to kind of mentally
filter those out and you maybe if you're
like me you kind of clear the console
and you something okay it's just too
busy just too noisy I'll kind of deal
with those at some point well if you are
like that completely understand where
you're coming from so we've added this
new thing which is the issues tab it
says the issues have been detected so if
you see something like this we've
detected some issues during the
execution of your page and you can go to
the issues tab which opens a new tab
here now sometimes if the page is
already loaded in you you bring up the
console you might say well there's
possibly more information would you like
to reload so sometimes you get an option
to reload the page and you might see
more issues coming through that way so
you can see here that this particular
page some say same site cookies issues
are starting to show up so you can see
I've got the issues listed here and I
can spin this down and it gives me an
explanation of what's going on
and how I can resolve this issue
directly it also tells me which cookies
in this case are affected and also links
me off to some informational web dev
about how this all works it's also true
of something like mixed content as well
so if I go to something with mixed
content which is HTTP and HTTPS
together similarly I can go here and it
says that there are eight cases where I
have mixed content where all resources
should have been loaded via HTTPS but
they haven't been and it lists again it
lists lists the requests and the
resources in question so hopefully
that's going to make the console less
noisy and makes it much more clear to
you how you can track down any issues
that dev tools has noticed in
site and you're up okay so the last
thing I want to talk about is color
vision deficiency emulation so let me
fire up this brilliant video of HTTP
very second yeah talking about imposter
syndrome something I personally suffer
from so if you've not seen that go ahead
and watch it's a really good video so
what I've got on my screen I've got the
rendering tools inside of dev tools now
if you've not seen this you can go to
more tools and then rendering down here
if you click on that this tab will pop
up and there's a load of tools just for
rendering inside of here
and since we're passing through here the
layout shifts that I talked about
earlier in the performance area layout
shift regions this is a live update
version of layer shifts so if you're
just wanting to see very quickly what
they actually have during the you know
the life cycle of your page you can
switch this on and if you see blue
flashes then that's the layout shift
that would have been caught if you took
taken a performance recording now I'm
not going to show this today because as
it says here may not be suitable
suitable for people prone to
photosensitive epilepsy and I want to be
mindful of that but if you think this is
the right tool for you definitely check
that out
when you're looking in the rendering
tools so if I scroll to the bottom here
of this list you'll see that you can
emulate vision deficiencies and if I
start playing this video back you can
see that if we work our way through this
list we have blurred vision which you
see applies a blur to everything and I
can still interact with the painting
still click on buttons and so on but you
see the content is completely blurred we
also have protanopia and there is due to
an opiate triton topia and a chroma top
seer assuming I'm pronouncing those
correctly if I'm not forgive me I find
it really cool that all these effects so
to speak I applied to the page without
disabling the interactivity or the
animations or even the video so you can
really check if all your animation
entire experience holds up when someone
has one of these vision deficiencies so
I think that's just a really cool thing
yeah absolutely
so you might noticed so these are they
seem fairly extreme when you look at
this it looks to me as somebody who
doesn't have any of these vision
deficiencies these look like a very
extreme form of change visual change so
I mean I said this in the introduction
with Dion earlier but to say it again
these deficiencies that we're emulating
are physiologically accurate but the
most acute form of that particular
vision deficiency so it's not on/off
like we have emulated here where it's
sort of knowing no vision deficiency and
then protanopia if you have one of these
vision deficiencies it's much more
likely to be a spectrum and you may have
a certain amount of one of these vision
deficiencies so what is like this is the
most extreme version of all of these
vision deficiencies and so that way you
can make sure if your page holds up in
the most extreme case you know it will
also hold up for any less severe case
you can make sure your website remains
usable for anyone really that is exactly
the idea behind it exactly that if
you're optimizing for accessibility you
want to be as confident as you can be
that you're capturing the colors and the
contrast and all of that stuff in the
most helpful way possible and so by
going for the most acute version of
these vision deficiencies exactly as you
said you can you can optimize for those
and then anything up to and including
those will also be covered as well so so
that says we've talked about the issues
tab we've talked about long tests we
talked about layout shapes color vision
deficiency and whoever simply debugging
with dwarf I know right and ballast
quite a lot of new things and dev tools
and you should definitely try those out
absolutely yeah so if you want to try
any of these out probably the easiest
thing to do is to fire up Chrome Canary
give them a go if you run into any
issues you can go over here to the help
menu and you can report the dev tools
issue which will create a bug and you
can fill that in and that'll make its
way aka your inbox I really
not so with that thanks for watching and
I guess we'll see you around see you
around bye
[Music]