Hello and welcome to "Security and Privacy for the Open
Web". I'm Maud, and I'm a Developer Advocate for the Chrome
team recording from Berlin.
And I am Sam.
Coming to you live-ish from Tooting Bec
in South London.
OK. First, Sam, let's travel in time a
bit and understand what the "open web" means because the
web is open by definition, right?
Yeah. Well, I mean, sort of.
The web was originally designed to be open and
transparent. In fact, Tim Berners-Lee envisaged
the web as a kind of read/write medium.
You know, the browser would be an editor as much as a
reader.
And right from the early days, the limited scope of what
browsers could do helped keep them safe for,
you know, anonymous, stateless document rendering.
But then capabilities and expectations
grew. And, you know, we wanted to log-in and then
e-commerce and so on.
And then we got phishing, malware, man-in-the-middle
attacks and all the rest.
Yeah. So in response, you know, we've had
browser sandboxing, ubiquitous HTTPS,
protections against malicious sites, plugin deprecation,
and all that stuff, which is great.
However, some of the web technologies designed
decades ago aren't being used in the simple
way that was intended.
You know, it was difficult in the 1990s to envisage how
user agent strings and cookies would
be used beyond their intended capabilities
in the 2020s.
And this evolution in how some web
technologies are able to be utilized, paired
with the rising expectations from users to
have more control and transparency over their personal
data, has led the whole web ecosystem
to evaluate longstanding practices.
And now, more than ever, I think the web needs privacy
and security by default for all users.
I think we'll see an increasingly high proportion of people
on the web who've never used a browser before
or who are simply outside their normal browsing
habits. People may be looking for information
who may be in a crisis or just feeling vulnerable.
And I actually think these are the hardest, most complex
and most important problems to solve on the
web right now.
But of course, this is not easy.
Even in terms of user interface design.
For example, how do you make quite complex concepts,
such as cookie management, understandable
for billions of users?
Yes. So that's why users need transparency and control
in their browsers.
And it's not just browser features, right.
Web standards and defaults also need to change.
Yeah, that's absolutely true.
I mean, cookies, for example, and data such as
user agent strings that can be used for device
fingerprinting and to covertly track individual
users.
Also features such as the referrer header that
can reveal private browsing data.
As developers, we need to rethink the way we handle user
data. Do you really need all the data you access?
And is it clear to your users what you're doing with their
data?
Yeah, because like as a developer, you're actually best
placed to understand potential problems
and help fix them.
So, OK, let's run through today's sessions.
We'll be talking about security, privacy,
payments, and identity.
Yeah. First up, our colleague Rowan Merewood has
some recipes to help you manage your cookies,
whether or not you've heard about SameSite and changes to
cookie defaults.
If you're using any kind of third party content,
such as ads or you're doing anything
with cookies on your site, you should definitely check
out his session.
Second, thinking about the cross-origin web, you need
to prevent information leaks.
And that's where powerful protections like the COOP and
COEP policy headers come in.
To understand how this can protect your website, check out
the great session from our colleague Eiji Kitamura.
OK. So that's all nice.
But how do you actually debug that stuff?
Like SameSite cookies and COOP and COEP?
Well, the new Issues tab in Chrome
DevTools is there to help you.
The Issues tab makes it much easier to find and
fix problems instead of console message
clutter you get clear instructions
on how to fix problems.
So with this sessions, you'll learn techniques to not
passively leak your users' data.
And there's a pattern here.
Debugging is important, but how can you and your team
develop a mindset around privacy and security
and prepare for the future?
Rowan and I thought about this and put together strategies
with concrete examples of web APIs and HTTP headers
you surely know, to help you make sure you're using
just the data you need.
And speaking of user data, a crucial entry point
for this is the ubiquitous sign-in
form. And this is particularly important right now
when lots of sites need to be accessible to new
users.
Now, in my session, I'll show you how to use cross-platform
browser features to build a simple email/password
log in form that's secure, accessible,
and easy to use.
Just like the sign-in experience, you need payment
flows to be clear and safe.
So what's new in web payments?
Eiji Kitamura will guide you through this.
So if your website uses payments, make sure to check this
session out.
Okay, so that's it for the sessions.
But we'd also like to tell you about one really important
initiative that we're all involved with, the Privacy
Sandbox.
Now, more than ever, people need to know that private
data stays private.
On the other hand, people want to do stuff on the web
that's private and personal.
You know, you want to go shopping, use your bank online,
communicate private information and so on.
And keeping data safe can't just be
about constraints. We can't just say no to everything.
The problem is keeping your users safe is not just about
getting your own house in order.
It's not just about first-party interactions because
most web sites use services from other companies
to provide analytics or videos and do lots
of other useful stuff.
Most notably, ads are included in webpages via
third-party JavaScript and iframes.
And ad views, clicks, and conversions are measured
via third-party cookies and scripts.
But when you visit a website, you may not be aware of these
third parties and what they're doing with your data.
And actually, publishers and web developers themselves may
not have visibility on the entire third-party supply chain.
Ad targeting, conversion measurement, and other use cases
currently rely on stable cross-site identity.
Historically, this has been done with third-party cookies.
But today, browsers have begun to restrict access
to these.
Other mechanisms for cross-site user tracking are also
being used, such as covert browser storage, device
fingerprinting, and requests for personal information like
email addresses.
And this is a dilemma for the web.
How can legitimate third-party use
cases be supported without enabling users
to be tracked across sites.
In particular, how can websites fund content
by enabling third parties to show ads and measure ad
performance, but not allow individual users
to be profiled?
How can advertisers and site owners evaluate a user's
authenticity without resorting to dark patterns
such as device fingerprinting?
Well, this is where the Privacy Sandbox comes in.
And just to avoid confusion, this is not the
same as the browser sandbox architecture
you may have heard of though it does build on some
of the same ideas of keeping your data safe.
The Privacy Sandbox is a set of proposals to implement
privacy-preserving APIs to support business
models that fund websites in the absence
of mechanisms like third-party cookies.
Now the Privacy Sandbox supports five core
use cases for a world without third-party cookies:
measurement for ads and other third party content,
relevance features for advertising, fraud detection
distinguishing real humans from bots and spammers,
getting rid of covert tracking, and finally,
secure and simple identity management across
sites. So we need browsers to support
third party use cases in a future without cookies.
But whatever happens, users
need cookie security and choice right now.
So how did the Privacy Sandbox proposal satisfy third
party use cases?
So I'm not going to go into the gory details of every
single one of the Privacy Sandbox proposals here.
Shameless self promotion, but you really should
read our article "Digging into the Privacy Sandbox",
which outlines all the proposals.
But you know what we really need though is feedback
on the proposals.
In particular, to suggest missing use cases
and more private ways to accomplish their goals.
The Chrome team is responding to feedback on the proposals
on GitHub and in W3C forums.
And we really hope you'll join the discussion.
And this is especially true if you work for a publisher,
advertiser, or an ad tech company.
And if you have other questions, feedback, or ideas to
share on today's sessions, ping us on Twitter @ChromiumDev
with the hashtag #webdevlive.
Yeah. Thanks, Maud. And if you want to get in touch, we'll
be online to answer questions in the live chat
during the web.dev LIVE event.
Or you can just add a comment to this video.
So thanks for watching.
So let's get on with this.