If users ever need to sign into your site, good
sign-in form design is critical.
This is especially true for people on poor connections, on
mobile, in a hurry, or under stress.
Now, more than ever, you need to ensure that sign-in
isn't a barrier to using a site.
Poorly designed sign-in forms get high bounce rate.
And, you know, each bounce means a disgruntled user who's
likely to exit your site, not just a missed sign-in
opportunity.
But first, a disclaimer.
This video is about best practice
for simple sign-in forms that use an email address and
password. It doesn't explain how to use federated
log-in with identity providers like Google or Facebook,
or how to integrate with backend services.
You can find out more about those topics from the links at
the end of the article that goes with this video.
So in this video, I'm going to talk about straightforward
frontend coding best practice, mostly
HTML, with a little bit of CSS and some JavaScript.
I asked the Identity team at Chrome what I should talk
about. And they said, get the basics of
sign-in forms right.
So be warned, this is simple stuff.
It's not rocket science.
And before we start, a quick reality check, you know, do
you actually really need users to sign in to
your site? People don't like being forced
to hand over identity information, and all that personal
data and the code that goes with it becomes a cost
and a liability for you.
If people can use your site without signing in,
all the better. The best sign-in form is no sign-in form
at all. Anyway, with all that out of the way, let's
get on with it.
First up, well formed HTML is the
backbone of a good sign-in experience.
Use the elements built for the job.
They've been around for years: , , ,
and .
And as I'll show you, using these elements as intended
enables built-in browser functionality, improves
accessibility and adds meaning to your markup.
Your basic HTML might start out something like
this.
So let's break that down.
Now, you might be tempted to just wrap inputs
in a
and handle input data submission
purely with JavaScript.
Well, don't do it!
You know, it's just generally better to use a plain
old element.
This makes your site more accessible to screenreaders
and other assistive devices and helps browsers
understand the intention of your code to enable a whole
lot of cross platform standardized built-in form
features that I'll show you later.
An HTML form also makes it simpler to build basic
functional sign-in for older browsers and
to enable sign-in even if JavaScript
fails.
So, first things first.
To label an input, use a .
There are two reasons for that.
First reason: a tap or a click on a label moves
focus to the input it's associated with.
Second reason, screenreaders announced label text
when the label or the labels input gets focus.
Sign in, heading one.
Email with hint.
You associate a label with an input by giving the label's
'for' attribute the same value as the input's id.
Now, placeholders can be useful, but don't
use them as input labels.
People are liable to forget what the input was for once
they've started entering text, especially if they get
distracted. You know, was I entering an email address,
a phone number, or an account ID?
I can't remember!
There are other potential problems with placeholders.
And you can see the article that goes with this video
if you're unconvinced.
Now, it's probably best to put your labels above
your inputs.
This enables consistent design across mobile and
desktop, and according to Google AI research,
enables quicker scanning by users.
You get full width labels and inputs and you don't need to
adjust label and input width to fit the label text.
Some sites force users to enter emails or passwords
twice. That might reduce errors for a few
users, but causes extra work for all
users and can increase abandonment rates.
I think it's better to enable users to confirm their email
address, you'll need to do that anyway, and make
it easy for them to reset that password.
Next. Use for buttons!
Button elements provide accessible behavior and
built-in form submission functionality and they
can easily be styled.
There's no point in using a
or some other element
pretending to be a button.
Give the submit button in a sign-up or sign-in form a
value that says what it does, such as "create
account" or "sign-in".
Not "submit" or "start", or whatever.
Considered disabling the sign-in button once the user
has tapped or clicked it.
Many users click buttons multiple times, even
on sites that are fast and responsive.
That slows down interactions and can add to server
load.
Conversely, don't disable form submission awaiting user
input. For example, like, don't just disable the sign-in
button if something's missing or in the wrong format.
Explain to the user what they need to do.
This is a real example. I was urgently trying to sign-in to
a site, and there was no way of knowing what
I was doing wrong.
Now that HTML code I showed you before
is all valid and correct, but
the default browser styling means it looks
terrible and it's hard to use, especially on mobile.
The default browser size for just about everything to do
with forms is too small, especially on mobile.
This might seem obvious, but you know it's a common problem
with sign-in forms on lots of sites.
In particular, the default size and padding for inputs
and buttons is too small on desktop, and
even worse on mobile.
Here you can see the various minimum guidelines for target
sizes. On that basis, I reckon you should add
at least about 15 pixels of padding to input
elements and buttons for mobile and around 10 px
on desktop. But don't take my word for it.
Try this out with real devices and real
humans. And also make sure to provide enough
space between inputs.
Add enough margin to make inputs work well as touch
targets. As a rough guide, that's about a finger
width of margin.
You should comfortably be able to tap each of your inputs
and buttons without bumping into something else.
You also need to make sure your inputs are clearly visible.
Now the default border styling for inputs makes them hard
to see. They're almost invisible on some platforms, such
as Chrome for Android.
So add a border.
On a white background, a good general rule is to use a
#ccc or darker. Or change the background color
instead. I mean, whatever you do, make it blindingly
obvious where to tap or click.
And remember, design for thumbs.
If you search for "touch target", you'll see lots of
pictures of forefingers.
However, in the real world, most people, many people use
their thumbs to interact with phones.
Thumbs are bigger than forefingers, and control is less
precise.
All the more reason for adequately sized touch targets.
Now, as with form control dimensions and padding,
the default browser font size for input elements and
buttons is too small, particularly on mobile.
Browsers on different platforms size fonts somewhat
differently. So it's difficult to specify a particular font
size that works well everywhere.
A quick survey of popular websites shows sizes of
around 13 to 16 px on desktop.
Well, matching that physical size is a good minimum for
text on mobile.
And that means you need to use larger pixel sizes on
mobile, generally. 16 px on Chrome on desktop
is quite legible, but even if you have pretty
good vision, it's difficult to read 16 px
text on Chrome on Android.
Lighthouse can help you automate the process of detecting
text that's too small.
Now let's talk about visual indicators for validation.
Browsers have built-in features to do basic form
validation for inputs with a type attribute.
Browsers warn when you submit a form with an input
value and set focus on the problematic input.
You don't need to use JavaScript!
Use the :invalid CSS selector to highlight
invalid data.
This is really widely supported by browsers
and for more recent browsers, you can use
:not(:placeholder-shown) to avoid selecting
inputs with no content.
Okay. We've touched on elements and a bit of CSS.
Now I want to talk about attributes.
This is where the magic really happens.
Browsers have multiple helpful built-in
features that use element attributes.
So let's take a look.
Add an 'autofocus' attribute to the first input in your
sign-in form. That makes it clear where to start.
And on desktop, at least, it means users don't
have to select the input to start typing.
Password inputs should, of course, have type="password"
to hide password text and help browsers understand
the meaning of the input.
Using also means that browsers,
such as Firefox, offer to save your password
when a form is submitted.
As I'll show you, browsers also used the 'name' and
'id' attributes to work out the role of form
inputs.
Use to give mobile
users an appropriate keyboard and enable basic
built-in email address validation by the browser.
Again, no JavaScript required!
If you need to use a telephone number instead of an email
address, enables
a telephone keypad on mobile.
You can also use the 'inputmode' attribute where necessary.
inputmode ="numeric" is ideal for PIN numbers.
But watch out!
Using type="number" adds an up/down arrow
to increment numbers.
So don't use it for numbers that aren't meant to be
incremented, such as telephone or PIN numbers.
And while we're talking about keyboards, unfortunately,
if you're not careful, mobile keyboards may cover
your form or, worse, partially obscure the sign-in
button.
Users might get confused and give up before
realizing what has happened.
Avoid this where you can by displaying only
the email, phone, and password inputs
and the sign-in button at the top of your sign-in page.
Put other content below.
Now, I know, this won't be possible for every site,
but whatever you do, test on a range of devices
for your target audience and adjust accordingly.
Some sites, including Amazon and eBay, avoid the
problem by asking for email, phone and password
in two stages.
Now, this approach also simplifies the experience; the user
is only tasked with one thing at a time.
So, next up: the 'name' and 'autocomplete' attributes.
These are a really powerful way for you to help browsers
help users by storing data and autofilling
inputs.
There are two parts to this.
The input 'name' attribute enables browsers to
work out the role of various inputs so that they can
store email addresses and other data for use with
autocomplete.
So don't make the browser guess.
Some browsers, including Firefox, also take note
of the 'id' and 'type' attributes.
When the user later access as a sign-in form
on the same site the 'autocomplete' attribute
enables the browser to autofill inputs using the data
its stored using the 'name' attribute.
Now you need different behavior for password inputs in
sign-up and sign-in forms.
Don't add autofill to a password input in a sign-up
form. The browser might already have a password
stored for the site, and auto filling a password just
doesn't make sense on sign-up: for example, if two people
share the same device and one wants to create a new
account.
Use the appropriate password input 'name' to help the
browser differentiate between new and current passwords.
Use name="new-password" for the password input
in a sign-up form and also for the new password
in a changed password form.
This tells the browser that you want it to store a new
password for the site.
Use name="current-password" for the password
input in a sign-in form, or the input for the user's
old password in a change-password form.
This tells the browser that you want it to use the current
password that it has stored for the site.
Different browsers handle email autofill and password
suggestions somewhat differently, but the effect is
much the same.
On Safari 11 and above on desktop, for example,
the password manager is displayed and then biometric
authentication - fingerprint or facial recognition -
is used if available.
Chrome on desktop displays email suggestions
depending on what you type, shows the password manager,
and then autofills the password.
Now, here's another reason to use
autocomplete="new-password".
Modern browsers suggest a strong password
if that's included for the password input
in a sign up form. Use built-in browser
password generators.
That means users and developers don't need
to work out what a strong password is.
Since browsers can securely store passwords
and autofill them as necessary, there's no
need for users to remember or enter passwords
and leave them on sticky notes attached
to the computer.
Add the 'required' attribute to both email and
password fields.
Modern browsers automatically prompt and set focus
for missing data.
And I'll say it again - no JavaScript required.
So, I've talked about the basics of getting
HTML and CSS right, but you're also going to need some
JavaScript.
Make sure to add a 'show password' icon or text
button to enable users to check the text they've entered.
And don't forget to add a 'forgot password' link.
Here's
how Gmail does it. It's really straightforward. You add a
listener
to your button and in the handler toggle the password
input type to text or password.
Make sure to include an 'aria-label' to warn that the
password will be displayed. Otherwise, users
may inadvertently reveal passwords.
Speaking of accessibility, use 'aria-describedby'
to explain password constraints, using the element
you use to describe your password requirements.
Screen readers read the label text, the input type and
then the description.
Now you'll also want to validate data entry
in real time and before submission. HTML
elements and attributes have built-in features for
basic validation, but you should also use JavaScript
to do more robust validation while
users are entering data and when they attempt
to submit the form.
Just bear in mind that this does not obviate the need to
validate and sanitize data on the back end.
The sign-in form code lab that goes with this
video uses the Constraint Validation
API, which is widely supported, to add
custom validation using built-in browser UI
to set focus and display prompts.
Okay. One really important extra thing.
'What you cannot measure, you cannot improve'
is particularly true for sign-up and sign-in
forms.
You need to set goals, measure success, improve
your site and repeat.
Usability and lab testing are really helpful for trying out
changes but you also need real world data
to really understand how your users experience
your sign-up and sign-in forms with analytics
and Real User Measurement (or Monitoring).
You'll need to monitor page analytics, including sign-up
and sign-in page views, bounce rates, and
exits.
Make sure to add interaction analytics such as goal
funnels. Where do users abandon your sign-up or sign-in
flow? And events - you know - what actions
do users take when interacting with your forms?
And lastly, track website performance:
use user-centric field metrics to understand the
real experience of real users.
Are your sign-up and sign-in forms slow to load, and, if
so, what is the cause?
And finally, some general guidelines to help reduce sign-in
form abandonment.
Number one: don't make users hunt for the sign-in!
Put a link to the sign-in form at the top of the page,
using well understood wording like "Sign-in", "Create
Account", or "Register".
Keep it focused. Sign-in forms are not the place to
distract people with offers and features.
Minimize complexity.
Ask for other user data such as addresses or credit
card details only when users see
a clear benefit from providing that data.
Before users start on your sign-up form, make clear
what the value proposition is.
How do they benefit from signing in?
Give users concrete incentives to complete
sign-up.
If possible, allow users to identify themselves with
a mobile phone number instead of an email address.
Since that's the way some users want to
do it, they may not want to use their email.
Make it easy for users to reset their password and
make the "Forgot your password?" link obvious.
Make sure to link to your Terms of Service and Privacy
Policy documents: make it clear to users from the start
how you safeguard their data.
And finally - finally - include branding for your
company or organization on your sign-up and sign-in pages.
Make sure your fonts, styles and tone
of voice match the rest of your site.
Some forms just feel like they don't belong to the
same site as other content.
Especially if they have a significantly different URL.
So there you go. That's the basics of sign-in form
best practice.
You can find out more from the web.dev article that goes
with this video, and the code lab that goes with that.
I hope that's given you a few items to add to your next
sprint to improve your web site's forms.
Of course, sign-up and sign-in is not the only
place that involves a lot of form filling that could be
improved. So stay tuned for Eiji,
who's going to talk through some of the new options for
payments on the web.