Hello and welcome. My name is Stephen Fluin.
I'm a Developer Advocate on the Angular team here at
Google. My job is really fun because I get to help
developers be successful with Angular.
And I get to spend a lot of time listening and engaging
with the community, so we can reflect your needs onto the
team. One things that we learned, having worked with a lot
of developers across the world, is that staying up
to date is really, really important.
And so today's talk is all about how to keep your
application as fast as possible and as fresh as possible
using Angular. We're gonna be diving into some of the best
practices that you should be following as an application
developer. And we'll take a look at live code and see how
you can actually go in and debug and build your application
out. So let's actually gets started.
So if we take a look at we've got here, this is a
application that I've built using the Angular CLI.
So it's a very, very basic application that should look
very, very familiar. It's basically we ran "ng new" and we
installed something called Angular Material.
And so if you take a look at the AppComponent, I've put in
an app dashboard. And so if we ran a command like "ng
serve", what we would see is a normal
dashboard of an application that's coming from Angular
Material. So we've got a few dependencies installed.
We've got a few other things installed and all that should
just be coming to you kind of automatically.
So here we go. This is just the default blank dashboard.
And so even though we haven't written a ton of code, we've
got the application up and running and it's pulling in
a ton of code, right? We're pulling in the features of
Angular necessary for these animations, for these menus,
for these dialogs, as well as for all of this content
around this dashboard that a user could interact with and
engage with. And so the first thing I want to do in order
to make my application fast as possible is I really want to
understand my application. And so we're gonna make a couple
changes within our build configuration in the angular.json
file. So what we're gonna do is we're gonna find the
angular.json file. You're gonna find this directly in the
root of your application.
And what we're gonna do is we're going to find in the
Production Build settings, we're going to change
two settings here.
We're going to say a sourceMap. I'm gonna change that from
false to true, as well as in our
namedChunks, we're gonna turn that on to true.
What sourceMap does is this will actually take my
application and map all of the generated JavaScript
that comes out of the build and map it back into
the code that that JavaScript came from.
So if some of the generated code came from Angular
Material, we'll see that. If it came from Angular itself,
we'll see that. And we'll even see things like the
generated JavaScript being mapped back to my HTML and
into the application code that I'm writing for all the
components that I'm creating.
So source maps are really great way for you to understand
what's going on in your application and the relationship
between what happens in the code you write in the IDE and
the code being delivered to your users.
And so there's a lot of steps that we end up taking along
that way, right? There's the angular compiler that takes
that HTML and turns it into JavaScript.
But there's also other steps that we do, like optimizations
where we'll change some of the property names.
You've got bundling so that we get all of this JavaScript
coming down as a single kind of cohesive bundle that makes
sense to browsers. And so sourceMap allows us to follow
that path, follow that process, and give us really good
insights. And so what we can do is, having made these two
changes, we can actually now go and run the ng
build --prod.
What that will do is that will create a production build of
our application, which is normally what you ship down to
browsers. But because we've turned on source maps and we
turned on namedChunks, we'll actually see the JavaScript
and be able to analyze those chunks.
And so we're also going to using another tool today called
source-map-explorer.
There's a bunch of other tools out there that developers
use to analyze bundle size and chunk size.
But we on the Angular team actually really strongly
recommend that you only use source-map-explorer because
other tools out there like webpack-bundle-analyzer that
categorically misrecognize some of those steps within
our process. And so we've done that production build, and
now whenever you want to actually take a look at what a
source map looks like, we can just run source-map-explorer.
If you don't have this installed, you can just install it
globally: "yarn global add source-map-explorer".
Or you can install it local to your project.
Whichever makes sense to you, just go and do that.
What we'll do is we'll run source-map-explorer,
and we will pass it in the JavaScript file that we
want to analyze. And so we can see it, we've got our dist
folder here and we're gonna look at the es2015
version of our JavaScript.
So if we run that, it's gonna pop up in a web browser, and
we're going to see this visual interactive story about
our applications. So we can see our overall bundle size, in
terms of minified but not compressed, JavaScript.
So it'll actually be a little bit smaller when it goes over
the network. We have about
452 kilobytes of application.
And what's really, really helpful here is that you can see
where that bundle size is coming from.
So you can see animations is 64 kilobytes
and your material is about 56 kilobytes.
We've got things like HTTP where we might
not actually need these things. And we might not even know
that they are in our bundle. We might have forgotten at
some point along the way. So you can see I'm pulling in
forms and HTTP.
If we actually go into our application, now that we know
that those things are there we can say, "Hey.
I don't actually need that for this dashboard". Right? Like
we're not - if we look at the content I'm showing you,
there's no form data here. There's no data coming from the
internet. And I can go into my AppModule and
I could pull those out. Okay? So I'll just comment these
out because we don't need a HTTP or forms.
What should happen is when I do my next production bundle,
all of that code is going to be left out.
So we're going to be able to see that our bundle size will
come down from around 450 KB to a little bit less
than that, which is really, really nice. And it should
actually be exactly leaving out the size of the HTTP bundle
and the size of the forms bundle.
And so source maps are one of the best tools in your
toolbox. And we really recommend that every developer be
using source-map-explorer.
Using this on a regular basis to understand your
application, especially when you're doing any sort of
performance optimization.
Now, let's say that you are looking at your bundle and
you're saying it's still too big, but I need all of those
features. I need all of those capabilities.
Fortunately, the Angular CLI offers a lot of really smart
capabilities. One of those capabilities is being able to
take an application and build out lazy loaded modules.
And so let's actually go ahead and do this.
And so I'm going to use the CLI here and I'm going to say
"ng", which is the Angular command.
And I'm gonna say "generate module", and I'm going to give
it a root module that it's going to connect
back to. So what we're gonna do is we're gonna create a
separate part of our application where we can pull in
features that we need and just leave all of that code
outside of the main bundle. And so we're going to generate
a module here and I'll just link it back to the module
known as App Module, which is the root of my application.
And now I'm going to give it a route.
And so what this does is it automatically wires up this
module to be lazy-loaded whenever a user hits that route.
And so we'll just make, for example, an about page.
And so it is going to do it's going to generate a module
called "AboutModule".
It's gonna be able to route to it and then is gonna give me
an AboutComponent.
So we can see all of that in our source code.
So it's just close all these files and we're gonna see
it created a new About folder with our new
module and our new code.
And so if we do another production build,
what we'll actually see, because we
turned on namedChunks, we'll actually get out now, not
only a main chunk, a MainModule, we're
also going to get out an AboutModule.
We can see and independently verify the size of that
module and independently verify what the
dependencies of that module are doing to the overall bundle
size of our application.
And so what you'll see is that by default, an Angular
module is really, really small. It's very, very thin.
It doesn't add a ton of bundle size your application.
It's almost always the dependencies that you are pulling in
as a developer, the features that you are reaching out for.
And what Angular will do is, intelligently based on the
where you do the imports, will lazy load and split
that code. So if you remember, we pulled HTTP and forms
out of our main chunk, we can actually now pull that in.
And so you can see we've generated a - Let's just
clear this out. Let's take a look in our dist folder here.
You can see we've got a main chunk and now we've got
this nice new AboutModule.
And so you can see in the es2015 version our AboutModule
is only about 1.1K of code.
So it's just that AboutComponent because it doesn't have
any dependencies. But if we add back in more dependencies
into that chunk, if we wanted to pull in, for example,
Angular Material into that AboutModule, then it's going to
pull in that code. But it's going to do it very, very
intelligently. It's going to lazy load all of that code.
So if you haven't set up lazy loading before, it's really,
really easy. Just generate a new module with that command
that I showed where we generate a module and we hang it
onto the routing structure of our application.
All right. Next up, I want to talk a little bit about what
happens after we build an application, after we've been
building it out and we've added more and more features.
It's very, very easy to backslide.
One of things that the Chrome team has seen consistently is
that even applications that spend a ton of time building
great performance into their apps tend to backslide because
we as developers, we want to add more features.
We want to push more functionality to our users.
And that often comes with more dependencies, which
sometimes we don't realize is negatively affecting our
bundle size. And so one of the features that's built into
the Angular CLI is called "bundle budgets".
And so, again, if we go back into our angular.json.
So we'll just search for that.
We can see this nice little budget section.
And what this does is it allows you to set several
different budgets for your application.
By default, we give you two out of the box.
We give you an initial budget.
So this is the JavaScript that it takes
to load the initial page of your application.
So right now, we are warning at
2 MB. So we'll see a warning as part of our build if our
application is over 2 MB.
And our build will actually error out if it's more than 5
MB. And so those are very, very conservative defaults.
We recommend you turn those as small as you can to really
just give yourself a knowledge of when you're increasing
your bundle sizes. It's a conscious choice rather than an
accident. You'll see we also have a few other types of
budgets, including any component style.
So what this says is that any scoped styles to a component,
we want to keep those under 5 KB.
And we are going to error out if they become above 10 KB.
And there's a few more that you can see if you just take a
look in your IDE.
You've got allScript, so that's just the total sum
of all the scripts in my application.
AnyScript are any individual scripts shouldn't be bigger
than this. The whole bundle overall, all those sorts of
things, so we've got a whole bunch of different features
that allow you to really take control and understand and
prevent bundle size increases.
So that's a really, really helpful tool.
So those are some of the top things that you should be
doing to keep your application as fast as possible.
But one of the best things you can do
that doesn't take a lot of work is actually staying up to
date with Angular.
So if we jump back to the terminal here, what we'll see is
that I actually created this Angular application on an old
version of Angular, it is running version 8.
So version 8 is not the latest version.
Version 9 as of this filming is the latest version and
version 10 is coming out.
But it's always the same. So if you're on an out of date
version of Angular, your bundle size is going to be bigger
and slower than it needs to be. Because what happens is
over time, every time we do a release, the Angular team is
looking at what can we do better?
With the release of version 8, we actually made a huge step
forward by automatically doing something called
Differential Loading where because we have this opinionated
control of the entire toolchain, we understand
how to make your production bundles.
And so what we did is we said, "Hey, modern browsers
are capable of loading JavaScript differently than legacy
browsers that don't support something called ES modules.
And so using that knowledge, you can actually conditionally
force modern browsers to load modern JavaScript
and legacy browsers to load legacy JavaScript.
And this is a really nice schism that allows you to
have two bundles that really gives you the best of both
worlds. Where you can ship the smallest, fastest JavaScript
to modern browsers that support the most recent
capabilities like classes, like modules, all those sorts
of things. And you can leave an older legacy
bundle for browsers that don't have that kind of support.
So we actually did this out of the box by default.
So you notice when we were doing those builds, we were
actually getting the two JavaScript bundles
for each of the files. So we had about-module-es2015.js and
we had about-module-es5.js.
And so, again, this is one of the changes that the Angular
team did behind the scenes without having to make you
change any of the code in your application.
And this is something we do every single release.
And so what we're gonna do now is we're gonna make our
application as fresh as possible so we can update to the
latest version of Angular and we're gonna automatically get
more improvements to our bundle size.
This is something that just happens every time you keep
your application up to date using Angular.
And so we're going to again, use the @angular/cli command
and we're going to use "ng update".
And we're going to update our application in a couple
stages. First, we're going to update the Angular
core packages. So core and the core
package, as well as the CLI package.
And then what we're gonna do is we're going to go and update
our dependencies. So we're gonna do it as two steps to make
sure that we don't accidentally enter a mistake or an error
where our application is no longer compatible with one of
those dependencies. So let's go ahead and get this started.
So I'm going to run "ng update" and what we're gonna do
is going to pass it angular/cli and angular/core.
Now, if you were on an even older version, what we do is we
recommend that you go one version at a time just so we can
apply things cleanly.
And if you want to do that, for example, if you are in
version 6, you want to go to version 7, you just say "@7",
and that will just do it for you. But we're gonna go all
the way from version 8 up to version 9, which is the
latest. So I'm going to run this command and
theoretically things should work.
There's a few places where this might fail.
If your repository isn't clean, then what should happen is
we're gonna throw this warning, which is what we're seeing
right now. "Repository is not clean, please commit".
Because what we want is we want you to have a very clean
history so that you actually know what the Angular update
process did, because this isn't like a normal "ng update"
where we're just modifying the node modules of your
project. We're actually making changes to your application
so that you stay compatible with Angular.
And the reason we're able to do this is because the Angular
team at Google, we have thousands of projects across
Google that are not run by our team that are using Angular.
And it's actually, according to Google policy, our
responsibility for keeping those applications working as we
make breaking changes to Angular. And so, and only way that
we can scale is at Google is to build really great
automation and really great tooling.
And so what we did is we baked that same sort of tooling
into the public world, into this "ng update" command.
So whenever we need to change a method name, whenever we
need to deprecate something, we're going to try and update
your application as best we can.
And so that's why we always make sure that you want to have
a clean history. So we'll just "git add" everything.
Commit that, and now we should be able to run our update
command.
So, again, what's happening behind the scenes?
It's going to be downloading and installing the latest
version of Angular CLI and then it's going to be updating
the packages in application and changing my code where
needed. And so if there's any sort of migrations what
should happen is while you're doing the update process,
it's going to report what migrations it's doing.
So you can see in your workspace migration, so it made a
few changes to the workspace layout.
So you can see it updated my angular.json file, it updated
my tsconfig.app, it updated the package.json.
And so it's making all of these migrations, even ones that
don't really have any changes to my app.
It's still double checking all those things so that we know
that my application is going to keep working.
Now, there's a couple other places that you can look for
the latest information.
You'll notice here at the very, very bottom of the update,
it actually says "for more information, please see this
link". And so we actually have guides on what changes we're
making behind the scenes with every version of Angular, so
you can know about things like deprecations.
You can know about things like removals and changes to the
way that the APIs work.
On the other one that I want to point you out to would be
update.angular.io.
So behind the scenes, when you ran "ng update", we made a
lot of changes to your project. And so, if you actually
wanted to see what you need to do, you can just go to the
update guide. And you can say "show me how to update".
And we'll say, "Oh, make sure you're on the latest version
here. Make sure using this version of node".
It walks you through the changes that are going to affect
you as a developer. And you can even tune this based on the
number and amount of features and the depth and complexity
of your usage of Angular.
Because most applications don't care about all of
the changes we're making under the hood. But let's say you
have a large application, you have several hundred
components. You have component libraries.
You're using things like Universal.
You can check these boxes.
And what we'll do is we'll show you all of the information
about the update, all of the changes we're making behind
the scenes. So you can have a full, complete understanding
what's going on. And the other way you can do it, is if you
just take a look at the git history, you can now go in and
see what all the changes we made were.
So, for example, when we move to version 9, we turned on
ahead-of-time compilation by default.
So that's gonna make your build a lot faster.
You can see that we've installed all the dependencies.
And not just on Angular, we've also installed things like
rxjs to the latest version.
We've updated your components so that they actually
continue working as we make changes to Angular.
So this is really, really powerful.
And then we can actually do a test to see if this works.
Let's just run "ng serve" and we can say, "Yes,
let's let Google Analytics track some of our CLI usage
anonymously".
And what will happen is when we return back to the browser
window, we're gonna get the latest version of Angular and
our app is generally just gonna keep working.
And then the way that this really affects you is not only
keeping you up to date as a developer, making sure using
best practices, but again, it's also going to improve the
performance of your application.
One of the things that you're going to see is
every time we make an update to Angular we're trying to
look for ways to making your more tree shakeable, to make
your build system better.
And so there's lots of experimentation, lots of ideation
going on there because the state of bundlers in JavaScript
are not static. Webpack keeps getting better, Rollup keeps
getting better, terser keeps getting better.
And these tools are changing, and they're evolving and the
way that they relate to each other is changing.
And so what we do is as the Angular team, we're trying to
stay on top of that for you.
And so let's go ahead and refresh.
And if we take a look in the DevTools, we should see we are
now on the latest version of Angular so 9.1.9 at the
ready. But whenever you use "ng update", it's just gonna
move you to the latest version. It's gonna do that
automatically for you so that you are staying up to date.
Staying fresh. Staying fast.
So once you've updated Angular and you've updated the CLI.
Now what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go and update all the
other packages. So if you take a look, for example,
we did not in our package.json, we didn't update
the CDK or we didn't update @angular/material.
So we're going to do one more "ng update" command
to update @angular/material and @angular/cdk.
You can do with any of your dependencies.
A lot of dependencies are starting to support these
automatic migrations. This is something we've been pushing
very hard for in the ecosystem.
Let's just run that "ng update @angular/material
@angular/cdk" command again.
And again, it's fetching the latest version of those
packages. It's updating their dependencies in your
package.json. And then it's going to execute any migrations
that you need to be on the latest version.
And I think we're just going to run "ng serve" one last
time and we will see that our entire application kept on
working and our bundle size should have gotten a little bit
better. Then again, it's doing a little bit of compiling
ahead of time. Generally, this is a temporary thing that
you're going to see with Ivy and with version 9, so we do
this extra compilation.
That's really to offer the latest version of Angular and
the latest features of Angular while still staying
compatible with the rest of the ecosystem.
So this is just a extra compilation step the Angular
team does to optimize things.
All right. As soon as this completion is complete, what
we're gonna see is we're going to be on the latest version
of Angular. And again, we updated the package.json.
So just all the dependencies, including removing
things like hammer.js and our application should just keep
working. Yep. There it is.
We have a great
dashboard, just like we had before right in the beginning.
Everything works, everything animates.
We're now on the latest version of Angular.
We're now in the latest version material and the CDK.
And our application is as fast as we can be because we're
budgeting. We're making sure that we're understanding our
application, making sure it doesn't grow over time.
We're analyzing the application bundle size with source
maps. And we're doing things like lazy loading so that we
only make users pay for the features that they're using at
the current time.
That's going to be it for us. Thank you so much for