Hey, I'm Maud.
Hey. And I'm Rowan. Now, over the past couple of videos,
there's been a pattern where the changes we've been showing
you have been to reduce cross-site data transfer
by default.
And because some of these changes restrict existing
behavior, you need to take action if your site relies
on that cross-site functionality.
So instead of just a list of features, we wanted
to give you a little framework for thinking about them,
both for now and for the future.
So we've brainstormed then finally distilled that down
into three questions you can ask yourself and your team.
And we'll be running three examples, but first, let's take
a look at the raw questions.
One, do I need this data?
Now, there's definitely a developer temptation to think,
just collect all the data. It might be valuable later, but
that's not really the right attitude anymore.
Right. And you're opening yourself up to more risk if that
data leaks. You've got more regulations to follow and
it's just more work.
So the lazy option is just don't.
Don't collect it, no risk.
No work.
Mm hmm. So we can sum this up as more
data, more problems?
Yeah. Onto the next question.
Question two, then: is there an alternative?
There are so many options there, so it depends.
Some things like site preferences might be better
in client-side storage, like IndexedDB or LocalStorage,
so you can still sync them with the server, but maybe
you don't need them on every single request.
Yeah, and there might be places where the query parameters
in the URL make more sense, if it's related to how the
content displays, because then if I share a link with
you, you get the same options that I have.
Sometimes cookies are the right answer, though,
so question 3: have I secured it correctly?
Oh, I know this one.
Watch my video from earlier.
Yeah, yeah, okay Rowan, okay - but let's do a summary.
So, first-party cookies should try using
the __Host- prefix so they're Secure and single-origin,
they should use HttpOnly to stop JavaScript
access, and they should set SameSite=Lax to
protect against cross-site request forgery.
And if they do need to be third-party, then try and do the
same, but with SameSite=None and Secure.
And that's it.
Cool. I feel good about this.
I think if you're asking these questions, you're headed
down the right track.
We should repeat these a few times, though, like good
scientists to see if it works with different topics.
Good idea. I might even have a topic I could talk about
right now.
Yeah, me too.
Okay, you go.
OK, first test drive of these questions then - we're
going to take a look at the User-Agent string.
Now, the original specification for this back in 1996
was pretty simple. It was basically a browser version,
library version and so on.
However, nearly a quarter of a century later, that
string has grown a bit.
If you want to successfully parse this, then you need a
whole bunch of regular expressions or a library
that hides them from you.
On top of that, the information about your browser and
device in that string can be pretty identifying.
From my string here, which is being sent on every single
request, you can see the exact build of Chrome,
the phone I'm using, the version of Android it's running.
Now - especially with less common devices - this
could be enough to track someone.
While we would eventually like to reduce the amount of data
exposed there, those 25 years of growth have meant that
there's a lot of genuine and valuable use cases out there
for the User-Agent string and maintaining backwards
compatibility on the web is what means that your modern
browser can still show you those 25 year old sites
successfully.
Right. Let's run the questions and see if it helps us.
Number one: do you need it?
If you're using the string to try and determine feature
support or capabilities, then it's far better
to use feature detection, progressive enhancement, or
responsive design to achieve those goals.
That means you don't need to maintain a mapping between
browser version and whatever feature you're checking for.
It also means you're less likely to exclude less common
browsers just because you couldn't match the string.
Question two: is there an alternative?
When I mentioned valid use cases before, some of those
examples might be matching the user's OS so you can show
appropriate downloads or match the UI conventions.
You may also need to work around browser bugs where the
specific browser version is the key bit of information
you need to know if it's been fixed or not.
For this, I want to introduce you to Client Hints, and
specifically the new set of User-Agent Client Hints.
Essentially, the idea is we could go from broadcasting
all of this information by default to a model where the
site asks the browser for each piece of info and
the browser decides what it wants to return.
With User-Agent Client Hints the default data shared
on each request is the browser name, significant version,
and the mobile indicator which comes in on these Sec-CH
headers. If you want something extra like the OS
platform, then your site needs to ask for it.
It can do this by sending an Accept-CH header
in its response asking for platform.
Then, on subsequent requests, the browser will send a
Sec-CH-UA-Platform header back.
You can also do this in JavaScript by calling
getHighEntropyValues() on navigator.userAgentData
and passing 'platform' as a parameter.
There's one of these User-Agent hints to cover each of the
bits of data that you can get from the string - so full
browser version, platform version, device model, CPU
architecture, on top of the significant version
and that mobile indicator.
But wait, there's more.
There are also existing Client Hints that can give you
things like device memory or viewport width.
Because even if you're getting the data in the right way,
it's easier to ask directly for the thing you want
instead of using User-Agent as a proxy.
OK, third and final question: have you secured it
correctly? For the User-Agent Client Hints they are by
default restricted to the same origin.
If you have other cross-origin or cross-site requests on
that page that need the Client Hints - let's say your
downloads are hosted on a separate origin, so you want to
send the platform hint there - you need to specify
each of the hint and origin pairs in a Feature Policy
to allow them through.
Now, eventually, we'd like to reduce the amount of
information exposed by default in the User-Agent string.
So ideally, if you can migrate to User-Agent Client Hints,
then that should absolutely be your route.
However, if you cannot, then try to be flexible
in your detection.
This kind of string parsing is inherently fragile - so
feel free to warn me that I might get issues with my
browser, but don't block me just because my string
didn't match your regex.
And there we go: User-Agent, one, two, three.
Done. We've got a lot more info on
web.dev but let's keep this rolling.
And do another round. Maud, over to you.
Thanks, Rowan!
Now let's look at our second test drive of these questions
to see how they work, using an example that's also
an HTTP header.
It's called the Referer.
You'll see it written with either one or two R's.
Don't be surprised. This is due to an original misspelling
in the spec.
Imagine that a user is visiting a page on site-one.
And to load an image, a request to site-two
is sent. In some cases, site-two can see the
full URL of site-one the user is on in the requests'
Referer header, which might be present in all types
of requests: navigation or subresource.
And this info is not just present in the header.
It may be accessed on the destination via JavaScript.
The Referer can be insightful.
For example, for analytics to know that 50%
of visitors to site-two were coming from socialnetwork.com.
But full
URLs can contain private data and even sensitive
or identifying details, especially the path and
query string. And requests sent
from your websites might include these details.
So, onto question one: do I need this data?
First, incoming requests.
Sometimes, like on this diagram, the Referer is used
to extract the origin to see where the request came from
or whether its the same origin.
But the Referer contains way more data than you need to
answer these questions.
If you're doing this, you're using it as a proxy to find
answers. And this is more work for you.
So, we'll look at alternatives in a minute.
Second, outgoing requests.
If there is no compelling reason for your web site to share
full URLs cross-origin, then you shouldn't.
We'll see how.
OK, on to question two: is there an alternative?
Yes.
First, incoming requests.
Back to what we said. If what you need is just the origin,
the Origin header gives you exactly this and it's
available in POST and CORS requests.
And if what you need to know is whether the request is
same-origin, you can use the Sec-Fetch-Site
header. Also a side note, if you're using the Referer
as extra protection against
CSRF, then replacing it with this or
Origin is great, but make sure that you're
using CSRF tokens and maybe SameSite as
a primary protection.
Now let's talk about outgoing requests.
Is there an alternative to sending the full URL in
all requests?
Again, yes.
Luckily, websites can control how much data is sent in
the Referer by sending a specific Referer-Policy.
And depending on the policy, either no referer
at all, the origin only, or
the full URL will be sent.
Back to our web sites.
Suppose you want the full URL, for example, to
understand how users are navigating within your websites.
This doesn't mean that you have to send the full URL in all
requests.
What you can do instead is set your Referer-Policy to
strict-origin-when-cross-origin.
It shares the full URL for a same-origin requests
like here on this diagram, but only the
origin in cross-origin requests.
Also, it's a safe policy because if from
your HTTPS websites, a request to an HTTP origin
is sent, the Referer will be stripped.
Which is good, because you don't want to leak URLs
on an unencrypted connection since anyone in the network
can see these, right?
And quick segue.
If you don't set a policy, the browser's default policy
will be used. And to have your back, browsers
have switched to or are experimenting with
more privacy-preserving default policies.
For example, strict-origin-when-cross-origin, the
policy we just talked about.
You can already try this out.
So check the article in the video notes for details.
OK, on to question three: have I secured it
correctly? strict-origin-when-cross-origin is
good, but maybe you can't set this for your whole web site
because of some specific use case you might have.
In this case, don't fall back to an unsafe policy
altogether.
What you can do instead is take a case by case approach.
For example, set strict-origin-when-cross-origin
as a general policy for your website and
a more lax policy on specific elements or requests
if need be. You need to pick a policy that
fits the level of sensitivity of the data and
maybe you have a cookie recipes websites, but
maybe you have a health care web app and the topic in the
path is sensitive.
Or some of the URLs contain user identifying
information.
On the whole, don't share the Referer to a third party
unless it's strictly necessary and transparent
to your users.
And, one last thought, data that might not look
sensitive or identifying can bring one
more piece to the puzzle and be more revealing than you
think.
So that it for the Referer.
And I think we're through.
So, Rowan, you want to wrap up?
Thanks. Yeah.
OK. Wow. That was a lot of topics in one session.
As always, we've got the links included so you can read
more on this. To close then, when you're reviewing data
usage, whether that cookies, User-Agent, or
Referrer or anything else, what are you going
to ask yourself?
One, do I need this data?
Two, is there an alternative?
And three, have I secured it correctly?
Speaking of needing data, though, what have we got next?
Oh, smooth transition.
So you definitely need data at sign-up and sign-in,
so you got to do these forms right.
And Sam's going to explain how to improve sign in
and sign up forms on your websites.
And we'll see you around!