Hello, mate!
Hello!
This is like remote 203, isn't it?
It's good.
It's, yeah, it's weird.
It's like so we have almost all the technology that we need
to make this work without feeling different
but it's still different.
We'll let other people be the judge of that.
If it works or not.
That's true.
So I'm here to talk about image compression.
It's something I've been wanting to talk about for a long
time, right?
I mean, we wrote an entire app around it.
We did. And we are gonna be seeing that as part of this
talk.
Nice, I like it.
If you look at the studies they do across web pages, like,
images are the biggest thing on the page.
50% around about of each page is just -
50% of the bytes that go over the wire for any given page
are on average images.
Yeah. And sometimes for fun I'll go and take just like some
images from a web page and like recompress them.
And usually I can half the size of them without losing
any of the visual fidelity.
So it's just like so much stuff on the web could just be
compressed better. Either by using a different format,
a better encoder, or just like better settings within
a particular encoder.
Yeah, that's what I found as well.
I recently had a little experiment and felt like even
without like going into like the very
deep settings of an encoder, often
people just don't optimize their images at all.
And just like doing the default setting in Squoosh will
already give you a really decent compression
rate without losing visual fidelity.
So if you're watching this at home, if you're the kind of
person who just like saves your images out of Photoshop for
the web, then this is the talk for you.
Cause I have things to discuss because I think you're
missing out on huge performance gains.
So I want to dive into image codecs.
I want to show how they work, and I want to explore some of
the lesser known settings.
So here are the formats.
Right. We've got lossy JPEG, and WebP.
We got lossless, PNG, GIF, and also WebP.
Hang on, my friend. Hang on.
You put GIFs under lossless?
They are lossless.
But they're 256 colors?
Yes, but you make that change before compression.
Like the GIF compressor won't accept images more
than 256 colors.
So that's a step you have to run before the compression.
It's lossless. Trust me.
Fine.
Because we are going to do the same for PNG as well, but
I've got a question for you.
If you have a digital drawing,
like a drawing that's been created on a computer, which
format would you use for this?
If at all possible, SVG.
Yep, I agree with you because, in fact, it can be any
resolution, so it's ideal for drawings.
But sometimes the drawing is really complex,
so they're actually smaller and much faster as a lossless
image.
But then again, if the drawing has a lot of gradients and
shading, it might actually be smaller and acceptable
in a lossy format without it looking bad to the user.
So a lot of talks and articles I see about like image
compression, they try and bucket kinds of images into
formats. And I think that can be misleading.
So instead instead, what I want to do is on a talk about
what these formats actually spend their bytes on.
Yeah.
So lossy of images, it's like sharp
edges. They really struggle with that.
That will that will increase the size of the image.
And also small details in undetailed
areas. That's, kind of, that sounds confusing.
So we'll look at a few examples of that in a moment.
For lossless, it's color change, especially unpredictable
color change. It's another thing we'll look at some
examples of that.
And also, total number of colors impacts the file size as
well. With vector, number of shapes and also shape
complexity.
There's a little difference with
vector, and that's the complexity of the shapes will
actually introduce a CPU cost in the way it doesn't with
the other formats. So that's, that's something to bear in
mind. That's the TL;DR of this talk.
Really. That's it.
Done.
Well, thanks for doing this and I'll see you next time.
Bye bye. No, no.
I want to get to know these codecs in detail.
I'm going to dive in.
Well, just to be clear, these are categories of codecs,
as you say. Like each of these categories has multiple
codecs to offer.
And I think the basic advice should be that you just
try the same image.
Like, if you don't know which category your image falls in
just try the image in all of these codecs.
That's kind of the ideal process, right?
Yes. But you can make some educated guesses based on your
knowledge of how these things work.
So Surma, have a look at this.
I know this is difficult because you're watching this over
WebRTC, so these demos are slightly limited.
Do you notice anything about this picture?
Yeah. If it's not the stream compression, then
I'd say the clouds have blocky
artifacts, going about.
I think that is just stream compression.
Ah OK, then let's try this again.
When you say notice, do you want me to find something that
is wrong with the image or just something
that should help me make a guess on which codec is best for
this?
Well, I'll tell you what, if you haven't noticed it
straight away, then that's good enough for me.
So if at home, if you're watching this in full HD,
that's 1920 by 1080 - obviously, you're getting
video compression on top of that, so you're not seeing
exactly what I'm seeing - but this picture, the
brightness data is full HD 1920
by 1080, but the color data in this image
is 96 by 54.
That's 0.3%
of the data and you barely notice
it. Closer, you can start to see a bit discoloration
around some of the fencing.
One of the fence posts was turned into a ghost.
Yeah, like, if you have that little resolution for the
colors, the colors will start bleeding across boundaries,
even though the light data still gives the contour.
So that's -
really...yeah.
And this is because you've got but eyes Surma.
Like, you have these terrible human eyes that are really
bad at seeing changes in color, but you're actually pretty
good seeing changes in brightness though.
So I'm going take this image and I'm going to flip it
around so that the brightness detail is low resolution, but
the color detail is high resolution.
And here it is.
And the first thing you'll notice is it looks
bad, but it is the same amount of data just flipped
around.
Here, it looks fine.
You can't go this extreme in all examples.
So here's a image that has a bit more
complex data around color.
You can see this yellow stripe and the red stripe on the
car. It's like there's some details, quite blocky.
But as we start increasing the amount of color data, again,
it becomes difficult to notice. With this image, once
I get the color data to around 5% of
the brightness data, it becomes impossible to notice for
me.
Now, I can build a little webapp to research this.
Of course you did.
This first is the first WebGL I ever wrote,
Surma.
Oh, you did it with WebGL. That's fun!
Yes. To do the color conversion.
So it's something you can - I'll put a link to this so you
can throw your own images at it. You can get some cool
effects. You can see the individual color channels because
this is what lossy codecs do.
They call it chroma subsampling it rather than RGB,
they do brightness and then two chroma channels, two
color channels. And that means they can just discard loads
of that color data and save a lot of file size
as a result. As you mentioned earlier, you get some color
bleeding as a result, but it's barely noticeable,
especially in like, photographic imagery.
One more thing that lossy codecs do in
terms of lossy stuff - it's another quiz for you, Surma.
I've made an alteration to this image.
Can you see what I have done?
There is a very ominous circle between the trees.
Yes. I've drawn a circle in the sky.
There it is. But that's not all I've done.
Down here, I've replaced the brightness
data with noise.
Just noise.
But you don't really notice that at first.
And here's the interesting thing.
Here's a diff of the image versus the original image.
Now, the circle in the sky
is so subtle, it barely shows up.
In fact, if you are watching this with video compression,
it might not be visible at all.
I can't see it right now.
But the noise in the in the bottom there, it's like a huge
difference.
But again, you have terrible human eyes.
You're good at seeing small changes in what we call low
frequency areas, like the sky, there's not a lot going on
so you spot that small difference.
Whereas you struggle to see the changes in the high
frequency.
This reminds me a bit of the
blind spot that we have in our eyes where our brain fills
in the gap for us because I see the circle.
And you showed me the diff, and faded back to the
full image, I saw the circle and then the shape of the
circle started blending into the environment.
And now it looks like a bush like, I know the circle is
there, but I can't actually quite see it.
So I think it's just my brain autocorrecting and I'm quite
frustrated with my brain for doing that.
It does. And this is something that lossy image codecs
like, they take advantage of this.
So what they do is they'll take an image like this and
they'll divide it into eight by eight blocks.
And rather than describe these blocks pixel by pixel, they
use this. They multiply these shapes together
to form exactly the same image.
Like, not at that intensity.
Each block can be at a different intensity.
It can even be negative.
But you can reconstruct any eight by eight image
using these shapes.
And this blows my mind, like I don't believe this.
I still don't believe this, even though I built an app to
show it.
Look, I've made a little pixel art 203, for HTTP 203.
I'm not very good at pixel art, but that's what I tried to
do here.
But what you see below is all of those shapes at
the intensity that it uses to reconstruct that image.
So we can actually sort of apply them one by one.
And you can see as it does the low frequency things, it
starts to build up like this blurry picture.
And then as it goes and starts to do the high frequency
bits of data, the full image comes into view.
It's incredible to me that this actually works, but it
does. Doesn't save much data, really.
But let's actually take a real bit of the image.
This is the picture of the woods from before.
I'm going to pick up some of the grass.
Now, what lossy codecs will try to do is they'll try and
discard some of this data.
So you see already it's not using all of those shapes.
That's where these zeros are coming from.
But as I dropped the quality and this is like,
jpeg quality in this case, we can see more and more
of those zeros appearing.
And the thing about sequences of zeros, they compress
really, really well.
So we're left with an image that isn't 100% accurate.
But this is high frequency data, you don't really notice
loads of data are saved.
I mean, even here in the side by side view, it is
hard to tell which pixels are incorrect.
Exactly.
But let's take a different example.
So this time a curve, which might be part of like a logo or
something. And in this case, even a very small
drop in quality is introducing noise that is very
noticeable, especially if the color is solid on either side
of this curve. That's low frequency data.
This small amount of noise is really noticeable.
It's like the circle in the sky.
Right. It's - you'll see it very, very easily.
And that's why, like, lossy compression is not very good
at sharp lines next to solid color.
So now if you look at a picture like this, which is a
heavily compressed jpeg and zoomed in, you can see
like what it's made of. You can see the color bleed from
the subsampling. You can see the eight by eight blocks.
You can see those waves that it's using to construct that
data. And that's it, you now know how lossy compression
works. There's only two elements of loss in both JPEG
and WebP, and that's it.
You've seen them both now.
I have a question because I'm trying to remember
WebP, I think, also does
this frequency based transfrom - discrete cosine transform,
as it's called, the conversion to this frequency patterns
and you add them up.
And no, yeah that's, that's yeah - that's what we just saw.
Yeah.
And I think WebP does it also at bigger
block sizes. If the - if they are low noise,
but I'm not quite sure I remember correctly.
Yeah. So WebP is just better.
So this is a few of things. Like you say it can use
different size squares. It can also, when it starts
a square, it can use a nearby square as a starting point.
Also, JPEG has to use the same
mathematical conversion for every eight by eight block
in a given channel.
Right.
Whereas WebP can you can have four.
So it could have a different strategy for like high
detailed areas versus low detailed areas.
And it has a better lossless compression thing as well.
Uses arithmetic compression rather than Huffman.
And it has better post decode filters as well.
So it is just better.
It also supports alpha transparency as well, which JPEG
doesn't.
So why have I wasted my time talking about JPEG?
Well,
Safari does not support WebP, it's the only one browser
that doesn't.
So that's the only benefit of JPEG.
Really.
We can still use WebP for browsers that support it.
This the picture element, so we're serving WebP for
browsers that support it and falling back to JPEG for
Safari and older browsers.
There are also client hints to do on the server side.
I'm not going to go into it. I'll put some other - some
links for that, if that's what you want to do.
So let's actually compress some images.
Now, the compression tools and things like Photoshop are
not very good, which is one the reasons that
we built this - not just us two,
it was part of a team. But yes, squoosh.app.
This has the latest WebP build.
Also has MozJPEG, a really good JPEG encoder from Mozilla.
So I'm going to use the F1 image from before,
because it was a bit of a tricky one to compress.
First thing I'm going to do is zoom it out.
So it's the same size as it will appear on the site.
So if you've got an image that's gonna be a thousand CSS
pixels wide, but you want to look good on a high density
screen, you want a 2000 pixel wide image.
But then you want to zoom it back out, so it's the size it
will actually appear on the screen.
Now going to start with WebP in terms of compression and
all I'm going to do - I think you mentioned this before -
just bring the quality down until it looks bad,
you know. And especially with a high density image
like this, you will be surprised how low you can go
on the quality, like, it's still really barely noticeable.
Now, it's really tempting to do
this, but please don't like, don't put your nose to the
screen. Don't zoom in, because
if you do that, it will look bad.
It's not going to look good. Right.
The more you zoom in, the worse it will look.
Oh, look at that. That's disgusting.
But honestly, so considering that we are at
- that we just removed 98% of
the data and it still looks that good
even when zoomed in. It's kind of cool.
Yeah. Absolutely incredible.
So if anyone comes at you and says, like, oh, I took one of
the images from your website and I zoomed in by a thousand
percent and it looks bad like, just say
"OK, zoomer", and ignore them, because that's
not what real users are going to do, and you should be
optimizing things for real users.
So keep it roughly the size it will be on the site.
I actually wanted to look into some of these advanced
settings in WebP because when we first built Squoosh, I
didn't know what these did. I just took the codec did and
made a UI for it.
There's a lot of it - but, I now know what they do.
I did some research.
The really interesting ones: auto adjusting the filter,
this is a good thing to do.
This really slows down the encoding time, but
it improves the visual a lot.
Now that the filter is actually a decoding filter,
it's just what it's going to do to remove that blockiness.
But it increases the encoding time because it tries to
figure out by looking at the image what the best kind
of filtering is going to be.
But, yeah, it's just it's just a one bit flag or not one
bit. A couple of bits.
Three bits, I guess, if there's eight levels of filter
sharpness.
Yes, exactly.
I think that might should be more.
I think, I think it might actually go from zero to 100.
But so it's probably a byte. The other one
that I always knew, Oh, this makes a big change to the
image, but I don't know what it's doing. It's a spatial
noise shaping.
Now, like I said, WebP can have these 4 different
strategies...
Did we- did we misspell spatial?
\h
thing is I've actually spelled it wrong in my notes for
this video as well.
Well, that's a bug report.
Yeah, so anyway. So the other option is spatial noise
shaping.
And so WebP can have these different strategies for
different parts of the image. SNS, what that does is it
changes the extremity between
those different strategies.
So higher SNS takes bytes away from the stuff that least
needs it and gives it to the stuff that needs it most.
It's like Robin Hood for image compression, basically.
In some images, turning that up to 100 has a positive
result. It doesn't here, 50 is actually a pretty good,
pretty good for this image.
Can you go too high?
And like going higher makes the image worse again?
Yeah. So with this image, it does go
worse.
Interesting.
So if I, if I make it extreme here, it's giving
more data to the road because that's where the blockiness
is. But it starts to introduce like,
it makes the tires of the car look bad.
I see.
You start to notice that the artifacts that - you start to
-because it's taking data away from high frequency area,
giving it to low frequency.
The image of the woods that I had on before, it
- actually SNS of 100 works really, really well because it
takes lots of data away from the leaves and stuff that you
can't you the noise and gives it to the
area of the sky. So it works really well.
We're gonna need a JPEG as well.
So just for fun.
I'm going to make the JPEG the same size as the WebP just
to show the difference in quality of the compression
here. So I have to take - the same again - quality right
down til it's about forty kilobytes.
I'm going to do what I said not to do.
Okay. This looks pretty bad to my eyes right now at this
level. But obviously with video compression, it might not
be as obvious so I am going to zoom it in.
JPEG creates this horrible, blocky effect across the road.
And like I said, this is low frequency data.
So this is going to be like the circle in the sky.
It's a super obvious.
Around the yellow strip, the cut, the transition from the
yellow strip to the road makes it really obvious where
the data's lost.
Yeah, you can see the blockiness there.
And this is where the filtering that WebP does is
much better. So, yeah, I just have to increase the size of
the jpeg until that horrible blockiness just goes away.
And at that point it's like double the size -
over double the size - of the WebP.
There are things you can do to improve it if you wanna
spend the time.
More advanced settings.
The most interesting advanced setting here I think is the
chroma subsampling.
Yeah.
This is what we discussed before.
Right. This is just reducing that color data, especially if
you're on a high density screen. You can get away with
less. In fact, most of time I would say you can just turn
it up to four. We saw earlier that this particular
picture is kind of sensitive to color reduction.
So three was it was a good one, but it knocked 10KB off so
that's worth having.
I also often combine it with the separate chroma quality
so that you can basically introduce the blockiness into
the colors but not into the brightness, which is much
less [inaudible].
Interesting. I've never had success with that.
I've always - I've tried that and I've never - I've
always been unhappy with the results.
But yes, like mileage may vary.
The option is there. So people can play around with
that.
Absolutely.
But, yeah, I think it's worth in this case, to serve both
the WebP and the JPEG because it's like half the size for
the browsers that support it.
But that's it. That's everything I really had to say about
lossy images.
Well, you said you had major research about the options.
What exactly is pointless spec compliance?
Pointless spec complaince removes the
progressive encoding and
some of the other things that according to a strict
interpretation of the JPEG spec, it's not
supposed to do that, but everyone supports it and it's good
for file size.
I thought I would totally put you on the
spot, but you actually know the answer. Well done.
Well I didn't research the JPEG, but that was one of the
ones I knew from looking into the encoder there.
So lossless - completely different world.
A lossless image describes pixels one at a time
from top to bottom, left to right.
But rather than describe each color from scratch,
it will use some of the surrounding pixels to make
a prediction and then it just encodes the difference.
There's a number of strategies that it can use.
It can look at the pixel to the left, it can look at the
pixel above. It can use an average of
some of those pixels.
But here's the gotcha. It can't change the strategy for
every pixel because that would just add too much data.
Instead, it has to stick with a particular strategy
until it decides to change strategy.
Now, PNG can only change strategy
at the start of a line. WebP can
define 2D blocks of different strategies.
But this is why lossless compressers can be really slow,
because it's just brute force going through all of these
different strategies to figure out which one is best.
Like trying all the combinations, but it means this
compression works really well.
If the pixel next to it is exactly the same or the pixel
above is exactly the same, because there's no difference,
then really easy to compress.
And it's why lossless format struggle with photo data
because there's lots of organically changing color.
Oh, one more trick that losless things have.
If there's 256 colors or less, it just
sticks those in a table and it can reference them by
number.
So rather than every time describing the red, green, blue
and alpha, it just says, its color number five, everyone.
There it is, pop that in there.
And that compresses really, really well.
So difference between the formats then.
WebP not many people know about the lossless
WebP format. It's like a completely different codec.
In fact, it is a completely different codec.
The only relation between the two is when you do lossy WebP
with an alpha channel. It's using the lossless format for
the Alpha Channel. Pointless fact for you all.
Oh, that's good to know.
Yeah, it is - it's just better.
It's got more strategies, it's got the 2D thing going on.
It compresses better.
But you do need the PNG for Safari and
that's all we talked about. And just never use GIF.
Just don't. Stop it, please.
Never use it. It's just - it's bad at everything.
It's just bad.
So stop using GIF for everything.
But let's put this into practice.
Back in Squoosh. This time I'm going to use something with
a lot of flat color.
And I say thanks to Stephen Waller, who donated me some of
his artwork to use here.
He's an artist I used to work with.
He makes these wonderful drawings.
Apparently, these are his teammates that he worked with at
the time. I didn't ask him about the bear, but
fair enough.
I would say the first thing to do here - same as before -
zoom it out. Like, keep it the same size as it will appear
on the site.
So the kind of scaling that you would actually use to use
the high density devices.
And now I'm just gonna go to use WebP because it's
the best, I'm gonna pick Lossless.
Yep. Completely different codec, whatever.
Very few people know about it, but it's really good.
We're straight down to 43K.
This is a slight loss option which I found very
funny. It's great isn't it.
What it will do is change the pixels to try and make them
more predictable.
I actually don't like the visual effect it introduces, but,
so I don't really use it.
But your mileage may vary.
It's fun to play with.
But remember when I said earlier that these formats do
really well with 256 colors or less?
We're going to do that. We're going to reduce the palette
down.
It doesn't look like this image has a lot of colors, but
because of the anti-aliasing around all of the curves, it's
got lots of like slight variations, blends of one
color to another.
I've also changed the codec to browser PNG, and that's just
cause it's really fast to compress.
So it's going to be - I'm going to get a quick response
when I'm changing the number of colors.
I'm also going to turn off dithering.
If you reduce the number of colors of something, you can
get this banding effect that you can see here.
Dithering like tries to remove the banding by
using like pointillism or like these
dots to kind of recreate the shading.
It's super effective, but lossless deals well
with flat color so it will increase the file size, so
I would avoid it unless you really need
it.
I have compressed a couple of, like, photographs to
PNG with dithering and it'll actually look -
if you zoom out and have it's small enough - it will
actually look almost the same.
Often it's imperceptible.
Yeah. And there are some times that you need to do that.
So now the same as before. I'm just going to reduce the
colors as much as possible until it looks
bad.
And this is why this one the reason we built Squoosh,
because it's like, it's so much
nicer to do this with a visual response than getting
like a computer to try and figure it out because it's not
going to do it as well.
I'd say important advice - same as before - don't zoom in
because it will look bad.
You know that you can see the harsh edge here.
But zoomed out, you barely notice it.
So it's fine. And that's how users are going to see it.
So there we go.
So we've been able to like, reduce the colors like down to
68. And so now if we're gonna go
to switch back to
WebP, turn the effort up, let it use all of its iterations
to figure out the compression.
And like, boom, there we go.
It's like 13K.
It's amazing.
Isn't it? like it's incredible how much that saves.
For Safari, we need the PNG.
PNG compressors are really varied.
So we use OxiPNG, which is a pretty good one.
And that will take it down to what, 17K?
It's a close second, pretty good.
It's close.
And I would say I would give a shout out to ImageOptim
which ships with OxiPNG, but also lots of other PNG
compressors that we would like to add to Squoosh at some
point. But we haven't yet.
And it brings the file size down even more.
In fact, it's only 3K off the
WebP. So in this case, I would probably not bother.
Unless I had like a load of images on the page, and that
difference adds up, I would say just serve the PNG.
It's fine, 3k is not worth the complexity.
So, yeah, rather than think of a compression format for a
particular kind of image.
Like my take away is like think about how the compression
actually works and use that as your
first guess. But as you said earlier, it's always worth
trying it in something else. So I'm going to look at a
couple of edge cases to finish up on.
Look at this. Look at this.
This is beautiful.
This is SVG.
I was going to say, it looks like one of these things that
the CSS artists build was just like a billion divs
and gradients and shadows.
And then a photorealistic thing turns out to just be
CSS.
It's pretty much what is happening here; but with SVG.
I think this was manually created.
Yeah. Very similar. If I minify it in SVG OMG, which
is a SVG compression GUI I made, but
it's based on SVGO, which is a node
app. I get it down to 37K.
But this is so complicated and uses so many filters, like
look at the jank there on the resizing.
And this is on a high end MacBook. It is taking a ton of
CPU to render that image.
So over in Squoosh, lossy WebP
does a really good job of this like 53K.
It's actually bigger than the SVG.
But the saving in CPU makes this a better decision.
And that's actually interesting because that's something
that Squoosh doesn't really allow you
to quantify, right?
The saving in the CPU.
Yes, exactly. Yeah.
It'd be nice if we could find a way to do that somehow.
But yeah, if it's struggling in
- with this image, you notice how slow it loads and
you notice in SVG OMG how slow it is to resize, so
that's a good signal.
The PNG equivalent - because can't use JPEG for this
because it's got alpha transparency - the PNG is 86K.
And I've had to reduce the colors and that introduced a lot
of banding, so I had to introduce dithering.
And that's actually noticeable.
You can see the dots.
It's not great, but without the palette reduction, it's
300K. So in this case, you would kind of say,
I'm sorry, Safari users, you don't get quite as nice
an image, you know.
Yeah, but it's worth it for the file size.
Although I guess you could also serve the SVG because - I
mean the picture element, you specify the sources
in order of priority.
So you could put the WebP first, and could put the SVG
second?
Yeah. You could decide like to say, well you know, Safari
users are likely to be on a high end device, so the
SVG is less bad maybe.
But it's still going to cause jank to other things on the
page. You know, it is like -
on a high end MacBook it's bad. But yes, you could make
that judgment call.
You can say the jank is better than the 300K or the
banding or whatever.
One more example I'll leave you with.
This is another one of Stephen's drawings.
It has a lot of flat color. So my instincts for this would
be to go for a lossless format.
But there's also a lot of shadows, a lot of gradients as
well. So, again, lossy WebP does a really
good job of this. Like it takes it down to 28K.
If you go for a lossless format, even with the palette
reduction, it's 118K and you actually get a lap banding
with it. So, yeah, it's like tools,
not rules. That's my take away from this.
Like think about the codecs in terms of what they are good
at. Think about how they work.
And with that, go and make your images smaller.
Please, please make her images smaller.
I've actually enjoyed this. This has been like - should we
do some more 203s like this?
Should we do some remote 203s?
I don't know when we're gonna get back to the office.
I was planning to. Absolutely.
Well, we've got the equipment, so let's do it.
Happy. Next time.
Happy next time.