Hello there. My name's Rowan, and I want to chat to you
about cookies. Like most delicious things, cookies
are great in moderation, but too many of them or
messing up the recipe...That's bad news.
OK, so what are we going to chat about?
Two bits. First, a good HTTP cookie recipe
for all occasions.
And second, how to work out when your cookies are going
wrong. Debugging, essentially.
Because discovering bugs in cookies?
Gross. We'll worry about that later, though.
First, let's get the recipe right.
We're going to start with a base that comes from Mike West,
who's really one of the head chefs of the cookie world.
This cookie recipe should be your starting point.
Everything else we do is going to be a variation on this.
So let's take a look at it.
It's a lot. I know, but it's mostly static.
If you set this up as your default configuration, so
it's just added automatically, your code still remains
as clean as "set a cookie with this name and this value".
And all of these attributes or ingredients come with
benefits. So let's step through them first.
That "__Host" prefix.
Now, that's actually going to set up a few rules for us.
It's enforcing these first two attributes: "Secure"
and "Path=/".
"Secure" means that this cookie will only be set or
sent over HTTPS connections.
If you haven't fully migrated your site to HTTPS, now
is really the time to make that a priority.
Browsers are getting more and more functionality behind
HTTPS and being more explicit in communicating
to users that plain HTTP isn't secure.
Now "Path=/" is interesting.
And we need to look at that along with another attribute
that "__Host" is enforcing.
But in this case, enforcing that it is not included.
And that's "Domain".
No "Domain" means the cookie uses the current document
origin and does not include subdomains.
And "Path=/" means that it's sent for all
requests to the origin.
So if I set a __Host cookie for example.com,
it will go on every request to example.com, but
not to images.example.com.
There you go, that was three-in-one.
"__Host" prefix gives you "Secure", top-level "Path" and
no "Domain".
Next up is the "HTTPonly" attribute.
This means that the cookie will only be sent in request
headers and is not available to JavaScript via
document.cookie.
To clarify, you can trigger requests from JavaScript
like fetch or XmlHttpRequest.
And if you've specified including credentials, cookies,
including HttpOnly cookies will be sent.
They're just not visible to those client-side scripts in
any way. So in the event that any of those scripts on
your site have been compromised or malicious, you've at
least limited their access to potentially sensitive cookie
data.
Finally, a personal favorite.
It's SameSite.
Specifically, "SameSite=Lax".
And what "SameSite=Lax" does is restrict the cookie to only
be sent on requests that match the current browsing
context. In other words, the top level site
the user is currently visiting and is right there in that
location bar.
Putting that all together, we have a nicely contained first
party cookie.
This is an ideal cookie for controlling your user session,
set by your server-side framework.
And let's talk about why.
What this gives you some pretty reasonable protection
against cross-site request forgery.
The attack works like this, let's say you have a blog where
users need to be signed in to post content.
And that content submission is just a form submission or an
API call.
If one of those signed in users visits a malicious site,
it can trigger a request to that content posting
endpoint with some kind of spammy or abusive content.
If the cookies aren't protected, the browser may well send
them. And when the blog server receives that request,
it's going to look like it came from the signed in user.
And it's going to post that content with their name
attached, but not with our cookie recipe they can't.
"SameSite=Lax" is what's protecting us against this attack.
The malicious site can make the request, but because the
user isn't actually on the blogging site, the site
is no match and therefore no cookie.
There are some other benefits too.
The "Secure" attribute means that we're going over HTTPS,
so other people lurking on the same network can't steal
our cookie. Look up Firesheep if you want to see
how someone created an extension to demo just how easy this
kind of session hijacking over HTTP was.
Next up, HttpOnly.
Like we said, that means the cookie can't be stolen by
malicious client side JavaScript, like a third party
dependency getting hacked and then included on your site.
Now let's talk about tweaking this recipe for your own
taste. If the "__Host" prefix is too restrictive,
like maybe you have a new site and you've set it up with
subdomains for each topic like "finance." and "politics.",
but you still want one session across all of those.
For that, you could use the "__Secure" prefix instead
and specify "Domain".
So far, these examples don't have any kind of expiry date
set on them. That means they expire when the browser
session ends. Which sounds short, but in
reality, a lot of people leave their browser open for a
long time or I have a session restoring feature
that also brings back all those cookies.
Now, there isn't a default right answer here.
It's down to your use case.
But what I would say is if it's something short term,
like a token for a form submission, then use "Max-Age".
Since you just specify the number of seconds until it
expires. Nice and simple.
If it's something more permanent, like a theme preference,
then use "Expires" and set it maybe a year
in the future.
I wouldn't use it for anything short term because it's a
date format. So you have to think about time zones, clock
changes, incorrect clocks.
It's it's a nightmare. I'm not even gonna show you that
one. Remember, you can always reset that
expiry date on future requests, but then if
the user doesn't visit your site for ages, you can also
ensure the browser cleans up for you.
And that just seems polite.
No one wants stale cookies.
We can also use the "SameSite" attribute to lock things
down a bit more. But it's really for quite specific
situations.
We talked about "SameSite=Lax", which allows cookies to be
sent on top-level navigations.
For example, I want my session to be sent when I first
visit the site because I want to see my signed-in
experience. "SameSite" can also be set to "Strict".
Which means I really have to be on the site already
or the cookie won't be sent.
This is useful for protecting form submission.
So that blog posting example?
If you set up a "SameSite=Strict"" cookie.
Pretty much the same as your session.
But you treat it like a token for "write" permission
and validate that it's included on that form submission.
Then you can be pretty sure it came from the user
submitting the form actually on your site.
Sometimes you do need that cross-site data, though.
Now, while the long-term goal is to stop supporting
cross-site cookies and bring in better mechanisms for
enabling that functionality.
We can still do some interim work to clean up those cookies
right now. The really important thing is that
you make the intent to send that cross-site data
totally explicit.
For that, we can turn the "SameSite" dial the other way
with "SameSite=None".
That tells the browser that there are no "SameSite"
restrictions and it can send the cookie whenever.
It does require "Secure" as well, though.
No restrictions on "Site" doesn't mean no restrictions
at all. Now, even if you don't like the default recipe,
I strongly recommend you move to setting an explicit
"SameSite" value on your cookies.
Chrome is moving to treat cookies as "SameSite=Lax"
by default for Chrome version 80 and up
with the release of Chrome 84 Stable.
That's around July 14th, two weeks from this initial
broadcast date. If you're watching this on the Premiere or
even sooner, if you're already watching this in the future.
or in the past. Anyway, the important thing is
cookies without a "SameSite" attribute will be treated as
"SameSite=Lax".
In other words, first party by default.
If you need cross-site with third-party cookies, they
must be set with "SameSite=none" and "Secure".
OK, so that's all simple enough for me to say, but
I know a lot of you are maintaining legacy or complex sites
where, to be honest, you don't always know
how or why those cookies are being set.
Told you were going to talk about debugging, so let's do
it.
First. Let's get our environment setup, starting with the
browser. Cookies are persistent, meaning that you've
probably got a lot hanging around in your browser.
On top of that, browser settings and extensions
can also affect their behavior.
Because of that, I strongly recommend testing with a clean
slate. That means either setting up a new profile
using a separate Chrome channel like Beta or Canary,
or use incognito mode across all of those, though.
Make sure that you don't have any extensions installed.
And check your user settings to ensure you're not blocking
third-party cookies or just blocking cookies in general.
Now, we can make sure the browser is enforcing the new
behavior. I'm going to pop
in chrome://flags
here and what I'm going to do is
search for cookies.
Now, the two that I want to ensure are enabled are
"SameSite by default cookies" here and
"cookies without SameSite must be secure" here.
There are a couple of other messages in here, a couple of
other flags that you can set. So if you look through, you
can also see this one "enable experimental
cookie features".
Now, what this will do is turn on all of the upcoming
changes. So this is actually great for general
testing. If you just want to check that, you know, your
site can behave well in the future.
But when you are trying to isolate individual bugs,
you can use the individual flags to toggle that behavior
on and off. Now, when you've changed a flag, you are
going to have to restart your web browser here
so that those flags take effect.
Now, I already have restarted and I have a test
site set up on samesite-sandbox.glitch.me.
And if you've got all the flags enabled when
you go there, you should see all this nice, soothing green.
Any red or orange Xs in there.
Go back, check your cookie settings, check your flags.
With all of that configured, I'm going to walk you through
this excellent debugging guide, which comes from Lily Chen,
one of the engineers working on SameSite.
So don't worry, if you don't catch everything I do in this
video, it's all written down in there and there's a link
in the info.
And going to keep using the SameSite sandbox for testing.
The code is all on Glitch.
If you expand the info there you can find a link.
Feel free to remix this if you want to run your own version
or try some different combinations of cookies and so on.
Let's open up DevTools and start poking around.
I'm going to start on the Console tab.
And you'll probably see some warnings, but we're
going to be cleaning those up.
So what you actually want to look for, if you're on a
recent enough version of Chrome, like 84 and onwards,
is the Issues tab here.
So the warnings are going to show you the same information
that Issues tab does, but the Issues tab is much
clearer, much more actionable.
Sam's got a video where he goes through the full tour on
that. So I'm going to go through this pretty quick.
Let's take a look. It's tap on "go to issues".
The first thing it tells us is that we want to reload the
page to get that full capture.
So let's take that advice and reload.
Now, you can see I've got some issues that have come up.
Let's take a look.
Now, the first one we've got is "mark cross-site cookies
as secure".
Let's expand that and see what's going on inside.
So you can see that this one is telling me that I've got a
cookie that's marked with "SameSite=none", but
it's missing the "Secure" attribute.
If I scroll down a bit more, I can also see I've got some
affected resources so I can expand that out.
And that is going to show me exactly the cookie that's
affected. If I click on that cookie here
and see it takes me to the Network tab up here.
I can expand that so we can see a bit of what's going on.
And it's using this filter entry to basically
filter that down, too.
So you can see it's filtered it specifically to the
cookie name that has the problem, so it is showing me all
the requests that include that specific cookie.
We'll come back to the network tab in a minute.
So hold on to that.
And we'll take a look at the other issue first.
So back in here, let's scroll down again
and expand that.
The second issue is telling me
that I have some cookies that don't specify
a "SameSite" attribute at all.
So the browser just doesn't know what to do with that
cookie. Maybe we're OK with it being first party,
but we haven't told anyone.
So let's take a look at the cookies that are affected in
there. So I'm going to expand this again.
And you can see I've got two cookies
affected.
Right well now, we know where the problems are.
Let's go over to the Network tab to take a look in detail.
This is a pretty simple site, so there aren't that many
requests. In reality, you've probably got far more to wade
through. So let's look at some ways that you can filter
that down.
What I'm gonna do is right-click in here and
go to header options where I can enable cookies
and also set cookies.
So this is going to show me each of the requests.
And how many cookies they are sending.
And how many cookies are being set by the set cookie header
in the response.
The other part of the puzzle then is this "Has
blocked cookies" toggle up here.
Now, if I turn that on, you can see one
of our requests is disappearing.
So when I have this on, it's filtering out all the requests
that are not being altered in any way.
So we've got a pretty good idea that it's these two that
are responsible for the issues.
Back on the table, let's look at the request of the page
first. So tap on there and
on the cookies tab over here.
I can see that I have one of my response cookies
highlighted. So I'm gonna hover over that.
And that info bar is telling us that
this is the cookie that's got the "SameSite=none", but is
missing the "Secure" flag.
So I've got the name.
I've got the value. Hopefully that's enough for you to
track it down the back end and get that secure flag
set. Okay, but we had another issue that
was listed as well.
So let's take a look at the second request.
That's cookies.json.
Now, this one looks fairly quiet.
So the thing we want to do here is enable this show
filtered out request cookies.
Suddenly, there's a lot more going on here.
Now, what this is showing us is all the cookies that
could have been included on that request but were
restricted for some reason.
Now, some of them are for the right reasons.
So you can see here we've got a cookie that has "SameSite=
Strict" and that's not included in the cross-site request.
Got one that says "SameSite=Lax".
Same deal. We don't want it on the cross-site request.
But then we've got these two where they've got a blank
"SameSite" value.
Now, that means that the browser is treating them as
"SameSite=Lax" and therefore restricting them.
This might be because you didn't specify a SameSite value,
but it might also be because you've got an invalid value in
there. So get into your code and look for those SameSite
attributes. And check the spelling to make sure there are
no typos in there as well.
Now, DevTools is great for this kind of interactive
exploration, but we can also explore the data for
a whole series of requests.
This is helpful if you need to grab the data for a
particular situation, like maybe it's one user
with a particular account type who has been able to
reproduce this problem and you can't necessarily
sit down with them at their machine for a good debugging
session together.
For this, we're going to capture a network log.
So open up a new tab.
Go to chrome://net-export.
If you've been doing a whole bunch of these, then you may
need to click "start over" on that.
And what we want to make sure of, in the options, is that
we say "include cookies and credentials".
Because that's what we're trying to test.
But just be mindful that including all
of this means that you may be logging some sensitive user
data. So treat it in exactly the same way that you would
with any other. Make sure that you have the consent to log
it. Make sure that you're controlling access to that log
and delete it when you're done debugging the issue.
OK, press "Start Logging to Disk".
And I am just going to save that in my downloads directory.
OK. Now do not close this tab because this is what's doing
the recording. But we are going to switch back over to our
test site, and I am just going to reload
the page to capture that behavior.
Now, in reality, what you want to do is capture the
entire user journey that you're trying to debug.
At a minimum, it's got to be the section that is causing
the problem. But often you should probably try and start
maybe from like user sign in or wherever the cookies are
being set because you probably want to capture that
interaction as well.
OK. Once you're done, we're going to switch back over to
our Network tab and we're going to say "stop
logging".
Now, you can say like "show file" here
and you can see that it's just a JSON file in this
directory. You can take a look at it.
It is pretty big and it's pretty verbose.
So what we want to do is make use of the NetLog
viewer tool which is linked from this page.
So you go there and I'm going to go to the hosted
version here.
Now I choose my file, which is
just there, chrome-export-log.
And there we go. You can see that I've got a whole bunch of
information about the logging that I've just done.
You can see my Chrome version, you can see the OS info.
What you can also see is if you dive
into this where you've got features here,
you can see all the flags that I've got enabled.
I've been playing with quite a few of them.
But there's also "cookies without SameSite must be secure"
embedded in there.
The stuff we're looking for, though, related to the cookies
is over in the Events section.
So I'm going to go over here.
And as you can see, I've got 200 events to deal
with. So this is pretty verbose.
This is all of the requests that Chrome is
sending, kind of all of the network related events,
including extensions, including other tabs.
So let's filter this down to something
a bit more useful. I want to type and it is
"URL_REQUEST".
Make sure there's no space after that column
and there you go. That's a bit more manageable.
You can see that there's a bunch of other things going on
in there, but I can see my SameSite sandbox
requests. These are the ones that I'm interested in.
Let's find that cookies.json one.
And inside of here, it's this string
that I'm interested in, "COOKIE_INCLUSION_STATUS".
Now, what that's telling me is basically why a cookie was
or wasn't included in the request.
And if I look through there, you can see each
of the different ones.
So I've got.
Let's see what we got in here.
"COOKIE_INCLUSION_STATUS" is
"exclude" because that's "SameSite=Strict".
That's one of the ones that we wanted excluded.
We've got one up here, that is "ck03",
that is excluded because "SameSite" was unspecified.
So it was treated as lax.
The search over here lets you do quite
a bit. So if I want to find where a particular cookie
is set, for example, let's say "ck02", I
can actually just search for that header value.
So "set-cookie:ck02".
There it is.
And then if I just control+F in here as well, for the
"set-cookie". There you go, you can see
all of the response cookies.
And if I look at that, that's my "ck02" one,
"SameSite=none". That's missing a "Secure" attribute on
there. And that's it.
So now you know how to debug your cookie issues.
And when you find them, you've got the recipe to put them
right. Remember, it's all about being explicit
on where you want that cookie sent.
We've got more on this theme.
You can watch Eiji's video talking you through some of the
other resources you can isolate with COOP and COEP.
And you can also come back to see me and Maud have more
header related fun.