[Music]
[Applause]
hi I'm Liam a web ecosystem consultant
at Google this talk will explore how
different companies are building fast
are resilient experiences in the world
we'll use the war box libraries to show
how to implement four different patterns
in your site but all of these features
can also be implemented by manually
writing the serviceworker code our first
pattern is called resilient search
experiences and can be applied to any
site that offers some type of search
functionality when a user searches for a
topic in Google search for Chrome in
Android devices and loses connection
instead of the standard Network error
page they are presented with a custom
offline page asking if they want to opt
in for notifications if the user accepts
the permission once the connection is
back they will receive a web push
notification informing that the search
result is ready clicking on the
notification will take the user to the
result screen this is a great way of
keeping the user engaged while letting
them complete the task they were looking
for at the heart of this implementation
is the background sync API which lets
you differ actions until the user has
stable connectivity in war box this can
be implemented very easily first you can
define the network only cache in a
strategy for the search endpoint so this
request always go to the network then
you can pass it background sync plug-in
to take care of the offline scenarios
let's see how the plugin looks like the
waterboxx background scene plugin
receives the name of a queue to store
failed requests to be retried later the
plug-in also receives an unseen callback
which will be called once the connection
is recovered inside the callback you can
retrieve any fail request process them
and inform the user of the result for
example with a notification before
moving to the next pattern let's take a
look at an important detail for
this implementation you might have
noticed that the notification permission
is requested when the user loses
connection at that point the user
understands the value of the service and
knows that the notification will deliver
timely and relevant updates this is an
example of the good implementation of
the web push permission our next pattern
is adaptive loading with service workers
and will allow you to provide a fast
experience regardless of the network and
the device tara is one of the biggest
media sites in brazil they have a large
user base coming from slow and fast
connections to provide a more reliable
experience to all their users they are
combining service workers and the
network information API to deliver lower
quality images to users on 2g or 3G
connections tera Duda strategy to the
next level when users are navigating on
slow connections they deliver the amp
version of the articles which are more
lightweight and tend to perform better
under these conditions to implement this
functionality in war box you can first
apply a cache first strategy to images
then you can pass an exploration plugin
to limit the number of entries in the
cache you can extend this strategy by
creating a custom plugin that we will
call adaptive loading plug-in decided
plug-in you can listen for the request
will fetch callback that will be called
before the request is made so you can
apply a transformation to it inside the
callback you can check the connection
type if it's a slow connection you can
create a new URL for a lower image
quality finally you can create a new
request based on that URL and fetch the
most appropriate image file according to
these conditions if you are using cloud
inari there's a war box cloud in re
plug-in making this feature even easier
to implement check it out as you might
have noticed the first two buttons have
some things in common we have combined
the functionality of runtime caching
strategies with
plugins this shows one of the benefits
of using were box allowing you to extend
the standard features in a very easy way
let's move now to the second part of the
dock our third pattern is called instant
navigation experiences and it's useful
for any type of site performing a task
in a website might involve several steps
each of them meaning a navigation
request navigation request live request
for HTML pages are normally satisfied
via the network this means using a cache
control header of no cache or a max age
of zero to ensure that the response is
reasonably fresh having to go against
the network means that each navigation
might be slow or at the least not
reliably fast to speed up these
navigations you can apply a technique
called prefetching in this example
MercadoLibre
the largest e-commerce site in latin
america dynamically shakes lien prefetch
tags in listing pages to accelerate
parts of its law but prefetching is not
only useful for ecommerce sites Italian
sports port out-build Giulia sport
you see service workers to prefetch the
most popular posts that appear in the
home page before the user even clicks on
them as a result load time for
navigation two articles have improved by
78% and the number of article
impressions has increased in 45%
prefetching is commonly implemented by
using a resource hint in your pages link
prefetch the tag tells the browser to
fetch a resource at the lowest priority
and keep it in the HTTP cache for five
minutes in the serviceworker side you
can intercept requests for HTML pages so
that you can extend the lifetime of the
prefetch resource beyond the five
minutes window for HTML pages as
tailwater revalidate strategy is a good
option to respond quickly from the cache
while simultaneously keeping it
to date before moving to the final
pattern there's a slight variation of
this technique if there are using
resource hints in the page some
developers prefer to delegate
prefetching completely to the
serviceworker for that you need to
implement a page to serviceworker
communication technique the war box
window package allows you to do that
so if you're interested on following
that route you can check that out
we have reached the end of our talk
our final pattern is app shell UX with
service workers and it's useful if you
want to make multi-page apps feel like
single page applications Dirk has become
one of the favorite platforms for
software developers the architecture of
their side is a multi-page up their team
was interested in the benefits of the
app shell model but didn't want to incur
in a measure architectural change so
let's see what they did first they
created partials for the header and the
footer of the homepage these assets are
added to the cache at the serviceworker
install event what's commonly referred
to us pre-caching the content of the
page is the only part that's actually
being fetched from the network when
navigating but the key ingredient of
this solution is the usage of streaming
thanks to that bytes can start being
painted in the screen before the full
response is ready war box you can start
by creating a regular expression too
much request for patience then you can
pass an array of stream responses to
compose for the header of the footer you
can use a cache first strategy for the
content you can use a network first all
these streaming sources will be composed
by war box and sent to the client
thanks to streams the header can start
being painted as soon as you speak up
from the cache without having to wait
for the full response we have seen for
advanced patterns for speed and
resilience as a complement of this talk
will be
loading guides and cold ups so you can
see them in more detail please check web
dev slash progressive elapse and web dev
slash reliable thanks for watching
[Music]
[Applause]
you