[Music]
[Applause]
hi everyone I'm excited to show you in
the next 15 minutes how you can use
structured data to make your website
stand out more in Google search and how
that can be done with JavaScript when
the static implementation is infeasible
we will start by looking at what
structured data is and why it is a good
idea for your website then we will look
at ways to implement it using javascript
and last but not least we'll take a look
at how to test and debug your
implementation all right now what a
structured data and why is it useful
structured data is a standardized set of
additional markup that you can put on
your pages to tell machines like
Googlebot more about the content on your
page on the right side here you can see
the information for a specific product
being highlighted in both the image
search as well as the search results
including additional information like
ratings and price we call such results
rich results to implement structured
data you can use json-ld microdata or
rdf a but we recommend using json-ld
here is an example of what a json-ld
block on your page might look like
besides products there are many
verticals that can benefit from
structured data and become Milledgeville
for which results here are some examples
but you should check the link for the
full gallery of supported verticals note
that implementing structured data makes
the page eligible for rich results but
does not mean that we will always show
them for every page that implements it
so now we talked about what structured
data is and how it benefits your website
let's walk through a few possible
implementations we've seen that the
easiest way is to include a script tag
the json-ld data in the page this can of
course be done in the backend or
straightening the HTML of a page but
what are the options if you are using
client-side oner JavaScript first of all
it is fine to implement it dynamically
with client-side JavaScript we recommend
to use server-side rendering to make
your website as robust as possible but
there is no issue with implementing it
with JavaScript per se in this session
we will look at three possible
implementation approaches of course you
can use JavaScript without libraries or
frameworks to inject structured data
into your pages here is an example of a
vanilla JavaScript implementation for a
client-side rendering single page
application it fetches the json-ld data
from an api and injects it into the head
of the page as Googlebot renders this
page it will execute the JavaScript and
the structured data will be rendered
just make sure that the API is available
to Googlebot and not blocked by
robots.txt when you are using frameworks
such as react angular or view J's
you very likely have helpers or built-in
functionality available to insert
structured data into your pages here is
an example of a react component using
the schema helper utility to create
typed json-ld for a person's profile
page should you not have access to the
code of your pages that have Google tag
manager on these pages
you may use a custom tag in custom
variables to create structured data from
the information that is on the page to
do that create a custom HTML tag in your
container and insert the relevant
json-ld as well as the variables for the
values of each field in the json-ld
block then create the necessary custom
JavaScript variables to extract
information from the page so it can be
inserted into the custom HTML tag
automatically we advise not to copy and
paste information from the page
directly into Google tag manager as that
will likely cause a mismatch between
page content and structured data
generated by Google tag manager to rise
in the future right so we've seen three
ways of generating structured data with
JavaScript let's find out if our
implementation works as expected there
are two main tools for testing the
implementations the first one is the
rich results test you can paste a URL
into the tool and see what structured
data is recognized as well as if there
are any issues with the structured data
on the page when using javascript to
generate structured data we recommend
testing a URL instead of pasting code
directly into the tool the other great
tool for testing this is the Google
search console in the URL inspection
tool you can see the structured data
that is detected and if it is valid but
you can also see which pages of your
site were eligible for which results and
which ones have arrows or warnings to
look into if you want to learn more
about Google search in structured data
check out our documentation at
developers.google.com slash search or
use this short link to read more on how
to use javascript to generate structured
data for your pages thanks a lot for
joining and have a great day bye
[Music]
[Applause]