[Music]
[Applause]
hi everyone thanks for watching this
session on debugging JavaScript SEO
issues in the next 15 minutes I will
take you on a short journey in which we
will talk a bit about the various that a
few SEO still have about JavaScript and
Google search then look at the tools
available to SEO and developers and then
get our hands dirty on a few case
studies from the real world now let's
get started with looking at the basics
can SEO and JavaScript be friends
there's a bunch of history behind this
that contributed to various opinions and
answers to this question today the
answer is generally yes sure as with
every technology there are things that
can go wrong but there's nothing
inherently or categorically wrong with
JavaScript sites in Google search let's
look at a few things people tend to get
wrong about javascript and search the
number one concern brought up is that
Googlebot does not support modern
JavaScript or has otherwise very limited
capabilities in terms of JavaScript
features at Google IO 2019 we announced
the Evergreen Googlebot this means that
Googlebot uses a current stable Chrome
to render websites and execute
JavaScript and that Googlebot follows
the release of new chrome versions quite
closely another worry is concerned with
the two waves of indexing and the delay
between crawling and rendering Googlebot
renders all pages and the two waves were
a simplification of the process that
isn't accurate anymore the time pages
spent in the queue between crawling and
rendering is very very short five
seconds at the median a few minutes for
the 90th percentile rendering itself
well takes as long as it takes your
website to load in the browser
last but not least be wary of blanket
statements that paint JavaScript as the
general SEO issue well some search
engines might still have limited
capabilities for processing JavaScript
they ultimately want to understand
modern websites and that includes
JavaScript if javascript is used
responsibly tested properly and
implemented correctly then there are no
issues for google search in particular
and solutions exist for SEO in general
for example you may consider server-side
rendering or use dynamic rendering as a
workaround further crawlers when saying
test your site properly the follow up
question is usually well how do I test
my site properly and luckily we have a
whole toolkit for you to test your site
for Google search let's take a look at
what's available
the first tool in your tool belt is
Google search console it's a super
powerful tool for your Google search
performance besides a ton of reports it
contains the gyro inspection tool that
lets you check if the URL is in Google
search if there are any issues and how
Googlebot sees the page the second tool
that is really helpful is the rich
results tests it takes any URL or lets
you copy and paste code to check its
main purpose is to show a structured
data is correctly implemented but it has
much more to offer than just that
the last but not least the
mobile-friendly test is similar to the
rich results test on top of the rendered
HTML the status of all embedded
resources and network requests it also
shows an above the full screen shot of
the page as well as possible mobile user
experience issues now let's take these
tools for spin I have built three
websites based on real cases that ID
bugged in the webmaster forums the first
case is a single page application that
does not show up and will at all as I'm
not the owner of the domain I don't have
access to Google search console for this
side but I can still take a look I will
start with a mobile
detests to get a first look at the page
in question as we can see the page loads
but shows an error message when I load
the page in the browser it displays the
data correctly hmm we can take a look at
the resources Googlebot tried to load
for this page here we see that one
wasn't loaded the API Dahl example.org
slash products URL wasn't loaded because
it's blocked by robots.txt when
Googlebot renders it respects the
robots.txt for each network request it
needs to make the HTML CSS JavaScript
images or API calls in this case someone
prevented Googlebot from making the API
call by disallowing it in robots.txt in
this case the web app handles a failed
API request as a not found error and
shows a corresponding message to the
user
we caught this as a software for and as
it is a narrow page we didn't index it
take note that there are safer ways to
show a 404 page in a single page app
such as redirecting to a URL with a four
for status or setting the page to no
index right we solved that one that's
pretty good all right on to the next one
this one is described as a progressive
web app or PWA that didn't show up in
search except for their home page let's
go find out why looking at the home page
it looks alright the other views in this
progressive web app also know just fine
hmm
let's test one of these pages we will
use the mobile-friendly test again to
get a first look at what's going on oh
the test says it can't access the page
but it worked in the browser so let's
check with our dev tools in the network
tab I see that I get a 200 status from
the service worker though what happens
when I open the page in an incognito
window whoops so
or the server isn't actually properly
set up to display the page instead the
serviceworker does all the work to
handle the navigation that isn't good
Googlebot has to behave like a
first-time visitor so it loads a page
without the serviceworker cookies and so
on this needs to be fixed on the server
great two websites fixed but I have one
more to go this one is a news website
that is worried because not all content
can be found by a Google search to mix
things up a little bit I'll use the rich
results test for this one the website
doesn't seem to have any obvious issues
let's look at the rendered HTML hmm even
that looks fine to me
so let's take a look at the web site in
the browser so it loads 10 news stories
and links to each news story and then
loads more stories as I scroll down do
we find that in the rendered HTML -
interesting this story isn't in the
rendered HTML it looks like the initial
10 stories are there but none of the
content that is being loaded on scroll
wait does it work when I resize the
window
oops it only works when the user Scrolls
well Google but doesn't scroll that's
why these stories are loaded that's not
exactly a problem this can be solved by
using an intersection observer for
instance generally I recommend checking
out the documentation at
developers.google.com slash search for
much more information on this topic and
other topics I hope this was interesting
and helped you with testing your
websites for Google search keep building
cool stuff on the web and take care
[Music]
[Applause]