[Music]
[Applause]
hi everyone thanks for joining I'm PJ
I'm a product manager on the chrome web
platform team responsible for
progressive web apps notifications and
permissions today's talk is about
quieter notification permission prompts
and how recent changes to how chrome
handles notification permission requests
can make browsing for the web a little
better for everyone
there's also important information in
here for developers who use
notifications to help you improve your
user experience improve your
notification accept rates and to tell
you about upcoming changes that will
detect and flag abuse abuse of
notification prompts or content if
you're not familiar with them web
notifications are channel for
communicating timely and contextually
relevant information to the user mostly
these work just like push notifications
in mobile apps except they can also work
on desktop on Windows Mac as well as
smartphones on Android for example web
notifications appear in the notification
drawer and on desktop
they typically appear in the top right
corner of the screen in some cases
notifications aren't just helpful they
are almost essential to the apps
functionality for example if you had an
incoming call from a communication app
like google google duo or chat that's
not something you want to know about
later you need to know about it right
away of course not everyone uses apps
that require notifications and not all
websites are putting the needs of their
users first and that means that we are
seeing a lot of websites out there that
are misusing notifications in ways that
are annoying or could be abusive before
we get into that though I want to talk
about how users get enrolled in
notifications to receive web
notifications a user needs to accept a
notification permission requests when
websites prompt users out of context for
a notification such as when a user first
arrives on the web site it can be a
pretty annoying distraction both from
the browsing experience it's
as well as from the website's content
worse some abusive websites look for
ways to trick users into accepting
notifications that are then used to
promote malware or undesired content I
want to cover why we have notifications
in the web platform in the first place
in a little bit more depth the web
platform is there to enable web
developers to create powerful
applications and web notifications are
part of that toolkit without
notification support there would be
entire types of apps that would be
simply impossible to build using web
technology so for example messaging apps
calendars ecommerce for food delivery
notifiers taxi or ride-sharing apps all
dependent notifications to provide a
timely tap on the shoulder to the user
and well you can imagine that some of
these apps might be usable without
notifications you could see that most of
the time you're probably going to want
one we've also all equally experienced
some of the misuse of notifications
though that includes things like
unwanted marketing promotions or content
that just isn't very important or
relevant to us at a given moment to
address this problem starting in Chrome
ad that was released in January of 2020
we started making changes to how these
notifications request work to help make
browsing the web safer and less
interruptive we're gonna get into that
new UI in the next slide in chrome 80 we
added quite notifications UI quite
notification UI is less interruptive but
it still lets the users know that the
request has been made there's a little
bit of animation to catch the eye but on
desktop the dialogue is in the omnibox
so it doesn't actually cover any part of
the web content on mobile the
notification prompt used to be a modal
in normal UI but in quiet UI it's an
easily dismissed info bar at the bottom
of the screen quite notification UI aims
to reduce the visual priority and
interruptive 'no sub mode vacation
requests on desktop what you're seeing
in this example on the left you'll
notice the bell icon initially animates
with text indicating that notifications
are blocked on the site in mobile the
quiet UI is now an info bar in both of
these cases in product help explains to
the user
why notifications were blocked on the
site quite notifications UI was created
specifically to address the concerns I
mentioned earlier in this talk we
received frequent complaints from users
in chrome feedback about disruptive
notification permission prompts or
unwanted notifications that being said
there are services with tens or hundreds
of millions of users like messaging apps
and calendars that are depending on
timely web notifications every single
day let's talk for a moment about how
users get enrolled in quiet notification
UI there's several ways that this can
happen first users could just enroll
themselves manually by changing their
preferences in Chrome settings second
sites that have very low accept rates
for notification permission requests
will be automatically enrolled in quiet
notifications UI and this is currently
sites that have the lowest few
percentile of notification accept rates
so the absolute rate needed for quite
notification UI does change over time
because we are using percentiles we'll
also periodically increase the accept
pre percentile that's needed to preserve
normal notification UI we always keep a
control group of users that are in
normal notification permission UI so
that if a site's accept rates improve we
can remove it from quiet UI and
enforcement third there are some users
who almost never accept any notification
permission requests these users simply
don't want notifications and for these
users we adaptively enable quite
notification mode on their behalf in
Chrome settings if they repeatedly block
notification requests as sites improve
their behavior and use of notification
permission requests we expect that there
will be fewer and fewer users who are
adaptively placed in quiet notification
UI mode finally and this is starting in
chrome 84 which is coming up soon we're
going to begin enforcing against abusive
notification prompts the try to mislead
users are fishing for private
information or promoting malware in this
case in addition to quite notifications
UI the user is going to be advised in
the notification prompt that the site
may be trying to trick them so
what should you do to make sure your
website is not enrolled in quite
notification UI well first and foremost
if your prompting users to enroll
notifications as soon as they arrive on
your website please stop doing that this
is the easiest way to improve your
notification accept rate very few users
will accept a notification from a site
they're visiting for the first time and
if you think about it why would they
we're all experiencing information
overload wait until you know your user
better and you know you can add value
for your user before you prompt them you
can and should prompt your user to
accept notification when there's a clear
user benefit and in the context of the
user's journey in your application
websites that ask for notification
permission in the context where the
benefit is clear the user have 80%
accept rates or higher that should be
your goal even if you do the best
possible job with your notification
prompt to UX it's possible that some of
your users may be in quiet notification
UI mode so the first thing you want to
check here is to make sure that the
accept rates on your site or what you
really expect them to be notification
accept rate data is in the chrome user
experience report which is a public
database containing important
information about real-world chrome
metrics for popular destinations on the
web there's a minimum number of users
and decisions that are required for data
to be available and the chrome user
experience report and that's to help
with preserving visitor privacy so if
your site doesn't have data and the
chrome user experience report you may
need to get that information from
somewhere else
for example most notifications service
providers will have this instrumented so
that you can check your accept rates or
if you've rolled your own notifications
implementation you may need to add your
own instrumentation it's also a good
idea to look at the notification accept
rates of sites that are like yours in
the chrome user experience report so you
can get a sense for what the benchmark
accept rates are and aim to be better
than those the article linked here in
the slide will give you more details
about how to use the chrome user
experience data set to learn more about
users notification permission prompt
decisions on your website so the second
thing you need to think about is how can
you make your notification requests
boring
context I know I mentioned this before
but it bears repeating you want to make
absolutely sure that you're asking for
notification permission at a moment in
the users journey that makes sense to
them in this example we're showing a
notification request the first time the
user receives a response to their first
chat this is a perfect moment even with
quiet notification UI it should be
obvious to the user why they would want
to accept notifications the activity and
motion in the web app combined with the
motion of the browser prompt should be
sufficient cues for the user to enroll
in notifications if they want them if
your user doesn't accept notifications
with this in context pattern there's a
pretty good chance that they just don't
want notifications and you should
respect that decision before I finish I
want to share a little bit about what's
coming next for notifications first
we're planning to increase the accept
rate percentile that's needed to have
normal notification prompts since this
is a percentile as well something to
keep in mind is that if other sites are
improving their notification UX and
you're not your site may be slipping
into a lower percentile and quite
notifications may be activated for your
site if your site is a notification
accept rate of over 50 percent you're in
safe territory but we recommend aiming
for 80 percent or better second chrome
places a high priority on user privacy
and security and we intend to take more
steps to protect users from abuse of
notification in the future that includes
more protections from usage notification
content as well as retroactive action to
help users who may have already enrolled
in notifications from abusive sites
prior to the release of chrome 84 most
important as we improve the
signal-to-noise ratio of the web
notification ecosystem we hope users
will come to view notifications as being
more helpful if this happens it means
we're doing a good job protecting users
from unwanted notification prompts an
unwanted notification content ultimately
this will help developers who use
notifications for key functionality in
their apps as users are more likely to
accept notifications when they have less
reason to be worried about spammy or
abusive notifications thanks again for
joining today everyone have a great day