[Music]
[Applause]
you
hi i'm andre today we're going to answer
some frequently features and
capabilities for installed pwas that
were reserved previously only to native
apps and to tell us more about what is
new and help us with some hard questions
we have a guest hi PJ tell us a tell us
about your role at Google
thanks so much Andrzej I'm PJ I'm a
product manager on the chrome web
platform team I work on progressive Web
Apps usually called pwace and basically
progressive web apps or modern
applications built using web
technologies that are making users
happier PWA is have a lot of
capabilities of which one is that they
can be installed into a user's computer
just the same as any other application
oh cool so that means we have exactly
the right person in the room for people
in the audience who are not yet familiar
with installable petaboys
can you tell us a bit more about what
they are and where they are available
being a savile is really a standout
feature for PW AAS because it's giving
web developers the ability to make
applications that can be started from
the Start menu on Windows from the
application folder on Mac the homescreen
on Android and iOS and these can really
look and feel like any other application
on the device so for applications that
users are using repeatedly being
installed means that that app is a
little bit more top-of-mind for the user
because that launching surface is is
immediately accessible to the user they
don't have to navigate anywhere in the
browser to get to get back to the
application it also means that the
application is showing up in the
activity switcher as a separate app and
that makes install quite attractive to
developers but I want to be clear that a
pw8 doesn't have to be installed to be a
PW a being installable is just one
property of a PW a us this question
about distribution so let's talk from
what about where PW A's are available
so first PW eyes can be installed
directly from the web browser on both
desktop and Android and on desktop pwace
can also be listed in the Windows Store
on Android you can find PW a powered
Android apps in the Play Store
these is a technology called a trusted
web activity
you also see pwace in the Samsung store
you might have heard that pwace are
showing up in the chroma West Play Store
and that's an early access feature I'm
really excited about so let's save a
little time at the end of the session to
talk more about that oh I'm really
looking forward to learning more about
Chrome OS Play Store but before that can
you tell us about the recent features
that you think are the most exciting for
developers I really wish that we had
time to go into everything that shipping
because there's a lot happening right
now but I'm gonna have to just pick a
few favorites for today so the features
that I'm most excited about are some of
the things that web developers could
previously only do using a hybrid
technology like an electron app or a
Cordova app and to begin here let me
just mention that the ability to install
pwace on desktop is still really new so
for those of you the audience who have
been paying close attention I might've
seen the announcement at i/o last year
this might seem like old news but I
think for a lot of the web development
community this is still a very new
feature and people are still getting
used to the super power that install can
happen everywhere you can now write one
app and have it be installable on
desktop on tablet on smartphones and
users can discover that app on your
website in search results in play in the
Windows Store in a Samsung store and
this is giving web developers a really
unprecedented reach for distribution of
their applications so I'm just super
excited that this is now possible for
they have install across all of these
different screens and through all of
these different channels the other
features that I'm most excited about are
all the capabilities that were
previously only possible with Cordova or
electron so for example registering a
file type handler for an app offering an
immersive mode so creating better web
games through an immersive mode and
adding context menus for shortcuts and
more so the file type handler would
allow a user to start a web-based image
editor by double clicking on an image in
their OS File Explorer
that's that's exciting exactly that and
so like with file type handling you can
register a file extension or mime type
so let's say that you've written a new
type of image editor and you can edit
jpg and pink files you could register a
file type extension for those file types
and then those files Heights will
automatically open and your editor if
the user double clicks on those a word
of warning file type handling isn't
quite here yet we expect it to go into
Oranje trial in chrome 85 in August and
to be available generally sometime in
the fall or winter looking forward for
this one to go stable tell me more about
the immersive mode what does that mean
immersive mode is a term that's just a
board from native it's a full-screen
mode and basically it removes all of the
operating system decorations so no
status bar no navigation bar and this is
great for games or other media basically
when you want to be able to address
every single pixel on the screen so I
could start a video player a full screen
from daikon and a home screen nice and
what about up short codes sure absolute
cuts are a way to provide quick access
to important functions in the app
directly from the app icon so for
example on Android you might be familiar
with a long press on the app icon on the
launch screen so or on the home screen
so if you were to long press on a home
screen icon for say a mail application
you might see compose functionality
directly in the menu that appears when
you long press on the mail client app
shortcuts also work on desktop operating
systems and that support will be
arriving in chrome 85 interesting so
that's like deep linking into parts off
might be the Blooey directly from the
icon that's on the home screen
exactly switching gears a little bit we
launched tracer to web activity at last
year's i/o and since then we have many
feature requests and questions from
developers and I wanted to go through
some of those with you today
first developers have pointed out that
the wait permissions work in the browser
any native is different
and that may stir users a little bit
confused as an example native apps gets
in the notification permission by
default while web apps need to need the
users to accept the permission first how
are how are we planning to solve those
inconsistencies so let's just start by
just sharing my perspective on the
philosophy here of I don't think that
users should need to think about what
technology was used to build the
application that they're using users
should really just have a job you know
users just have a job to get done and we
want to help developers help users as
easily as possible so wherever it makes
sense I think an installed web
application should use the operating
systems typical UI for things like
managing permissions launching and
switching between applications just to
match the users expectations for how
things should behave on the device that
they're using so we've introduced this
concept of notification delegation into
installed pwace and that means that when
a PW is installed it will delegate the
notification permission into the native
setting area on Android so another
difference between an app installed from
Play and a web for example is that an
app install from play automatically
receives notification permission so we
want that experience to be the same for
Android applications that were built
using a PWA and that's why we've
delegated the web notification
permission to the notification settings
panel in Android and these apps can be
configured to auto enroll users and
notifications so that they just look and
feel and behave exactly like any other
Android app and the user doesn't even
need to know that this application was
built using web technology in the future
we're going to be adding location to the
Settings panel to of course there won't
be any auto enrolment for location
because users are not Auto enrolled in
location before location permission on
in Android native apps either so we're
just gonna match what the behavior is
between you know for a native
application for apps that are installed
for
say the Play Store or from any other you
know distribution channel where the user
you know may or may not be aware that
this application is a web application
we're going to continue as well to
delegate more permissions and match OS
preferences over the next few releases
got it so this will make the experience
more seamless to users regardless of the
technology that developer used to build
app another frequent request developers
sometimes feel that when they make and
write an Android app using pdaboy and
treszura web activity they should have a
communication channel between the native
application and the web app this would
allow them to use native platform
capabilities where an equivalent on the
web doesn't exist already is this
something that is being considered I'm
really glad you asked this question
because this is exactly the kind of
product question that I really love and
I'd like to hear from our audience on
this one so today you can pass
parameters into a trusted with activity
when you launch it and you can use
intents to leave the trust of activity
and pass some information into another
activity inside of your app and we're
considering adding support for a message
bus for example we could extend post
message to enable a bus with this
functionality however I don't have use
cases from developers on exactly what
they need here most capabilities are
already in the web platform or are
planned in you know it herb plant as
part of the fugu effort to add web
capabilities to the web platform so if
the web platform has missing
capabilities I'd really rather add that
capability to the web then create a
message bus to native because if a
capability is part of the web platform
then it's gonna work everywhere and
developers only need to have one code
base which is simpler and that code base
will work in multiple browsers whether
the app is installed or not installed
etc so I'd like to turn this just to do
a question for our audience what do you
need to do in native code that you can't
do today in the web platform and other
things we could do to improve the web
platform so you wouldn't need to do that
in native
perhaps it's something that could only
be done in native and you really need
that message bus I'd really like to hear
from you about this cool I'm also
looking forward to hear from folks on
Twitter or if you're watching this live
on the live chat many developers have a
native application and prompting users
who install a PDA in the in the browser
when they already have the native app
installed can lead some confusion is
there a way to prevent the prompts from
showing when the native app is already
installed so that's a great question
it's also probably one of the the top
concerns that I hear from teams that are
implementing a progressive web app it's
it's called channel conflict and it
arises where you're not sure which
experience is going to be best for the
user so I think the most important thing
for developers to know is that you do
have full control over the promotion a
PW install so you know you don't need to
worry about the browser promoting your
PW a if you don't want it to there are
ways you can prevent the browser from
promoting the installation of your PW a
if for example you have a native app so
let's let's talk about how that works
first in the web app manifest there's a
couple of fields you should know about
one is called the related applications
field and this is where you can list
native apps for Android and iOS and then
there's another boolean field called
prefer related apps and if this is set
to true the browser's not going to
promote the install of your PW a
secondly there's an event that fires
when a PW a passes the install ability
check in the browser and when this
happens developers can call a prevent
default method and that's gonna block
any promotion of the PW a install in
browser UI finally there's a new
JavaScript API just landed earlier this
year called get installed related apps
and this is gonna let developers inspect
if the user has native apps installed on
the device that are associated with the
origin that the user is currently on and
just to be clear this isn't gonna let
you see any app that the user happens to
have installed in the device the app has
to be associated with the origin that
the user is on this API does allow for a
lot of programmatic flexibility for
developers so it means you
you have full control which experience
do you want to promote to the user you
could use for example user behavior you
could provide the user with preferences
in your HTML it's really up to you how
you want to use this control but it does
give you as the developer a lot of
control over what you promote to the
user and when it happens so this means I
can use this API to check my
notifications installed and make
decisions like showing that sounds crane
prompt or not what if my native app is
using trusted web activity willed is a
pee I use to return so yes absolutely
this does mean that you can use the API
to check your native app is installed at
Russell web activity is really just an
Android app so it will show up just like
any other Android app and to say this
API will return it it will also return
if the if the app is a it has been
installed from the web browser so a PWA
installed from the web browser will also
get returned by kit installed related
apps cool on the developer experiences
side we've been working on tools like
bubble wrap
to help developers view their project to
use interest of web activity but many
developers is you wonder if it wouldn't
be easier if you could just copy paste
in your own to the Play Store that's a
great question
so the reason why we've been focusing
our efforts on making this easier for
developers on bubble wrap is that we
could create a much more powerful much
more flexible system for developers for
building Android apps using a
command-line utility like bubble wrap
then what we could do in a web interface
so app stores are really a different
ecosystem and they have different
requirements and policies and we believe
that developers should have powerful
tools that they need to rethink the
experience of their applications for
this environment and we also want to
avoid giving developers the perception
that they could just drop a website into
the store without thinking about that
experience so there are all kinds of
design decisions that should go into
building an Android app whether or not
it's a PWA powering that up for example
you know what's the splash screen it'll
look like when you're gonna hide it when
to show content didi notifications there
wouldn't be that's this kind of
flexibility for configuring these
options with a web interface that being
said we wanted to be as easy as possible
so we've worked to streamline it to the
maximum extent that we can with bubble
wrap and make it a powerful but flexible
and easy-to-use developer tool what
about police or policies do Android apps
that use PW inside the tricity web
activity Stu needs to comply to those
policies I think you said the magic word
there which is Android app it doesn't
matter how your Android app is built
whether it's built using PWA s and web
technology or whether it's built using
Java or : play policies apply to all
Android apps distributed in the Play
Store and therefore they also apply to
Android apps built using progressive web
apps gotcha
so same same store policies apply what
about applications designed for children
can developers use web technology those
apps
if the target audience for your
application is children you need to
comply with the Play family policy
requirements and these requirements are
intended to help keep minors safe from
inappropriate content unfortunately
that's really difficult for the review
teams to evaluate with web apps where
the content can change and not only can
the first party content change but it's
really easy to include third party
content inside of a web application
which can be unintentionally
inappropriate let's imagine that you
were using you know an advertising
network or something else where you're
loading content in from a third party
site you might not be able to verify
yourself for sure whether or not that
content is always going to be
appropriate so for the time being it's
not possible to build Android apps using
trusted web activity that comply with
Play family policy we are working on
ways to make this possible in the future
got it so it seems PWAs are crossing
over ecosystems and developers need to
adjust some of their expectations from
that developers using trusted web
tivities are also expected to fulfill
your quality criteria is that wide that
criteria exists yeah nobody wants an app
store that's gonna be cluttered with
low-quality apps and we also want
developers to
succeed with their apps in the Play
Store keep in mind something that's
really different about distributing
through the Play Store than it is to you
know just sort of build a PWA on your
own site is that these apps have user
ratings and reviews and we want to make
sure that developers are set up for
success to get good ratings and reviews
on an aunt for their app so at a minimum
users expect apps that they install from
the Play Store to look and feel app like
to be fast to work offline and that's
why we have quality criteria for pwe
than in the App Store and this is
exactly what progressive web app
criteria has been intended to do from
the very beginning so first I want to
share that there are certain types of
events that can happen to a web
application that are effectively a crash
and these are things like you know a 404
happening these are things like failing
an offline check when the user goes
offline and returning to chromed I know
this is effectively a crash failing the
digital asset links verification which
is something you need to do with a
trusted web activity to verify that you
are the owner of the content and the
owner of the application in the app
store so if any of these things happen
starting in chrome 86 in October we are
going to be mapping those crashes into
Android vitals crash events and you will
see Android apps begin to crash if you
if users are running into 404s in your
application etc so that's just something
that developers should be aware of and
we're we're making another announcement
with more details about this the second
thing is on the performance side right
now don't have a date to announce with
respect to enforcement of enforce of
performance but developers should be
aware that the criteria is a full batch
PWA and a light has performance score of
80 or better and you can use
webpagetest.org slash easy or PageSpeed
insights against your start URL as the
fastest way to check whether or not
you're meeting this criteria because
having the app launched quickly is an
essential part of having a great
application experience for your users we
will be providing a lot of notice as to
when enforcement will begin it will be
in 2021 it won't be in 2020 for the
performance and full batch PWA scores so
Xbox
hear more about this later in the year
so less one tutor has recently launched
their pdaboy
on the chrome s Playstore which was
quite exciting can you tell us more
about how they did how they did it and
when it is this is becoming january
available i'm really excited about this
right now this is an early access
program and it requires manual
intervention from our team members so
it's not something that we can extend to
everyone in the community but we're
working on getting it to general
availability and when that rolls out
it'll be possible for everyone to just
do this themselves I'll give you a hint
it uses trusted web activity so if
you're building a great trusted web
activity
it'll be really easy to make your
progressive web app available in the
Chrome West Play Store in the future and
I hope we could share more about this in
the second half of the year so what are
soda web activities are coming to Chrome
OS nice well I think we covers a lot I
wish we had more time to discuss our
YouTube and though so for those of you
who are watching please do reach out to
us or Twitter if you want to give
feedback and if you're joining watching
this live please join us on the live
chat we'll see you there and thanks so
much for watching
yes thanks for watching
[Music]
[Applause]