Hello, I'm Jake.
I'm Jason.
Earlier in this conference, we released - Is this a
conference? Actually, is this a conference or it like an
event? I don't know. Let's call it a conference.
Earlier in this conference. We released Tooling.Report.
This is a website. It looks at all the different JavaScript
bundling build tools.
Shows the things they're good at and things they're not so
good at. But in this session, we are going to write our own
plugin.
Right. So cruising around the web, we see lots of sites
with performance issues.
And a lot of times these can be solved with something
simple, like a preload tag for a web font
or some selective code splitting.
But the thing is, when these are controlled by a build
system or even, like, deep in layers within a build system,
making those changes can be really tricky.
So supposedly simple changes can start to seem impossible.
Yes. But once you are familiar with writing build plugins,
sure, that means you can write build plugins.
But it also gives you like insight into how the build tool
works. It makes it easier to debug things when they go
wrong. And of course, it means that you can go and help
with community plugins as well and do PRs and add features
and fix bugs, that kind of thing.
Definitely. So we're going to create the same plugin for
Rollup and then for webpack.
Just because those are the two most popular and growing
build tools that we've seen.
So what are we actually building?
We are going to build a service worker plugin.
Of course, we're going to build a service worker plugin.
So the actual subject matter of a service worker
plugin itself doesn't matter all too much.
We picked this because it touches on a couple
different parts of the build process.
So it's one of those things that seems simple on the
surface. But there's actually quite a bit of complexity
when you dig in.
Right. So here's the app.
Now we're going to go through the whole app, but it has
JavaScript, CSS, images, and HTML, all
of which are part of the build process.
Right. So the bit that we care about for this session is
specifically the registering of a service worker.
So the URL of a service worker should never change.
And that's because we need to be able to go and check for
updates at that URL, but it'd be really nice if we didn't
have to duplicate that URL here and
in our build configuration and on disk.
And instead that was just filled in by the build system.
So here's a code for the service worker.
We're not going to go over all about how service workers
work. There are articles for that, but here are the things
we need for this build system.
We need a list of URLs to cache.
So this should be our HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and images.
These are the things that a native app would ship as part
of its bundle. Now, we can't just hard
code these because the build system is going to change the
file name, it's going to make them cachable.
It might also code split as well, which is going to
generate a whole new JavaScript files that we didn't know
about in advance. So because we can't predict it, we
need to build tool to fill it all in.
Right. So we also need a version for
the cache. And this is because when we're installing a new
version of the app, we want to use a new cache.
That way, we don't potentially disrupt any current version
of the application that's in use, maybe in another tab.
And so because of that, we need the version to be unique
for each given set of assets.
Yes. And if we don't change the assets, the version number
should stay the same. But if we, say like, update the
HTML, the version number needs to change.
Easy, right?
Right. So the challenge is that we
really want the service worker to be part of the main
build. We want it to potentially take part in code
splitting. We want to minify it just like we would our
application JavaScript.
And also apply any other plugins and optimizations that we
have to that code.
The thing is, it also needs to know about the final build
result. And that is only available once the build
is finished.
OK. Here is how I would do this in Rollup.
We need to get that service worker URL.
So I'm going to import it.
Now, note it looks a little bit magic.
It's got this sort of fake URL scheme.
This divides people.
I really like this because I want this to look weird
if it's a special part of the build, because it means you
look at this code you like, huh?
That's odd. Yes, it is odd.
The build tool is going to do something special here.
It also means like if the build tool doesn't do something
special, it is going to fail really, really early.
But like I said, this divides people.
Jason. How do you feel about this?
I mean, I like this idea for the fail early reason.
Like, that's a nice thing. If you if you pull this code
into a new project, it's going to tell you, "Hey,
this isn't a thing". Which is sort of exactly the message
you would want to receive.
But I also like that, you know, on the right hand side
of that colon, it's still just a module path.
So it's it's really clear for you when you're visually
looking through. This is the special part.
This is the regular part.
Yes. So all we need to do now is create the
build plugin, I guess.
So here's the config. The Rollup config.
You've seen this before if you've used Rollup, I'm going to
import this new plugin and add its to our list of plugins.
Now, all we need to do is write it.
Rollup has a one pager on how to write plugins,
but it's quite a long page.
But I have to say that the API is really well-designed
and the documentation is really well written.
So let's get started.
This is what Rollup plugins look like.
It's a function that returns an object.
It has a name as part of that.
And that's for error handling and logging.
But everything else, the rest of the object uses methods
that are called throughout the build that they're
essentially callbacks.
Rollup calls them hooks because they'rer hooks into the
build process.
The first hook we're going to look at is resolveID.
This is called for every module that's loaded.
So it's going to be called for the main file there, but
it's also going to be called for this import and everything
it imports, including dynamic imports.
The ID you get is the raw, unedited
import ID, so that's going to start with the dot-slash in
this case.
And in this case, it's going to include our special made up
URL scheme as well.
The second argument is the importer.
This is the path to the module which did the importing.
And this is the only time you get this piece of
information.
The job of the resolver is to return a full absolute
ID that doesn't need the importer anymore.
So, you know, any relative paths should be turned into
absolute paths.
Now, if you've used Rollup before you'll know that
it doesn't support node modules out of the box.
You need to add a plugin to be able to do that.
It's an official plugin, but you still need to add it.
All that is is a resolveID hook.
It sees these bare modules and it goes, oh, okay, well,
I'll try and find that in node modules.
But also if you want to create like path aliases
to make them work in Rollup, all you need to do is create a
resolveID plugin.
So we don't need to do anything with this first import.
We just need to handle the second one with the special URL.
So here we go.
The first thing I'm going to do is just exit early.
If it doesn't start with that prefix, actually, we're going
to do that sort of thing a few times.
So I'm going to pop that in a variable up here.
It's going to come up time and time again.
So there's an early exit. And it means if it doesn't start
with that prefix, we can hand it off to other plugins or
the default Rollup stuff.
Now, I'm going to remove that prefix and resolve it.
'this.resolve', this is a Rollup API.
And what it says is, like, take this ID and go
and find it for me.
It couldn't do it by default before.
But now we've removed the prefix.
Off it goes. And that's going to actually pass it back
through all the plugins that do resolving, including
our own. But we're going to ignore it because it doesn't
have the prefix anymore.
But it means like if you have a service worker in node
modules or if you have like path
aliases, it will all just work.
So if there's no match, just bail, and
that will cause an error eventually because it means that
we couldn't find that service worker.
Otherwise, I'm going to add that prefix back on so we can
pick it up later on.
But now we have an absolute path to the service worker.
We have achieved a thing.
We can try and build it.
Here we go. (sad trombone) It's not going to work.
But you can see in that error message it's failed because
of that special prefix.
But the rest of it is an absolute path to
the file as it is on my system.
So all we need to do is tell it how to load that script.
This is another hook "load" it gets the ID
as it's been fully resolved.
Again, we want to ignore if it doesn't have that prefix and
let other plugins deal with it.
And what we need to do now is return the content for this
module. So we could just actually make the module,
I'm going to do that and the return "hello".
And now we've done that, the project will actually build.
It's going to turn that fancy custom import into
"hello".
This is kind of silly, but just knowing those two things,
knowing how to resolve and knowing how to load, you can do
all sorts with that, that you can do all sorts of cool code
generation, loading of your files, that sort of thing.
I guess it's not so what we set out to do.
But like, you could totally see how this is basically like
a constant plugin.
Yes, exactly. And I've built constant plugins, and
that's exactly how you do it.
But let's improve on that.
So instead of just returning "hello", we need to bring the
service worker into the build system and return
it's URL. To bring a file into a build and can use
emitFile. This is a Rollup API for adding stuff into
the build.
I'm going to say this is a chunk and that's telling Rollup
like, "treat this like a JavaScript entry point".
So it should be processed by all the same plugins that deal
with JavaScript like minifiers, code splitting, and all of
that sort stuff.
It could also be 'asset'.
And if it's an asset, that's that's like an image, CSS,
I don't know, WebGL shaders.
Anything that's not JavaScript essentially you can process
in this way.
I'm going to give it the ID and that's telling Rollup where
to find it. So we've removed the prefix again
and I'm going to give it a file name. And this is not
something you would usually do.
What this does is it overwrites the naming
system that Rollup would usually use because Rollup would
usually add a hash to this file.
But with service worker, you don't want its name to be
changing. You want it to be in a static location.
So that's how we achieved that.
Actually, I'd say this is this is something that you would
offer to the user as configuration.
So I'm going to do that. I'm going to add an option object
to the top here.
And I'm just going to like change the variable
down here. So it's using that.
So that means the user can change the path of the service
worker, the file name, all of that sort of stuff.
Now, what we need to do is get the URL for this file and
strap in. It's a bit of magic.
Woo! There it goes.
So I'm returning the import.meta, and
then this sort of magic string that ends in a file ID.
And we've got the file ID from emitFile.
Rollup will see this and it will turn it into a URL for the
resource. So here's what that looks like.
Here's the input and here's the output.
So it's created this URL object.
And it does that so it can create a relative
URL from this script to
the service worker. Because on the web, if you've got an
image tag with a source or whatever, or
when you're calling serviceWorker.register(), by default
URLs are relative to the page.
But Rollup doesn't know anything about the page.
So it creates this, this script relative URL.
You can actually configure this in Rollup.
So you can tell it, "Hey, all my stuff is actually at the
roots of the origin.
All you need to do is add a slash to the start".
And obviously that will clean up the code a bit.
It just doesn't do it by default.
But also in our build, we've got a service worker, so that
bit is working.
All we have to do now is deal with these two things, the
version and the assets.
We'll handle the the assets first.
To do this, we need to know the full details of
the build. So because we need those hashed file names
and all of that sort of stuff.
So we need a hook that is towards the end of the build
process.
We're gonna use generateBundle.
This happens just before things are written to disk.
The options parameter, you know,
it's the output options. It's not very interesting for us
in this case.
But this, this is where
the party is at.
This is full of interesting details about
the build.
It's a JavaScript object where the key is the file name
and the object has details on the file.
So this is an asset. So you can see it's got a file name
and it's got a buffer representing the content.
But for chunks, look at all this all this stuff
we get. This is amazing.
It tells us things like the imports and the exports of the
file. I've used this and other plugins
if I'm generating HTML and I'm putting a script tag
on the page.
I know that that script is just going to import other
scripts and I want to preload those things.
Well, I can do that here.
So this will tell me which things it's going to immediately
import so I can turn those into preloads.
Anyway, loads of interesting info.
We're going to make use of this.
In the generateBundle hook, I'm going to get that service
worker chunk just from that output option, because that's
the file name of it.
And then we need to figure out which assets the
service worker needs to know about the things that it wants
to cache.
But iterate over the bundle, get the values, and I'm going
to get everything except the service worker item itself.
If a service worker caches itself like
it doesn't cause the world to end, like you might imagine,
it's it's just a bit wasteful.
We definitely designed around that.
We were worried people would do that.
So it's actually OK. But this is a point where people might
want to configure the things which are actually cached by
the service worker. So what I'm going to do is add another
option here. 'filterAssets' returns true by default.
And I'm going to call it down here.
Slight complicating factor.
We want these paths to be relative to the service worker
itself. And unfortunately, Rollup doesn't give us access
to it's URL resolving magic stuff.
I've filed a issue for that.
But we're gonna have to do ourselves this time.
So I'm going to use node's posix path resolving
stuff. Another reason I'm doing that is because posix paths
have the forward slash and that's the same as URLs.
So we can we can rely on that.
And then down here, this is how I curate the relative URLs.
This is done by saying "give me the relative path from
the folder that the service worker is in to the item
from the build".
And now we've got that.
I can prepend that to the file.
So this bundle object is live
in that any changes I make here are actually going to be
written to disk. So here I'm just taking the code for the
service worker chunk, adding that
assets line to the start, using JSON.stringify to correctly
escape everything.
And now that will be part of the service worker.
And if we build, there it is.
There it is in the output. The assets.
We've created a problem, though. And this is something
that catches a lot of people out when they're doing service
workers. It's this it's easy to think that the service
worker is caching files, but it's not.
It's caching URLs.
And we don't want .HTML in our URLs.
We don't want index.HTML in our URLs.
So we need to fix that.
Back in our plugin, this is where we were before.
How can we solve a problem like this?
Regular expressions. Of course, it's Regex.
I'm not going to go through how this works.
I see a back reference in there? I'm not even...
I love back reference.
I often say that regular expressions are write-only.
You can't read them again afterwards.
But trust me, this is removing the .HTML and it's removing
the index.HTML as well.
This could land us with an empty string, which is a problem
because that will resolve to the service worker script
itself. So in that case, just gonna output a dot.
And that solved the problem. There we go.
Index.HTML there is replaced with a dot.
OK. Last thing.
Just need to deal with that version thing.
Thankfully we're most of the way there already.
This is going to be a hash, so I'm going to include nodes
hashing stuff.
Down in the generate function, create one of these objects.
I picked 'sha1' because
I've heard of it before, and it wasn't MD5.
It's secure.
I'd heard it was worse. Yeah.
This is, this is very secure.
I mean, yeah, security doesn't matter in this case.
It's just, it's just for hashing.
Oh don't quote me on that. Like security generally matters.
[Laughing] Jake Archibald, security doesn't matter.
What a quote to take out of context!
OK, so now here I'm adding
everything to that hash.
So it's either the the source or
the code, depending on whether it's an asset or whether
it's a chunk.
And now I could get a hex version of that hash and
include it in the old output there.
And that's really it. That's it.
We can see that the hash is now in the service worker.
There's a couple of caveats here by
editing the source right at the end.
That was after source maps were generated.
So we have just broken source maps.
Just for the service worker.
I filed an issue with Rollup because
I would like there to be an easier way to do this.
So hopefully they can add something.
We could we could probably work around this by adding those
blank lines in a transformed step
so we can fill them in later because that that will -
those extra two lines at the top, will at least be taken
into consideration with the source maps.
I don't know. It would be good if there's a proper way of
doing this. But anyway.
That is it. That is the full plugin.
So, Jason, how would you do that
in webpack?
Right. So building plugins for webpack works a little
bit differently. And to illustrate this, I'm going to use a
fairly similar approach and naming to what we saw
in Jake's Rollup version.
Much like with Rollup, the place where we're gonna start
will be the bundler config.
Now, a typical webpack.config.js file specifies
some entry points, which are going to be the modules where
bundling starts.
Some options for the format and location of files
generated on disk and plugins, which is what we're
concerned with today.
All we need to do is import our plugin that we're going to
write and then add it to the plugin's array.
At its core, a webpack plugin is really just an object
with an apply method and that apply method gets passed
the compiler instance.
So wait one second. So this is like I see you using classes
here. So in Rollup, we were using the function which
returned an object. But in webpack land, it's it's all
class based?
So technically, webpack does not care.
It just needs an object with in the apply method.
But all of the webpack core modules
are classes. And I think as a result of that, all of
the ecosystem plugins tend to be classes just because
when people import it, they expect to instantiate with new.
You could totally write a webpack plugin that was a
function that returns an object.
I was even actually tempted to do that for this talk to
make it look more like the Rollup plugin.
But you know we'll stick with the thing people actually do.
All right. So if you member in Rollup, plugins
define special hook methods that get called in response to
events. In webpack, we do the opposite.
Your plugin taps into events.
And so what we want to do is want to handle a special
service-worker:import prefix.
And so to do that, we need to tap into normalModuleFactory.
And just to preempt because everybody gets confused at
this. Normal modules are source
modules. These are the code you write, the code you
get from NPM, code that you're going to put in your
application. There are other types of modules, which
is why there is other module factories for things like
loaders. Basically, they're more on the infrastructure
side of things. So if what we're looking to do here is
resolve our own import, we use normalModuleFactory.
And so similar with Rollup, anytime we tap into something,
we want to pass it a name, which is the name for our
plugin. And this gets used for debugging and logging
purposes. And also when taking performance profiles.
So within normalModuleFactory, we can
now hook into webpack's resolver.
And this gives us a reference to webpack's own resolve
function, which is the thing that sort of handles finding
modules and loading them from disk.
But it also lets us return our own custom resolver
function, which gets passed a dependency description
and a callback because it's asynchronous.
And so this function we can call the original
resolve function. We can do something custom, we can
combine the two.
To make things easier, we're just going to take those three
bits of information that we have and pass them to a new
resolveID method that we're going to write.
And that sort of everything we needed from apply.
So our resolveID method is going to be called
for each import specifier in the app
with a description of the dependency, that
original result function from webpack, and the callback to
call when we're done.
A dependency description is an object with context
and request properties.
Context is the directory of the module that's doing
the importing. So in this case, dot-slash and
request is the unmodified import specifiers.
So in this case, it includes our service worker prefix and
also the relative path to that file on disk.
So similar to Rollup, the first thing we want to do is
figure out whether this is an import that has our
prefix that we want to handle.
If it isn't, then we can just call webpacks original
resolve method. It will do what it would normally do.
Since there's no prefix, we don't really care about that
module.
But if it does have the prefix, we need to remove that
prefix and then pass it through resolve.
And so if the module can't be resolved, we can just forward
that error up. That will break the build.
There will be an error in the console saying, "Hey,
couldn't find module SW/index.js".
If it does work, then it'll pass us back a new dependancy
object where the request property is a fully resolved
disk path.
The thing is, we don't actually want to resolve this module
to a path.
Right. we want to resolve this module to a string somehow.
Right. This the string that contains the location of our
service worker.
And so to do that, we need to sort of - We need to come up
with a way of producing a virtual module.
Even though we're inside of the resolver.
Essentially, we want to intercept this service worker
prefix request and then resolve it to a module
that we create on the fly. It doesn't actually exist.
That just exports the string URL for our service worker.
And then one thing we do need to account for here is when
when we're working with URLs in webpack, we need to make
sure that we respect any webpack public path
magic global that has been set.
And so this is either the output.public_path
configuration value or some value that has been set
at runtime.
Right. OK. So this is this is another difference from
Rollup. So Rollup had to do some of the magic
around, like, you know, resolving URLs
and stuff, whereas here you've just got a string,
which is like where in the webroot is it.
Right. Yeah. So like Rollup.
You know, they have automation here to sort of give
you module relative paths.
In webpack, it's a configuration value.
And the nice thing is, you know, because everybody
uses that configuration value, all plugins tend to respect
it. So here, if we combine these two strings, we'll get
the slash, which is sort of our default webpack public path
value. And that means that the result of this import
will be the service workers
URL. The thing is, we haven't actually explained how to
construct a virtual module yet.
We know what we want to do.
We don't know how to do it.
So first, we want to start with that code that we want to
generate. And you'll notice here, I've parameterised the
URL from that code string, and
that's because we want to make that configurable.
So in our constructor, we'll accept an output parameter.
The developer can pass us the URL to use.
We'll store that and then we can inject it into our code
by JSON.stringifying it, which will escape it and
wrap it in quotes.
Then the last bit is to take our piece of code and pass
it back to webpack and to do this.
We're going to use something called RawModule
and we're going to import this from webpack core.
So RawModule is basically
a way for us to provide code back to webpack in the same
module format as it
would expect modules loaded from disk.
And the reason why this matters is we need to provide
webpack with an object that has a source method
that returns is a code string and an identifier
method that returns some sort of a unique identifier for
that module. In our case, based on the code string.
And in doing this, webpack will actually grab the code that
we send back to it and avoid ever going to disk to resolve
this module. It will just use whatever we pass.
So now we have our import resolving to the
URL of the service worker, but that URL doesn't exist
because we have not yet generated our service worker.
Let's do that.
For this, we need a new plugin hook.
And so when we need a new plugin hook, we have to jump back
in to Apply.
We need information that's going to be
codified into the service worker, those version and assets
globals. And to get this, we need to tap into something
that happens at the end of the build, once that information
is available.
So for this, we can use the emit hook.
You'll also notice we're using tapAsync here.
And this is because our emit hook is going to be
asynchronous. And we want a hold back compilation until
we're done working.
So the emit hook gets past a compilation instance
and a callback, which we're going to forward onto a new
method just to keep things clean.
In webpack, each compile pass is referred to as a
compilation, and the main thing that we're interested here
is the generated assets, which are an object
where the keys are file names and the values
are asset descriptors.
I recognize this. This is the same as the Rollup
bundle thing, right?
Like we had in generateBundle.
Yeah, it's really similar. I don't think I actually
realized until we were sort of looking at these things side
by side. They contain really similar metadata.
So it has, you know, the dependencies.
And "is this an entry chunk?". And all that information.
It's also for both JavaScript and non JavaScript assets.
In both cases, there's a source method on
the asset descriptor that will return either a buffer
with the non JavaScript asset contents or
a string with the JavaScript code.
So we need a list of files for the service worker to cache
and to get that, we could just take the keys of the assets
object.
Similar to with the Rollup plugin, though, it's generally a
good idea to make it possible to filter these assets before
they get embedded into the service worker just to avoid a
huge list.
So we'll add a filterAssets constructor parameter
that a developer can set and provide a function that takes
a file name and returns a boolean indicating whether that
asset should be in the list.
Now we have our list of asset file names.
The next step is to calculate a version based on a hash of
their contents.
And so to do this, we need to
pull in the createHash method from node's crypto module.
Then we'll loop over each file name in our filtered list
and add its corresponding assets source, which will be that
code, string, or buffer to the hash content.
Then our version string is just going to be a hex digest of
the combined contents of all of those assets.
So that's the magic version global done.
Now we can do the assets magic global.
So as Jake explained in the Rollup walkthrough our assets
array contains file names, but our service worker needs to
work with URLs.
And so to fix this, we need to prepend any configured
public path value to the names in
case we're deploying somewhere that isn't the root domain.
Right, so this is it again, this is gonna be simpler than
it was with the Rollup case, because you can just got this
string that you can add to the start.
Right. So because everyone knows to configure that public
path, we can basically count on it being there.
If it's unsent, we'll just use slash, but we're gonna be
able to resolve these things at build time.
So I'm showing some of my biases here.
But like, I think this is way
more complicated than the Rollup solution.
But it's interesting seeing these little details that
like I'm like, "Oh, I wish I wish Rollup had that!".
I mean, I know why it doesn't, but oh that would be so much
simpler for me if it just had like a public path,
like string or whatever.
Yeah. Maybe that's part of Rollup adding that, you know,
exposing their built-in resolution is maybe there is an
option you could pass that's like, "Oh by the way, like
resolve it all against this public path".
That might be a convenient thing.
Who knows.
So while we remap all of those file names to prepend
that public path, we can also remove any
trailing index.HTML, because that doesn't appear in URLs.
We want to cache the URLs not the file names.
And we will use that dot workaround to safeguard
against an empty string actually caching the service
worker, which we don't want, instead, we'll have it catch
the directory the service worker is in.
So that's both of our magic globals prepared for the
service worker. Now it's time to generate it.
And here we're going to create one last function to handle
compilation of the service worker.
So to build our service worker module, we're going to use
something called a child compiler, which is essentially a
nested webpack compiler.
And we'll configure this to output this
sw.js file.
And one thing to think about when using child compilers
is they can have a completely different list of plugins
compared to the main compiler.
So we can pull in a plugin that generates worker
compatible code because we have a service worker target.
So this could be a difference as well, isn't it?
Because, like - Well, actually, you tell me.
Because you're using a child compiler and
it's like a whole different pass.
Does that mean that this service worker bundle is not going
to be able to share code with the main bundle.
It's not going to be up to code split there.
Correct. Yeah. So any split points that end up happening
in the code generated by this child compiler are going
to be totally independent from the main compiler.
They'll be a separate set of files.
That's an important difference between the two.
I mean, it's not common to share code between your service
worker and main thread, but the Rollup version could
do that.
Yeah, exactly.
So the other thing that worker template will do in this
case is, if there are split points, rather than
using a script tag to load those chunks
of code, it will use import scripts, which is available in
workers.
Cool.
And so the last thing we need is a second plugin.
Also imported from webpack core.
And this just lets us specify the entry module
to start compiling from.
Which is, in this case, our service worker source module.
So finally we run our compiler as a child
of the main compiler.
And this just ensures that if our compiler takes a while to
run, the main compiler won't finish and terminate the
process before we're finished.
And then once it's built, the callback will be called with
our compilation.
And also any error.
So just like with the emit hook, we are going to grab the
generated service worker asset from compilation.assets
and then we can pass that back to emit.
If there was an error in the child compiler say, you know,
a syntax error in our service worker code, we'll just
bubble that up. That will fail the build and print it to
console.
If there wasn't an error, we do now have our compiled
service worker asset.
The thing is, it doesn't yet have version and assets
magic global variables.
So to inject those, we need to pull in something called
ConcatSource from the webpack-sources module.
And this lets us concatenate strings essentially.
It's very similar to string concat, but with the
added benefit of, it is able to produce
source maps.
Ah yes.
OK, so this is interesting because I broke source maps in
my solution.
But this, this is going to just, just work.
Now I could have done the same. In Rollup I could have
created essentially - It doesn't
support child compilers and such, but you can just call
Rollup as a sort of separate layer.
That would've been a lot more complicated.
So it's interesting now, like some of the complexity that
you're using here with webpack is actually
paying off.
Right. Yeah. So like the initial bundle of service worker
was harder. But as it turns out, it's the same number of
lines to support source maps as it is to not support
source maps. Now that you've opted into some of that
complexity. So that's sort of an interesting tradeoff
between the two.
So, yeah. So the last step, we've constructed this asset,
but it's only just an object in memory.
So what we need to do is merge it into
the compiler's generated assets.
Like with Rollup, this is a live object and anything that
we merge into here will get written to disk.
And so with that, our plugin is done.
So we can call the callback compilation will finish.
And what we get is our generated
service worker source.
We can see here that we have assets with
the generated array of URLs.
And we also have version which is that
string based on the hash of their contents.
So we did it.
Amazing. And that's it.
Yeah. And I guess that's that's bringing this talk to a
close. Provided that everything is recorded
properly and we don't have to do it again because I can't
tell you this recording has been absolutely cursed.
We have done so many takes due to just Bluetooth stacks
failing on my machine, recordings not happening on Jason's
machine. So who knows?
Maybe this will be the final record.
If you're watching this right now, then I am so happy
because it means we don't have to do all of this again.
Oh, right, OK.
If you want to see those implementations, they are both on
Tooling.Report along with how to handle assets, code
splitting, hashing, transformations, all of that stuff.
And not just webpack and Rollup as well.
We also have Parcel, and we also have
Browserify. Remember, Browserify?
And Gulp! And all of that sort of stuff.
I mean, you might laugh at that, but this
is if you look at the stats on NPM, that is still
absolutely huge and climbing.
So we did actually find some cases where it really holds
its own and was maybe better than some of the
more modern things that we deal with.
So go on and check all of that out.
Thanks so much for watching this.
Hopefully final take of this talk.