[Music]
[Applause]
hi everyone hope you're all staying safe
my name is Usain journey and I'm a
developer advocate on the web team at
Google for this segment of web dev live
we want to talk about different ways to
explore and analyze JavaScript undos on
a web page analyzing bundles is a good
first step to optimizing the amount of
JavaScript shipped to the browser which
can improve page load times and directly
result in better large example paint and
first input delay jobs the bundling is a
term commonly used to describe the
approach many websites take to group
multiple job script files or modules
into a single file or bundle
many tools that bundle JavaScript code
for the browser usually include a number
of different optimization steps such as
minification and sculpt wasting this is
a good thing because code written across
multiple files and modules can be
combined into a single optimized bundle
although this might be useful from a
developer and user experience standpoint
this process usually obvi skates
JavaScript code to the extent that it
can't easily be read and analyzed
without the help of additional tooling
let's take a look at some examples to
get a better idea if you're using Chrome
the network panel on the dev tools is
the easiest way to look at all the
JavaScript downloaded on a page open dev
tools by pressing ctrl shift J or
command obviously J on the Mac and click
the network tab to open the network
panel to take a look at all the network
activity during page load reload the
page while dev tools is still open
click the dogs good button to filter
requests by JavaScript and click any URL
to view the response by the format
button can make a minify file more
readable notice how with this simple
static site there's only a single jobs
file and although minified it's easily
human readable if we do the same for a
site that bundles the JavaScript code it
gets harder try
understand exactly what lives in the
bundle this is an example of a site that
bundles many third-party libraries and
hundreds of first party modules into
just a few discrete bundles so let's
take a look at some ways to analyze this
code the coverage tab can show you how
my JavaScript code is unused in any of
your files or bundles directly in dev
tools open the command menu with ctrl
shift P or command C SP for Mac type
coverage and select the show coverage
command click the reload button to
reload the page while capturing coverage
and in a drop-down menu select
JavaScript and the table the unused
bytes field shows exactly how much
javascript is unused for each file click
any URL to see a line by line break them
so although the coverage tab gives us a
lens of how much code is being used on a
page
it still isn't easy to identify which
modules make up the bundle now there are
other tools out there to make this
possible if you're already bundling code
for your site chances are you're using a
module bundler like web pack or roll-up
and many of these module by lenders
provide either first-class or a
third-party tooling that you can use to
visualize and map your bundles let's go
over an example if you use webpack you
can generate a staff JSON file that
contains statistics about all bundled
modules a single CLI command omits the
file
although reading this file yourself can
give us some information about what
modules live in the bundle there are
community build libraries that can
consume this file and display a more
useful visualization
one such library is called WebP at bonds
landlines and it works by parsing the
bundles generated by web pack and then
mapping them to the module names in this
task JSON file
by doing this it creates an interactive
tree map visualization of an entire
bundle showing the sizes of each module
as well as the relation to each other
gzip and parse sizes are also displayed
to give you a better idea of how large
each of the modules are bundler specific
visualization tools
Green they make it easier to see what
makes up each of your bundles but they
are blunder specific for any site
regardless of whether a specific module
Bunder is used or not source maps are a
way to map original written code to
transform the output this is useful
because it allow us to continue to
obfuscate and transform our code during
the build process but still have a means
to map it back to its original form
Java's new files that have been
transformed Duty minification or other
bundling optimizations need to point to
the location of a source map file with a
source mapping URL comment or a source
map HTTP header all newer browsers
support source maps and with chrome you
can enable it in the dev tools by
opening up settings and checking the
enable JavaScript source Maps option
when chrome can detect that of source
map it's available and also a message
and we're able to open and debug these
separate associated files as regular
JavaScript files source map Explorer is
the library that you can use to see a
tree map visualization of the bundle
this visualization is an example of
using source map Explorer with a
production tool just by looking at this
we can identify a few issues already a
few common GS models here moment J s and
lo - are already larger than they need
to be if they were switched to use es
modules they could be smaller and more
optimized there are duplicate copies of
react and code needed from multiple
different routes all live in this bundle
and they could easily be lazy loaded
into their own separate bundles these
are all common issues than many sites
run into and we can spot them by using a
visualization tool like source map
Explorer other tooling that you may
already be familiar with are also
starting to consume source maps in
different ways that can be useful light
house an open source website auditing
tool is currently experimenting with
source map support for some of these
audits with source Maps the unused
JavaScript audits to show how much
onions code and potential savings live
in bundled modules there's also a new
legacy jobs audit being developed that
takes advantage of source maps to show
legacy code within the bundle that
contains polyfills and newer browsers
don't need and there we have it we just
went over a number of different
techniques to analyze bundle JavaScript
code to recap the network panel and dev
tools is the easiest way to start seeing
how much JavaScript code is being
downloaded the coverage tab could show
you how much javascript is actually used
many module bundlers have supported
tooling and make it easier to visualize
bundles if you use webpack for example
you can administer a JSON file and use
webpack bundle analyzer consider
enabling source maps on your site and
use source map Explorer to visualize
your bundles if you'd prefer not to omit
source maps from production you can set
it up as part of your build process so
that it's only generated during
development and lighthouse is also
working collecting source maps to
display more useful audit
recommendations these changes will land
in a future version so keep an eye out
so analyzing your bundles and limiting
the amount of JavaScript in a web page
reduces the amount of time the browser
needs to spend parsing compiling and
executing JavaScript code the speeds up
how fast the browser can begin to
respond to any user interactions
improving first input delay and results
in a fast render improving largest
content paint thanks for watching I hope
you found this screencast super useful
[Music]
[Applause]