[Music]
[Applause]
hi everyone my name is Thomas and today
I want to talk to you about the
explorations that we've been doing with
the zoom team over the past few months
and some of the specific advanced api's
that we've been exploring together as
you've all probably seen zoom has become
a staple in many homes and so it's
critical that we're able to provide a
good experience directly through the
browser zoom does have a web version
today but compared to its native client
it's missing some features and sometimes
misses the mark in performance we wanted
to change this and so even before Cova
did we started working with the zoom
team to understand exactly what changes
they would need and what new things in
chrome they would want to create a truly
great experience now zooms of course a
video conferencing application you can't
talk about video conferencing on the web
without talking about WebRTC WebRTC is a
really great full-stack solution that
provides a complete package for
achieving video conferencing on the web
web RTC was build and standardized about
10 years ago and now ships in all major
browsers this makes it the best choice
if you want a complete solution with
broad support across browsers WebRTC is
strength of being that complete solution
can however also be a challenge for
someone like zoom who have their own
custom protocols and their own
architecture zoom would rather want a
set of more simple low-level api's that
they can then build their own
architecture and system on top of
themselves and the three specific ones
that we've been exploring and that I
want to talk to you a little bit about
today are webassembly sim D web
transport and web codecs I'll mention
from the start that all of these are
fairly cutting-edge and most of them are
in active development so while they're
all in a place where you can start to
play with them these aren't shipping
api's just yet but hopefully this
presentation will cover some of the
early parts of it and by the time you're
watching this it might be in the future
and you'll be able to actually use these
directly and lock already shipped so
first of all I want to talk about
webassembly sim D and how it can provide
really highly performant code most of
you have probably heard about
webassembly already but as a recap web
assembly is a new low-level binary
format for the web that is compiled from
other languages and offers maximized
performance
this means that you can take something
like C++ or rust and then compile it
into web assembly the
for shipping it to the client
webassembly has been out for a while and
has been shipping in all major browsers
for a while but we're continuing to
expand it with functionalities such as
Cindy which stands for single
instruction multiple data to explain
Cindy let's look at this incredibly
simple loop that just adds two arrays
together without Cindy the CPU would go
through this loop and add their
different elements together one by one
requiring four full steps but with Cindy
the CPU is able to vectorize these
elements and then take just a single CPU
operation to add them the best part is
that because compilers are so smart they
can automatically detect these
optimizations and do them for you in
unscripted you just need to pass the -
MMD 128 argument - EMCC and for rust you
can pass - c target feature equals plus
70 128 this will cause the compilers to
automatically find and use Cindy where
possible sometimes you also want to have
more explicit control and this is where
you'll want to use Cindy intrinsics
which let you use the Cindy instructions
directly this is more detail than I can
cover here but if you're interested I
highly encourage you to go and check out
these links simply it can be used for a
huge variety of things including highly
performant ml models such as this hand
tracking a real life invisibility cloak
and real time automated background
removal and this last use case is just
one of the things that zoom is excited
about using Cindy for they have an
awesome feature where you're able to
automatically remove the background so
that people and conferences can't see
all the random stuff that you have in
your background and then replace it with
fun videos or animations if you're
interested in diving into webassembly
and Cindy here are some of the links
that should help you get started
webassembly cindy is doing an origin
trial in chrome m84 which will start
rolling out to users in July 14th if you
aren't familiar with origin trials it's
basically a mechanism for you to test
out features with production users while
we may still be making some changes to
the API you can read more about those
origin trials at this link as well so
the next IPI I want to get into is web
transport which is a next-generation
networking
pi4 client-to-server communication let's
look at the definition of web transport
web transport provides bi-directional
transport through both unreliable data
grams and reliable streams based
mechanisms that's a mouthful but let's
see if we can't break it down and
understand it a bit better first
bi-directional means that it enables
easy two-way communication with
something like HTTP the connection has
to be initiated by the client and you
have to send all of the requests at once
and then wait for a response
with web transport you don't have these
limitations and so you can enable a much
more interactive session looking at the
two different mechanisms unreliable data
grams are one of the mechanisms for
sending data through web transport these
datagrams are similar to UDP data grams
in that they are packets of information
that gets sent but with no guarantees
about delivery or ordering reliable
streams in contrast are similar to TCP
streams and provide reliable and ordered
data communication so now that we have
an understanding of the definition of
web transport let's understand what you
might actually use it for firstly web
transport will be the only mechanism to
do unreliable data communication without
leveraging WebRTC and this is exactly
why zoom is interested in looking into
web transport because it'll allow them
to simplify their deployment and put it
a little more in line with the other
platforms that they support it's
important to note though that web
transport won't be just a pure UDP
sockets API since it does have some
requirements around encryption and
congestion control it does offer an
alternative to WebSockets and to
understand exactly how it compares to
WebSockets and WebRTC let's look at this
chart so to understand the differences
let's dig into each of these pieces
first web transport and WebRTC offer
both reliable and unreliable while
WebSockets only offer reliable delivery
web transport is a in-development API
while both WebSockets and web RTC are
widely available while
RTC provides a fairly high-level
complete solution to the problem of
video conferencing web transport and
WebSockets are both much lower level API
s that doesn't solve everything for you
but gives you more of that basic access
web transport also enables multiple
cancelable streams whereas WebSockets
can only do a single stream and web RTC
can also do multiple streams but they
aren't cancelable so here is a quick
example setup for how you can actually
use web transport in this part of the
code we really just set up our new quick
transport which is specific subtype of
web transport and create that object
passing in the URL that we want to
connect to then we just set up some
simple logging function and await the
transport being ready for us to use then
we can simply grab the writer from the
send datagrams function of our transport
object which we can then use to send
data at any point remember that this
data that we send does not have any
guarantees of delivery or the order that
it will be delivered in next let's look
at how you can actually read data from
the server here you see a simple example
where we get the reader from the get
reader function and then in a classic
while true loop we just read things from
that reader and then detect them when
we're done and console log out the
actual values that we're able to read
web transport is still very much in
development but we do have a blog post
already published about how you can use
it and you can find that and more
information at these various links so
now it's time for us to jump in to our
last and exciting API the web codecs API
which aims to offer direct codec access
on the web but first let's back up and
remind ourselves what exactly a codec is
a codec is a device or computer program
which encodes and decodes a digital
stream or signal while many of us have
not worked directly with codecs we've
all seen common examples like mp3 vp9
h.264 and many others codecs are
actually used in tons of places
throughout chrome such as the audio and
video tags Web Audio WebRTC and the
media recorder API however in all these
places where it's used you can't really
configure and get pure access to just a
codec part for example Web Audio allows
for decoding a media file but needs to
work on the complete
file and doesn't support a streaming
based approach media recorder has some
controls but they're very high level and
you can't really configure it to support
extremely low latency use cases as
mentioned previously WebRTC does give
you a lot of this control but it needs
you to bring the whole package of WebRTC
along and without doing that it's hard
to get access to just the encoding and
decoding parts that you want as a result
of this lack of configuration some apps
have started compiling these codecs to
JavaScript and web assembly some of you
may remember that this is how the
awesome application screw Sh lets you
resize and we encode images this
approach is really cool and workable
today but has some specific drawbacks
specifically it increases your bundle
size lowers your the performance cause a
slower startup time and reduces the
power efficiency really what you want is
to avoid shipping these codecs all
together and just get the direct access
that you need through the codecs that
are already shipping as part of the
browser and that's exactly what the goal
of web codecs is and in their own words
the goal of web codecs is to provide web
apps with efficient access to built-in
both software and hardware media
encoders and decoders for encoding and
decoding media web codecs main advantage
is that it lets you get the direct
access that you need to again build your
own systems on top of the basic coding
access this completely unlocks some use
cases like video editing since you
really need that frame-by-frame access
and faster than real time encoding and
decoding to do this properly something
that's currently completely impossible
on the web platform
except for maybe shipping codecs with
web assembly additionally many existing
things that are possible today on the
web but only if you use WebRTC things
like cloud gaming live streaming and
video conferencing will get more
flexibility about how they can interact
with these codecs zoom for example is
looking into using this API in
conjunction with the web transport API
they're hoping that they'll be able to
take encoded video frames and send them
up to the server using web transport at
the same time that they'll be fetching
down encoded frames and then decoding
them to
to the client providing a really smooth
integrated experience next let's look at
some of the simple examples for how you
can use the decoder part of this here in
this canvas setup part we're really just
grabbing a canvases context and then
making this very simple function to
paint a video frame to that canvas from
converting it to an image bitmap now
when you want to set up the decoder part
you just call this new video decoder
element and you set up the output
function that we defined previously as
well as just constant logging out any
errors then you configure it with the
codec that you want to use and then you
have this incredibly simple function
that you just pass in your ending coded
chunk and called the decode function
from your video decoder and then it does
the rest of the work for you web codecs
is still extremely new but for those of
you who are curious you can go and check
out the explainer to see what the team
is currently working on we will also be
doing a web dev post about web codecs so
if you're seeing this in the future be
sure to go and check out that and that
brings us to our overview of these three
new exciting api's that we've been
exploring with zoom you've hopefully
getting a better understanding of some
of these new and advanced API s and
hopefully an understanding of how they
will be bringing all of us closer
together in the future thank you so much
for your time and I hope you enjoy the
rest of the sessions