[Music]
true or false
indexdb is limited to 25 Meg's false
gone are the days of tiny storage quotas
true or false
local storage should be avoided true
it's synchronous and may cause
performance issues by blocking the main
thread all right here's another one
true or false cookies are a great way to
store data false they've got their uses
but to never be used for storage how
about this one app cache is a great way
to make your app work offline yeah a
trick question absolutely false app
cache is awful and it's going away soon
thankfully so how should we be storing
data and caching our critical app
resources on the client how much can we
store how does the browser deal with
eviction and be sure to stick around to
the end and I'll tell you how you can
start Chrome with only a tiny storage
limit so you can test what happens when
you exceed your storage quota I'm Pete
LePage let's dive in to storage on the
web modern storage makes it possible to
store more than two small chunks of data
on the user's device even in perfect
wireless environments caching and other
storage techniques can substantially
improve performance reliability and most
importantly the user experience with the
cache storage API you can cast your
static app resources like HTML
Javascript CSS ensuring that they're
always instantly available and with
indexdb you can store all kinds of data
article content users document settings
and more index DB and the cache storage
API are supported in every modern
browser
they're both asynchronous and will not
block the main thread they're accessible
from the window object web workers and
service workers making it easy to use
them anywhere in your code there
several other storage mechanisms that
are available in the browser but they've
got limited use and may cause
significant performance issues if you're
concerned about storing large amounts of
data on the client
don't be unless you're trying to store
several gigs modern browsers typically
won't even bat an eye and even then it
really comes down to the amount of disk
space available on the device
of course implementations vary by
browsers Firefox allows an origin to
store up to two gigs Safari allows an
origin to use up to one gig and when
that limit is reached Safari is
currently the only browser
that'll prompt the user to increase that
limit and Chrome well look it's a little
complex but stick with me here chrome
and most other chromium based browsers
limit storage to 80% of the total disk
space and each origin can only use 75%
of that for example if you had a 10 gig
hard disk chrome with limited storage to
8 gigs then each origin would be limited
to 6 gigs essentially each origin will
be allowed to use up to 60% of the total
disk space it sounds complex but there's
an easy way to see what's available in
many browsers you can use the Storage
Manager API to determine the amount of
storage that's available to the origin
and how much storage that you're already
using it reports the total number of
bytes used and makes it possible to
calculate the approximate bytes
remaining unfortunately the storage
manager API isn't implemented in all
browsers yet so you must use feature
detection before using it but even when
it is available
you still need to catch over quota
errors in some cases and I'm looking at
you Chrome it's possible for the
available quota to exceed the actual
amount of storage available most
chromium based browsers factor in the
amount of free space when reporting the
available quota chrome does not though
and it will always report 60% of the
actual disk size this helps to reduce
the ability to
the size of stored cross-origin
resources so what should you do when you
go over quota most importantly you
should always catch and handle right
errors whether it's a quota exceeded air
or something else then depending on your
app design decide how to handle it for
example delete content that hasn't been
accessed in a long time or remove data
based on its size or provide a way for
users to choose what they want to delete
both indexdb and the CAF api throw a dom
error named quota exceeded error when
you've exceeded the quota available for
indexdb the transactions on abort
handler will be called passing an event
that event will include a Dom exception
in the error property and if you check
the name of the error it'll return quota
exceeded error for the CAF API rights
will reject with a quota exceeded error
Dom accept some data stored in the
browser can be cleared in a couple of
ways it's most commonly initiated by the
user choosing to clear data in the
browser's site setting panel but it can
also happen when faced with storage
pressure like load disk space in this
case browsers typically automatically
delete data from the least recently used
origins and continue to delete that
until the storage pressure has been
relieved if the app hasn't synced data
with the server it will cause data loss
and means that the app won't have the
resources needed to run both of which
can lead to a negative user experience
thankfully research by the chrome team
shows that this doesn't happen very
often and it's far more common for users
to manually clear storage thus if a user
visits your site often the chances are
small that data will be deleted let's
take a look at a specific example of how
automatic eviction might happen in
chrome origin a is the least recently
visited site origin B is the next least
recently visited site and so on
origin e and
George and Kay are getting close to
their quota limits but they haven't
reached it yet and the overall usage is
less than the total quota so nothing is
gonna be evicted origin B has a star
next trip because it was granted
persistent storage meaning that it can
only be deleted by the user check out my
article on web dev for more info about
persistent storage when you should be
using it and how to request it now let's
say the user visits Origin n again which
happens to be a music playing site the
user saves a few more songs for offline
listening
now each origin is still within its
quota limit but Chrome has exceeded the
overall limit to get back under the
overall limit chrome will start evicting
stored data from the least recently used
origin first and continue until it's
back under the total limit Firefox and
other chromium based browsers work in
essentially the same way Safari is a
little different when it's out of
storage it will prevent anything new
from being ready but they recently
implemented a new 7-day cap on all
writable storage including indexdb
serviceworker registrations and the
cache API this means that after using
Safari for seven days and not
interacting with the site it will evict
all content for that site this eviction
policy does not apply to progressive web
apps that have been added to the home
screen essentially installed pwace check
out the WebKit blog linked in the
description for complete details modern
computers typically have large hard
drives which makes it hard to test the
over quota failures so here's a little
pro tip create a small RAM disk here
I've created a 500 mega on my Mac then
start Chrome using the user data der
flag this tells chrome to store the user
profile and user data on the RAM disk
Chrome now thinks my disk is only 500
Meg's thus is gonna limit my storage
quota to only three hundred Meg's which
I can quickly fill this makes it much
easier to verify that my code behaves
properly when it hits those quota
exceeded errors chrome dev tools also
have
helpful features for understanding
what's going on with the data that
you've stored in the application panel
the clear storage panel will show you
how much storage you're using for the
origin and makes it easy to clear some
or all of that data that you've got
stored the storage panel lets you see
what's in local and session storage as
well as what's in index DB including the
actual databases and even the individual
entries and the CAF storage panel shows
you what's stored in cache storage gone
are the days of limited storage and
prompting the user to store more and
more data using the cache storage API
and indexdb you can effectively store
all the resources that your app needs to
run be sure to check out my article
storage for the web where I've got
additional details and info on some of
them not so good storage mechanisms then
check out my article on persistent
storage to learn how you can protect
your data from being blown away even
when the device is facing storage
pressure see you soon
[Music]