[Music]
[Applause]
back in March 2003 Nick Fink and Steve
champion stunned the web design world
with the concept of progressive
enhancement a strategy for web design
that emphasizes core web page content
first and that then progressively adds
more nuance and technically rigorous
layers of presentation and features on
top of the web content while in 2003
progressive enhancement was about using
at the time
modern CSS features unobtrusive
javascript or even scalable vector
graphics progressive enhancement and
20/20 is about using modern browser
capabilities my name is Thomas Tanner
I'm a developer advocate based out of
the Google Hamburg office today I want
to talk about progressively enhancing
like it's 2003 building for modern
browsers since we all can be here
together in person due to the
coronavirus I've converted my talk into
an online trip that I want to take you
on with me for this trip you need a
solid understanding of JavaScript
talking of JavaScript the browser
support for the latest quod JavaScript
features is great promises modules
classes template literals arrow
functions you name them all supported
basic functions work across the board in
all modern browsers and even super
recent language editions like optional
chaining and knowledge coalescing reach
support really quickly when it comes to
CRO JavaScript features the grass
couldn't be much greener than it is
today for the trick that we are going on
the likeness should have a good
understanding of progressive web apps
for this talk I work with a simple PWA
called fugu greetings the name of this
app is a hat tip to project fugu where
we work on giving the web all the powers
of native applications you can read more
about the project at web tour death
slash food - status
fugu breedings is drawing up that allows
you to create virtual greeting cards
just imagine you actually had traveled
to Google i/o and wanted to send a
greeting card to your loved ones let me
recall some of the pwe concepts
fool greetings is reliable and fully
offline enabled so even if you don't
have Network you can still use it it can
be installed to the home screen of the
device and it integrates seamlessly into
the operating system as a standalone
application with this out of the way
let's dive into the actual topic of this
talk progressive enhancement starting
each greeting card from scratch can be
really cumbersome so why not have a
feature that allows users to import an
image installed from there with a
traditional approach you have used an
input type file element to make this
happen first
you'd create the element set its ID and
the to be accepted mine types and then
programmatically click it and listen for
changes and it works perfectly fine the
image is imported straight onto the
canvas when there is an import feature
that probably should also be an export
feature so users can save their greeting
cards locally similar to before the
traditional way to saving files is to
create an anchor link with the download
attribute and with the blob URL as it's
a trove you would then programmatically
click it to trigger the download and to
prevent memory leaks from happening
hopefully make sure not to forget to
revoke the blob URL but wait a minute
mentally you haven't downloaded a
greeting card you have saved it rather
than showing you a safe dial-up that
lets you choose where to put the file
the browser instead has directly down on
the greeting card without interaction
and it's put it straight into your
downloads folder
this isn't good what if there were a
better way what if you could just open a
local file edit it and then save the
modifications either through a new file
or back to the original file that you
had initially opened turns out there is
a better way the native file system API
allows you to open a grade files and
directories make modifications and save
them back let's see how it can feature
detect if the API exists the native file
system API exposes a new method choose
file system entries I can use this to
conditionally load
import image MJS and export image MJS if
the API exists and if it isn't available
load the files with the legacy
approaches from the earlier slides but
before I dive into the native file
system API let me just quickly highlight
the progressive announcement pattern and
browsers that don't support
file system API hello the legacy scripts
you can see the network tabs of Firefox
and Safari here
however on Chrome only the new scripts
are loaded this is made elegantly
possible thanks to dynamic imports that
all modern browsers support as I said
earlier the grass is pretty green these
days let's look at the actual native
file system API based implementation for
importing an image I call window choose
file system entries and pass it an
accept option parameter where I say I
want image files both file extensions as
well as mime types are supported this
results in a file handle from the file
handle I can obtain the actual file by
calling its get file method exporting an
image is almost the same but this time
you need to pass a type parameter save
file to the choose file system entries
method so I get a file save dialog
before this wasn't necessary since Open
File is the default I said the accept
parameter similar as before but this
time limited to just PNG images again I
get back a financial but rather than
getting the file this time I'm creating
a writable stream by calling crate
writable next I read the blog which is
my greeting card image to the file
finally I close the writable screen
everything can always Fame the disc
could be Arg space there could be a
write or read arrow or maybe simply the
user cancels the file a lot this is why
I always read the calls in a try-catch
statement I can now open the file as
before the imported file is drawn right
onto the canvas I can make my edits and
finally save them with a real save
dialogue where I can choose the name and
storage location of the file now the
file is ready to be preserved for the
eternity about from storing files for
the eternity maybe I actually want to
share my greeting card this is something
that the web share and web share target
API is allow me to do mobile and more
recently also district operating systems
have gained native sharing mechanisms
for example here is safaris share sheet
on Mac OS triggered from an article on
my side block Tommy icon and click the
share button you can share a link to the
article with a friend for example by the
native messages
the code to make this happen is pretty
straightforward I call navigator dot
share and pass it an optional title text
and euro but what if I want to attach an
image whether one of the web share a P I
that you can see on the screen doesn't
support this yet the good news is that
web share level two has added file
sharing capabilities let me show you how
to make this work with a fool greeting
card application first I need to prepare
a data object with a files array
consisting of one blob and then a title
and a text next as a best practice and
the use of the new navigator dot can
share method but does what its name
suggests it tells me if the data object
I'm trying to share can't technically be
shared by the browser if navigator can
share tells me the data can be shared
and in the final step ready to call a
navigator dot share that's before again
everything can fail in the simplest way
when the user cancels the sharing
operation so it's all wrapped in
try-catch blocks as before I use a
progressive enhancement loading strategy
if both share and can share exists on a
navigator object only then I go forward
and load shared on MJS why a dynamic
import on browsers like mobile safari
that only fulfill one of the two
conditions
I don't load the full functionality if I
tap the share button on a supporting
browser the native share sheet opens I
can for example choose
Gmail and the email composer Richard
pops up with the image attached up next
I want to talk about contacts and when I
say contacts I mean contacts as in the
devices address book when you write a
greeting card it may not always be easy
to correctly write someone's name for
example I have a friend who prefers the
name to be spelled in Cyrillic letters
I'm using a German qwertz keyboard and I
have no idea how to type their name this
is a problem that the contact picker API
sells since I have my friends stored in
my phone's contacts app by the contacts
picker API I can tap into my contacts
from the web first I need to specify the
list of properties I want to access in
this case I only want the names but for
the use cases I might be interested in
telephone numbers emails avatar icon or
physical addresses next I configure an
options object and set multiples to true
so you can select more than one account
finally I can call navigator
contacts that select which results in
the desired properties once the user
selects one or multiple of their
contacts in fugu greetings when I tap
the contacts button and select that two
best pals said again makarevich Bryn and
Laurence Edward Larry Page you can see
how the contacts picker is limited to
only show their names but not their
email addresses or other information
like their phone numbers the names are
then drawn onto my greeting card and by
now you probably learned the pattern I
only load the file when the API is
actually supported up next is copying
and pasting one of our favorite
operations as software developers is
copy and paste as greeting card
elephants at times and I want to do the
same either paste an image into a
greeting card and working on or on the
other way around
copy my greeting card so I can continue
editing it from somewhere else the I
simplified API about from text also
supports images let me walk you through
how I have added copy and paste to the
fugu breeding set in order to copy
something onto the system's clipboard
you need to write to it the navigated
clipboard right method takes an area of
clipper items as a parameter
each kept one item essentially as an
object with a blob as a value and the
blocks type as the key to paste I need
to loop over the clipboard items that
are obtained by calling navigated or
clipboard Audrey the reason for this is
that multiple clipboard items might be
on the clipboard in different
representations each clip pod item has a
types field that tells me in which mine
type the resource is available I simply
take the first one and call the
clipboard items get a type method
passing the mime type I obtained before
and almost needless to say by now I only
do this on supporting browsers so how
does this work here I have an image open
and the Mac OS preview app and copy it
to the clipboard when I click paste the
fugu breeding zap then asks me what I
want to allow the app to see texts and
images on the clipboard finally after
accepting the permission the images then
paste it into the application the other
way round works to let me copy a
greeting card to the clipboard when I
then open preview and click file and
then new from clipboard the greeting
card gets pasted into a new untitled
image another useful API is the badging
AJ
as an installable PWI fugu greetings of
course does have an app icon that users
can place on the app dock or the home
screen something fun to do with it in
the context of frugal greetings miss use
it as a pen stroke counter with a
batting okay it is a straightforward
task to do this I have added an event
less than that on pointed down
increments the pen strokes counter and
sets the icon whenever the canvas gets
cleared the counter resets and the badge
is removed in this example I've drawn
the numbers from 1 to 7 using one pen
stroke for each number the batch counter
on the icon is now at 7 this feature is
a progressive enhancement so the loading
logic is as usual want to start each day
fresh with something new a neat feature
of the fugu greetings app is that it can
inspire you each morning with a new
background image to study a breeding
card the app uses two prokaryotic
background sync API to achieve this the
first step is to register a periodic
sync event in the serviceworker
registration it listens for a sync tag
called
image of the day and as a minimum
interval of one day so the user can get
a new background image every 24 hours
the second step is to listen for the
periodic sync event in the serviceworker
if Devon Tech is the one that was
registered a slide ago the image of the
day is retrieved for the get image of
the day function and the result
propagated to all clients so they can
update their chemists and captions again
this is truly a progressive enhancement
so the code is only loaded when the API
is supported by the browser this applies
to both the client code and the
serviceworker code on lan supporting
browsers me of them is loaded note how
in the serviceworker instead of a
dynamic input I use the classic import
scripts function to the same effect
sometimes even with a lot of inspiration
you need a nudge to finish it started
reading code this is a feature that is
enabled by the notification triggers API
as a user I can enter a time and I want
to be nudged to finish my greeting card
and when the time has come and I get a
notification that my greeting card is
waiting after prompting for the target
time the application schedules a
notification with the show trigger this
can be a timestamp trigger with a
previously selected target date the
reminder notification will be triggered
locally no network or server-side is
necessary as everything else i've shown
so far this is a progressive enhancement
so the code is
me conditionally loaded I also want to
talk about the wakelock API sometimes
you need to just stare long enough on
the screen until the inspiration pieces
you the worst that can happen is for the
screen to turn off the way okay P I can
prevent this from happening in food
readings there's an insomnia checkbox
that when checked keeps your screen
awake in a first step they obtain a wake
lock with the Navigator table like dog
but request not a pass it the string
screen to obtain a screen leg lock I
then add an event listener to be
informed when the wake lock is released
this can happen for example when the tap
visibility changes if this happens I can
when this happens with will again we
obtain the wait look yes this is a
progressive announcement so you only
need to load it when the browser
supports the API at times even hysteria
the screen for hours is just useless the
idle detection API allows the app to
detect user idle time if the user's
detected to be idle for too long the app
resets to the initial state and clears
the canvas this API is currently gated
behind the notification permission since
a lot of production use cases of idle
detection or notification related for
example to only send a notification to a
device the user is currently actively
using after making sure that the
notifications permission is granted I
then instantiate the idle detector a
register an event listener that listens
for idle changes which includes the user
and the screen state the user can be
active or idle in a screen can be
unlocked or locked if the users detected
to be idle the chemist clears I give the
I detector a threshold of 60 seconds and
as always I unload this code and the
browser supports it whoo what a writer
so many ideas in just one sample app and
reminder we never make the use of pay
the download cost for a future that
their browser doesn't support by using
progressive enhancement and make sure
only the relevant code gets loaded and
since with HTTP 2 requests are cheap
this pattern should work well for a lot
of applications although at times you
might still want to consider a bundler
for really large apps this has been a
short overview of many of the ApS we're
working on in the context of project
Google definitely check out our landing
page they can find links to detailed
articles for each API that I've talked
about
if you're interested in FUBU greetings
go find and fork it on github and with
that thank you very much for watching my
talk you can find me as tomahawk on
github Twitter and the web in general
[Music]