[Music]
[Applause]
hi my name is Andrew bandeja and in this
video I'm going to show you how to use
your progressive web app inside an
android application without writing a
single line of native code progressive
web apps or petaboys
combine the reach of the web with the
capabilities that were almost available
to native apps if you are new to
petaboys read more about them on webdive
slash progressive - web - apps it is
natural that developers building great
petaboys
wants to reuse those experiences inside
their Android applications in the past
possible ways for developer to use their
progressive web app inside an Android
application included using the Android
webview or embedding a browser engine
the webview doesn't provide support for
many of the new capabilities on the web
like push notifications or web Bluetooth
so the output can be a super experienced
compared to the pdaboy it's built on
creating and maintaining an app with an
embedded browser requires a considerable
amount of engineering effort and
produces an app that's larger than a
native app equivalent at last year's
Google i/o we announced trusted web
activities which allow developers to use
their progressive web app inside an
android app in a full-screen tab that is
powered and has the same features and
capabilities as the browser providing
this leads to a small development cost
and application size even though Tercel
web activities provide a better
alternative for using a PWM site and
enter that developers to needs some
knowledge about native application
tooling and development so to create an
easier path for developers who want to
create their Android app using their
pdaboy excited we have created bubble
wrap emoji is projects that contains
both a library and a common line
interface developers can use to generate
and build their Android application in
the next few minutes I'd like to guide
you on how to
figure bubble wrap and use it to
generate an application from an existing
progressive web app I'm going to use
Romero woods persistence app as a
starting point but you can use any
existing progressive web app check the
video description for the link to the
persistence app who needs to modify the
application later so I'll open the app
scroll down and click on the code link
then I'm going to remix the project so
we can modify it we can get the link to
the remix tab by clicking on share then
live app and then copying the link we
are going to need that information soon
in order to use bubble wrap we need
node.js 10 or above installed on the
development computer and optionally an
Android device setup in developer mode
so we can test the application check the
link on the video description for more
information on how to setup on an
Android device for developer mode bubble
wrap builds on top of native SDK tooling
so we'll start by downloading the
Android common line tools and the Java
development kit or JDK version 8 to
download the Android common line tools
we can use the shortcut on the
bubble-wrapped CLI documentation which
is a linked on the video description
inside the page click on the link for
your operating system
accept the license and click on download
the bubble-wrap CLI documentation also
links the corrections version of the
Java development kit inside the page
choose your operating system event
architecture then download the
compressive tar file for the JDK in our
terminal we now create a directory where
we can place both dependencies then we
unzip the common line tools and then the
Java development kits make sure to take
note of the directories where those
files were decompressed as we're going
to need them later I like to rename the
JDK folder to just JDK as it's easier to
remember with the penisy is now ready we
can install bubble-wrap using NPM
install
with bubble wrap and its dependencies
now installed we can start the creation
of the Android app itself let's start by
creating a folder for it and now we can
initialize the Android project by
calling bubble wrap in it and passing
the URL to the web manifest to it
when bubble wrap runs for the first time
it will ask for the location of the JDK
and the Android common line tools we
downloaded previously while also
automatically installing order
dependencies then the CLI will ask you
to confirm values read from the web
manifest and fill in any missing
required values needed to create the
Android app we can for instance change
the Stars URL so that we can use Google
Analytics to measure how often our users
are opening the pdaboy from the Android
app Android applications needs to be
signed with a self-generated key in
order to be uploaded to the Play Store
if bogu rep is unable to find an
existing key it will prompt the
developer to grade one so let's go ahead
and create it and make sure to take note
of the password you choose finally we
can now invoke bubble wrap build to
build the project the comment will
output three important things the
quality criteria for the peter blake an
asset links that json file used to
validate the domain open and inside the
trusted web activity and assigned
android application that can be uploaded
to the place where bubble wrap would
check the quality criteria against the
URL used to launch the trusted web
activity we strongly recommend the
repeatable passes the called secret area
the quality criteria is measured using
lighthouse against the start URL and
consists of a minimum performance score
of 80 and getting the peelable a check
in order to be shown in full-screen
developers need to implement digital
asset links bubble-wrap takes care of
the configuration of the android
application but there is one extra step
that needs to be done in the web app the
content of the asset links to JSON file
to be made available on dot well-known
slash asset link JSON on the root of the
domain on my remix project I'll create a
dot well-known slash asset links to JSON
file then I'll paste the content of the
file generated by bubble-wrap into it
the application is now fully setup if
you have an Android device in developer
mode you can now connect it to the
computer and run bubble wrapping start
to launch the app congratulations you
have built an Android app when uploading
an application to the Play Store for the
first time you ask if the developer
wants to use app signing if opting into
app signing the Play Store will manage
the signing key for you making sure it's
not lost this is important as losing the
key means it's not possible to update
the application on the store anymore but
it also means that the final key used to
signed application will be different
than the one is generated by bubble wrap
to update the asset link start JSON file
we needs information on the key used by
the Play Store this information can be
found by clicking on the add links item
on the menu on the left and copying the
details for the fingerprint and using is
to update asset links dot JSON file on
the web app it is possible to use both
fingerprints in the application check
out the video description for a link on
how to add both case to the application
booboo wrap removes friction for web
developers who wants to open repeatably
in an android app I'm a fan of comma
line tools if you are more like a
graphical user interface person checkout
peel away builder it uses bubble wrap as
a library to power their Android
application generation and that's all
for bubble wrap today make sure to check
the github repo and drop us some
feedback and if you're watching this
live jump into our live chat and tell us
what you think thanks for watching
[Music]
[Applause]