Hi, I'm Una, a Developer Advocate on the Chrome team,
focusing on CSS and Web UX.
Thank you for joining me today. I am super excited to get
started and talk about some magical lines of CSS that
do some serious heavy lifting and let you build a robust
modern layouts.
Before we dive into that, there are a couple of key terms
that will help you in your styling journeys and are super
good to know about as we walk through these techniques.
Most of the items I mentioning today are used in
conjunction with grid or flexbox layout, and you
can denote those as display:grid or display:flex
on the parent element.
The first key terms are fr and auto.
These are used with grid layouts to denote fractional units
of space - that's fr, or automatic space - that's
auto - based on the minimum content size of the items
within that element. For grid layout, we also have
the minmax() function, which let's us set a minimum
and maximum value within our layout bounds to enable
responsive design without media queries!
We also have separate min(), max(), and clamp() functions
available in some browsers that bring logic to CSS.
The browser determines which value to choose based on the
function provided for min and max, and for clamp, we'd
set both a min and max, with a relative value in between.
We'll definitely be covering these within the video with a
demo.
And within these layouts, we can also use auto-fit or
auto-fill to automatically place child elements
into a parent grid.
This is another tool for dynamic, responsive layouts
without media queries.
We're going to be going over all of those terms and more
with demos galore.
I'm really big nerd and I don't know why I made that rhyme
and put that in this video, but I did so...
So let's just dive into the demos and 1-line
layouts. I made a handy little site called 1-Line
Layouts at 1linelayouts.glitch.me
so that you can follow along or play on your own and have a
reference for the power that CSS can bring to your layouts.
For our first 'single-line' layout, let's solve the biggest
mystery in all the CSS land: centering things.
I want you know it's easier than you think with
place-items:center, I call this the Definitely
Centered Layout.
What we need to do is first specify the layout method,
which is display grid here, and then we are going to write
'place-items: center' This is that one magical
line of code and I have these highlighted under the titles
here. So what happens here is no matter what you put
in here, it is going to stay centered to that parent
element. So if we look at the HTML we have
this parent and it's just getting background blue and then
this child with a coral background and it's contenteditable
so we can actually just type in here - we can have vertical
content, 'Hello, world' - and even as I'm typing,
this child element is staying centered within
the parent box. So I think that this is a really cool
technique. 'place-item: center' will solve all of your
centered dilemmas.
Next, we have the deconstructive pancake!
This is something that we see all the time on marketing
sites. You see this row of 3 items and usually
on mobile, we'll want that to be stacked, which is why I
called this the pancake stack, but deconstructed,
because as you increase the size
of the viewport, those items will start spanning into
the same line. So it starts when they're all on
top of each other and then they start to deconstruct as you
increase the size of the viewport.
So the way that we're going to be doing this one is using
the shorthand for flexbox - 'flex: 0 1 ' - is
what we will be using for this look that you're seeing
right now without the stretching.
But if we did want to stretch, we can set that to 'flex: 1
1 '. And the reason
why we do this is is because the flex shorthands stands for
flex-grow, flex-shrink, and then flex-basis.
So again, here we have 'flex: 0 1 150px'.
That is the basis here. So as we increase the size, it
is not going to be growing much.
Also, when we decrease it is going to be staying within
that 150px size.
When we do change that to 1, I'm just going to delete this
line of code here - now we see that this is going to be
stretching. So here you can see that it stretches to fill
the space even as it wraps.
And as I increase it to be even larger of viewport size,
these items are going to be filling that space.
So this is the deconstructive pancake, a really common
technique that we see in marketing sites.
This is usually going to be like an image with some text
about the product and you can write it by using the flex
shorthand.
I like to call this one Sidebar Says and it takes advantage
of that minmax() function for grid layouts.
So that is this line here.
We have grid-template-columns, minmax, and then
min and max value.
That's pretty straightforward with minmax.
But what this is doing is essentially as we're increasing
the size of the viewport, it's going to be taking that 25%
size, that max size.
And as we decrease it, it hits this point where its 150px
and where 25% is smaller than 150px,
so it's going to clamp it at that minimum size.
So it's going to be increasing when it can take up that
viewport space, but if we have content in here that we
don't want squeezed or we want to stop being 25%
and at a minimum be 150px or whatever value
we set here, then that is exactly what minmax()
is doing for us.
And in the grid-template-columns here we are writing
grid-template-columns, minmax, that face value, and
then the relative value, so 25%, and that second
element is getting 1 fr. So if we look at HTML, we have
these two elements, this yellow side bar section, and then
this purple content section.
And they are taking up the units of space that we are
specifying. In this specific case, we actually even set
this to auto, and it would be looking the same because
we are only saying the size to that first elements.
We're gonna go over auto versus 1 fr in the next example,
but I think that this is pretty neat.
A great way to set a minimum size, but then
let your elements stretch on larger viewports to
fit those layouts a little bit better, based on how
your user is seeing your website.
Next, we have the pancake stack.
Unlike the deconstructive pancake, this one does not shift
when the screen changes sizes.
This is a very common layout that we see for both
websites and applications across mobile and desktop
functions. So it looks like this, as we're increasing
and decreasing the size.
This content is not changing.
And what we are doing to create this is we are writing the
grid-template-rows to be auto, 1fr,
and auto. So what we are doing is essentially
telling the first and last row to take up
the space that the internal elements allow.
So if this header was two lines, then it's going to
increasingly take up more space within this
vertical layout.
With this auto section, I could have more content
here, but it's not going to increase the size because
what we're doing is setting the auto placed
row first to take up that specific size based
on the content within it.
And then the remaining space is remaining fractional units.
So as we increase this also vertically, you could
see that the first and last row are not
growing. They're still only gonna be taking the size that
they need, but if I decrease the horizontal space
as footer content moves onto the next line, it is going
to be taking space up within that layout.
So with 'grid-template-rows: auto, 1fr, auto' you can
create the pancake stack. You could even have an
application toolbar down there.
Again, this is one that we see really commonly and
grid-template-rows is a great one to know.
Another very common layout is the Holy Grail layout.
Does this look familiar?
I think we've all seen a website or two that looks exactly
like this at some point on our web journey.
We've got your header, your footer, your
left sidebar over here, your main content and a right
sidebar. And we can write all of this
in one line of code using grid-template.
So grid-template allows us to write the
grid-template-rows and grid-template-columns
at the same time.
So that's pretty neat. It's also super responsive.
Again, you see this auto content taking up
what we are specifying here internally and then
this main content taking up the 1fr.
And so what we are specifying here is grid-template
with auto, 1fr for this middle space,
and then auto for the footer.
And then we've got our columns of auto, 1fr, and auto.
So you get the whole Holy Grail layout with
'grid-template: auto 1fr auto / auto 1fr auto'.
This slash is what denotes our rows versus
columns when we are writing the grid templates.
So I think that this one is great to know.
Grid-template is something that I use all the time.
This is not exactly one line.
I mean, all of these, you know, you have a little bit more
to add. But with this, when you are ready in grid-template,
you can then specify grid-columns
and grid-rows for each of these
elements. So here I am specifying what grid-column I am
placing the header in.
I'm going all the way across all three.
So 1 / 4 to get those grid tracks from
the first track to the last track.
And then the left side, we have it going inside the first,
so from 1 to 2.
This main section going from 2 to 3.
So that's gonna be taking up the middle section and then
the right side is from 3 to 4, so that's going all the way
to the end of this grid that we've created.
And then for that footer, it's going all the way across
just like the header. So you do specify where
items are placed when it is a little more of a complex
UI. And in here, if we look at the HTML, I have
this parent, then I have header, then I have left-sidebar,
then I have the main section, right section
and then the footer.
So you can write all of your layouts in one line
using grid-template property.
Next we have another classic the 12-by or 12-span
grid. You can quickly write grids in CSS using
the repeat() grid function.
And here we're setting a repeat of 12 columns.
So that looks like this grid-template-columns, repeat
- the number that you want to repeat - and then 1fr.
So this would be the same as writing
'grid-template-columns: 1fr 1fr 1fr'
twelve times, but because I don't want to do that, I'm just
going to write repeat, 12, and then 1fr and then
we have a 12-by grid.
So now we can place our items within this grid
however we want. If we want it to span all the way across
the 12 columns, we would use this span 12
element. I just gave it a span12 class and have it going
from 1 all the way to 13, so taking up the full space
of the 12 columns ending at the grid track of 13,
which would be the end of that 12th column line.
For the span6, this is going from one to seven.
For span4 this is going from 4 to 8.
It can go anywhere. I could start this at the first line
and make it go all the way to 9.
I could have this go to 5 and have it still span 4.
But the cool thing is you can just place this wherever you
want inside of your UI.
So if I want to have this start from 6 and go to 10,
I could do that. And then we have this span2, and this
is just going from 3 to 5. Again, that could be placed
anywhere. And then a peep at the HTML, we just have
this parent element, and then the inside of
here, we're just giving classes based on those span
elements that we were just adjusting within that grid
template. So the repeat function is very,
very useful when you don't want to keep typing out
1fr auto multiple times.
It just lets you quickly write information.
We're going to expand on the repeat function for number
7. And this technique is super cool, super
useful. If you take away anything from this video, I think
this would be a great one to keep in your repertoire.
I like to call this the RAM technique, which stands for
repeat, auto, and minmax, and the line of code
here, it looks like this. You have the
grid-template-columns, repeat, auto-fit, or
autofill, minmax, the base value, and then
1fr for a fractional unit.
And here we have that base value as 150px.
I'll show you exactly what's going on.
So as we increase the size here, these
elements are going to fit to take up the space, these
four boxes. As I decrease it, they're going to hit
this 150px base value and then
they're going to wrap onto the next line.
But here we have them auto-fitting, so
they're going to be spanning the take up as much space
as they can. There's some really cool algorithms at
play here. Now, if we change this to
auto-fill, this will look a little bit different.
So let me just update that to auto-fill. Here, now,
as I increase the size, it's not going to
be spanning and stretching to take up the remainder
of the space, it's actually going to be using that 150
pixels as a baseline and stay within that.
At smaller sizes, there's no difference here.
But you really see the difference at larger sizes as
you have additional space.
And I use this technique on the page that you're looking
at here itself, this auto-fill, so
that these two segments would stretch and
shrink, but not exceed a specific
space that I wanted them to.
And then I have them centered, so you can center this
within the parent as it spreads to a larger size.
That's always an option and a really great technique to
know. Remember R-A-M,
repeat, auto, fill or fit, and then minmax,
and you can get these responsive boxes.
You can use these for images, you can use them for a lot of
things. It's something that we see all the time for cards.
And this is a great use of all of these fancy new
grid capabilities in CSS.
For our next layout, we're heading back
to flexbox land.
I want to include this one because I just find it so useful
and I use this all the time.
I call it the Line Up. Why?
I don't know. I'm tired.
If you have a better name, please let me know.
Leave a comment. But the main thing that I wanted to
demonstrate here is justify-content
for placement of items. And here specifically, I wanted to
highlight 'justify-content: space-between' to place
items at their edges.
And so in this example, we have these three cards
and you can see that as I'm stretching or shrinking
the size of this viewport element, they
are maintaining the same height as each other.
And in fact, we are having them
fit to the top and bottom and this interior
content - so this description like, I can keep
typing here - this is then going to be centered
within the remaining space.
And so the reason this is happening is because
for these cards, we're giving them this flex-direction
of 'column'. This display-flex, the flexbox mode,
and then we're justifying content space-between.
So because this is a column for the flex-direction,
the space-between is going to be right here in between
these three elements; this little box here, the
description, and the title.
And so here, as I'm having additional space
added or removed vertically, they are centering themselves.
And this just makes for a much neater layout.
I've used this a lot here, without that justification, it
looks a lot more messy.
But because of the stretching here, because of the flexbox,
because of this 'justify-content: space between', I use
this all the time and I think it's really important to know
that with flexbox you can change the direction
and you can justify your content in unique ways.
It doesn't have to be just centered.
You can also do center, you can do a space-around
as well or space-evenly.
But in this case, I think that the best way to justify is
space-between. Because this way we are ensuring
that the first and last element here
in our layout, which is going to be this H3 and this whole
visual box, remain flush
to the top and bottom of our cards.
Here's where we get into some techniques with a little less
current browser support.
I like to call this one Clamping My Syle and it's a really
neat trick. Remember at the beginning of this video,
we talked about min, max and clamp?
Well, here's where it can come into play for layout and
element style. Here I'm specifying the width
using this clamp function and I'm setting clamp to 23ch,
50%, and 46ch. What
does this do? Let me show you exactly what's going on here.
As I increase the size of this element, the
parent container here, it is going to increase
the size of this card.
And as I decrease it, it decreases it.
But what we are setting here is a minimum and maximum size
for it to clamp to as it reaches that
50% size.
This card wants to be at 50% width, but
if that 50% means that it's bigger than 46ch -
which stands for 46 characters - then
it's going to stop getting bigger.
The same thing happens with the smaller viewport size.
It's going to stop decreasing in size when 50%
of its parent size means that it is smaller than 23ch
- which is 23 characters.
And these specific character units can be used to make
legibility a little bit easier.
So in this case, I don't want this card to get any smaller
than that because then the paragraph gets harder to read.
And same thing with getting bigger than 46 characters, then
it gets too long and hard to read.
So you can use width, clamp, minimum size,
the actual size, and the max size to create
some really cool responsiveness within this element itself.
And you can also use clamp() for font size.
That's a really great use case, too.
You can have this responsive, flexible typography.
You could have like clamp, 1.5rem,
and then like say,
10vw for the viewport width, and then 3rem
as the biggest size.
And that way, as you resize your window, you're
going to be having a minimum value of
1.5rem, maximum value of 3rem, and then
you're gonna have that grow and shrink into that remaining
space. So it's pretty cool to see this
actually working in a browser.
Again, this doesn't have a full browser support,
but it is a really great technique.
So if you're using this, make sure the fallbacks and do
your browser testing.
And finally, we are at the end and this is the last
layout tool. And this layout tool is the most experimental
of the bunch. This is recently introduced to Chrome Canary
and Chrome 84+.
And there is an active effort from Firefox in getting this
implemented in browser, but it is currently not in any
stable browsers - at the time of this recording.
I do want to mention it though, because it is such a
frequently met problem and it's just simply maintaining
the aspect ratio of an image or a video or
of an iframe.
And so what this is, is respecting
the aspect, Respect for Aspect.
That's name I gave it. And it is the aspect-ratio
property. Oh, my gosh, I'm going to be so excited when this
is implemented in all browsers.
What this is doing is, as I am resizing this
parent element, the image here
- so this is just like I gave it a class of visual for this
box here. That is right here.
- this is getting an aspect ratio of 16 to 9.
And no matter how I increase it or decrease it, it is going
to keep that aspect ratio.
This is something that is so needed for when you
are pulling in content from a CMS or otherwise,
and you have a specific dimension that you have that
media at.
And this, for example, in the previous example, if I
scroll up as I resize here, since I'm only
setting a height and it's just getting the 100%
width of whatever remaining space that I'm providing here,
it's actually changing the aspect ratio of the sole visual
box. And that's not what we want.
That is going to make you force a decision on
if you want to either fit the content inside of there so
it's smaller and fits within the space, or if
you stretch it out and you have it fill the content
and then you're only seeing a piece of that media and not
the full image - and that's also going to cause all sorts
of problems. So having this aspect ratio is
very exciting.
You can also set this to a square if you do 1 over 1.
You could have this be 1 over 2, where you have this
actually longer than it is wide within this parent
here. So that's going to be maintaining that aspect ratio.
And it's just exciting, so I wanted to mention it and let
you know that it's coming down the pipeline.
And those are the 10 really powerful lines of CSS that
I wanted to talk about in this 1 line layout video.
I hope that you all learned something new.
And if you're looking for these demos, check out
1linelayouts.glitch.me. Thank you all for watching.
If you want more CSS content and to dive deeper into layout
techniques, including all the bells and whistles of CSS
grid and flexbox, check out the CSS podcast
that I do with my co-host, Adam Argyle.
It is at pod.link/thecsspodcast.