[Music]
[Applause]
welcome back to web dev live as a Brit
and tickled to be kicking off day 2 from
an Amir friendly time zone yesterday we
spoke about government's doing great
work getting the word out on the web and
one of the most inspirational digital
services is from the UK where I saw a
government convened online for the first
time now we've all been learning how
best to work and learn from home and at
Google we're trying to get a deeper
understanding of the needs of web
developers partnering with the community
as one of our close partners I wanted to
invite our friends at Mozilla to chat
more about that work and also get
information on what's new in their world
welcome khadiyah and Victoria hi Deon
great to be here hey
so kadia web developers know mdn really
well and many may have participated in
the last DNA report but can you get us
up to speed a little bit and tell us
about its history and what we're trying
to do yeah of course so this really
started in late 2017
shortly after CSS great was shipped CSS
great was a massive success but was also
years in the making and layout had been
an issue for web developers at least
since the 90s when we abused tables
implement our UI designs so we asked
ourselves how can we have more of these
wins and we talked to people who worked
at the web platform at Mozilla about how
they prioritize things and one thing
really stood out because almost everyone
said the same thing they said we need to
hear more from developers and it makes
so much sense
because none of us can be successful
without that part it's hard to
prioritize the right thing without
knowing about developer pain points and
it's hard to find the right solution
especially if it and it's hard to get
people to use something if it's not
solving that problem or not solving it
in the right way so for all of those
reasons we proposed developer needs
assessment and the DNA in short is meant
to be a single and simple tool for harsh
characterization representing very
diverse populations and a huge future
space and it's publisher I'm Deanna
that's important because it's not owned
by a single browser vendor when you know
she initially proposed this under the
umbrella of the MDM product Advisory
Board where we have representation from
browser vendors like Google and
Microsoft and Samsung but also the w3c
and industry stakeholders and as a
community we need to have at least a
common understanding of the facts when
it comes to needs even if we draw
different conclusions from them and for
this situation in 2019 more than 20,000
developers and designers took the 20
minutes necessary to fully complete the
survey and that's from 173 countries
total and that's about ten thousand
hours of time contributed by developers
and designers to help us understand what
their pain points and needs are and we
believe that makes the amnion web DNA
the biggest web developer a design and
focus survey ever conducted so far yeah
well when you put it that way
just really want to say thank you to to
the community and anyone that took the
time to go through those you know 20
minutes and getting us the feedback it's
it's incredibly useful to us but but
thank you so much so when you were going
through the results
Kadir the 2019 report what kind of
really kind of stood out to you you know
one thing really
and that's web compatibility and
interoperability the four of the top
five issues were focused on exactly that
topic and one of the biggest strengths
of the web is that there is no single
entity controlling the platform but that
doesn't come for free web developers and
designers are frustrated by not being
able to use features by having to find
workarounds fiddling with browser
differences and also by the difficulty
to verify that something that works in
one browser will not break in another
browser and related to that it was a bit
of a surprise that the top five issues
were extremely stable between very
different markets so whether it's China
in the Japan the US or France the top
issues for web developers revolve around
web compatibility and interoperability
got it so when you take this feedback in
how does it actually kind of change the
roadmap at Mozilla like what are you now
looking to focus on based on this
feedback yeah so web config web
compatibility was already a focus at
Mozilla even before this but we now have
doubled down on it so recently we made
browser compatibility data machine
readable on MDM and that's now starting
to pay off so if you use yes code very
popular code editor the tooltips have
compact data information when you write
CSS and we also recently started a
collaboration with can I use comm to
share the data that we have so we are
all looking at the same browser company
information and I'm sure Victoria can
say more about it in a moment but the
Firefox dev tool say now come with
combat data information built-in got it
yeah this the feedback has been really
helpful for us and the web platform team
is really you know working even deeper
on stability compared issues that you
talked about helping with testing layout
really kind of understanding what what
the development needs are and kind of
bringing it into our prioritization too
so it's actually almost time for the
next version of the DNA report so what
do we have in store for developers this
time around yeah so one thing we are
super excited about this year is to see
how things have changed year-over-year
so we want to see that developer
satisfaction go up or down and however
the top pain points changed so this is
really the first opportunity to see
those trends well I can't wait to get
that out to developers and I hope that
everyone's watching would do us a favor
and take some time to to get that
feedback in so we can like really know
what we can prioritize in the future for
our roadmaps now Victoria I actually
used to work on there on developer tools
at Mozilla and not only was it the birth
of a you know great tooling in the
browser back from Joe Hewitt's you know
Firebug on words but it really continued
to push the bar so I'd love for you to
be able to kind of catch us up on what's
the latest what's new in in Firefox dev
tools hi Dan as Kadir explained we know
that differing browser support for CSS
features is a top issue for web devs so
our team built a compatibility panel to
make it easier to stay on top of this it
lists all CSS on your website that's
unsupported in certain browsers as well
as deprecated Styles you try it now in
Firefox dev edition I really love the
the UX touches there especially the
turtle and the like that's that's great
and in general you know a lot of great
features Lydia that I landed there and
I'm curious if there's anything on the
upcoming roadmap that you're excited
about sharing we've also been working on
the Firefox profiler it's our
performance tool which features
shareable links for collaboration we've
been integrating the recorded UI into
Firefox so it's easy to get started this
tool is also currently in dev edition as
far as our debugger I want to highlight
two unique features in 77 we added a
type of break point that's new to
browser tools the watch point it let's
see pause when an object property is
accessed or changed also we made source
mapped variables work when you pause in
an original file we now reverse engineer
the scope chain so that variables look
correct in the scopes pane and work in
the console oh this was six months of
incredibly challenging work done by our
teammate Logan who had deep knowledge
for being tech lead on Babel the year
before we dropped that he's the only
person in the world who could have
written this so recently I really
embraced the open design process for a
network panel redesign we set and we
sent out a survey and posted early
mock-ups to Twitter and got amazing
input I originally used bold to indicate
large files and someone suggested it be
more clear to have Mouse and elephant
icons for small and big that's how we
ended up with the turtle for slow
responses people also told us that when
it comes to the domain column they
mainly want to know if it's third-party
or not so in this condensed view with a
sidebar we hid the domain column and add
an icon that indicates third-party
requests originally I made these
brightly-colored file type icons and
some people love them and others said it
was too much label like candy so i ated
tone down
colors and got to the result you see
here most of this has landed in the
latest nightly we hope everyone will try
it out and give us more feedback awesome
great so Victoria
Kadir thank you so much for taking the
time to join us today we really
appreciate the great work the Mozilla
continues to do for the web now you
spend a lot of time both in your
developer tools and also on the core
task of building your app UI
so to chat more about modern web UI
let's welcome you now idea hi Yuna now
we were just talking about the develop
and need survey with Mozilla and there
was plenty of feedback from developers
on layout so I was just curious you know
there any recent additions to the
platform that you think target these
needs oh yes you've definitely been
listening and CSS has been evolving so
rapidly in the past few years and really
months so tomorrow I'll be going over a
ton of cool aspects of modern layout
with CSS grid and flexbox
including how to harness the power of
CSS functions like clamp fractional
units Auto placement the min max
function justification place items the
VP function and a lot more to create
robust layouts breaking down how
powerful a single line of CSS can be
there are also some CSS properties
coming down the pipeline that will help
with a lot of user needs that haven't
yet been met an aspect ratio is one of
them this just landed in Chrome Canary
and it enables users set to find width
to height ratios for media items like
images and video previously the way to
do this was a hack using padding and
calculating a percentage but now you can
set your ratios in a much more readable
way I'm looking forward to the planning
and browsers and making a lot of
developers lives easier because I know
this is something that I run into a lot
we're also getting the gap property in
Flex box this one is exciting because of
how many times we've just been styling a
series of items and wanting there to be
space between those items but not around
those items gap enables the parent
element to control spacing not the
children making it easier to style these
items uniformly within that parent
currently you can use gap to create
tracks with CSS grid but you'll be able
to use with a flexbox layout too meaning
you can leverage all the benefits of gap
with the greater
choice and layout mechanism the web
animations API is also getting a lot
more robust in chromium 84 now we have
promises replaceable animations
composite modes partial keyframes and a
way to access animations from CSS and
JavaScript check out the blog post on
web app dev for more information about
these updates and try them out in Chrome
Canary yourself the act property rule is
also available behind a flag and canary
and something that I am particularly
excited about because this allows for
semantic variables in CSS with a
property you can declare a CSS custom
properties that have semantics typed
values and fallbacks this is the part of
the CSS Houdini effort specifically the
properties and values API and previously
was possible in JavaScript with CSS to
register property as a part of Houdini
but the app property declaration brings
us into our CSS files meaning a nice
collocation of super-powered styles with
the rest of your CSS the other Houdini
API is to keep an eye out for our the
type object model the paint worklets
animation workbook and the layout work
with great so javascript seems to kind
of have its time with the addition of
async away yes modules and the like it
was great to see that evolution it's
really feeling like this is a big time
for for CSS I love being able to get
features that like gap that you made
though you mentioned and the like to
just make things a lot easier for us and
super excited at how deep you can get
into on the Houdini side too but if I
use these and I'm building these super
rich designs and the like with this
great power comes great responsibility
so how do you think about the role of
accessibility here I love that you bring
up accessibility because accessibility
should always come first I think you're
absolutely right that that needs to be
top of mind your users need to be able
to access your content and navigate your
product it is not an enhancement I think
of accessibility as a core feature and
from 83 actually just launched with some
new accessibility testing features which
are pretty neat because they allow for
visual accessibility testing so now
their dev tools you can examine if your
UI works for users with the various
vision deficiency is like blurred vision
and for different types of
colorblindness yeah it's great we're
actually gonna have pool Luis come on
then kind of
through that a little bit and so thanks
so much I also have really been enjoying
your new CSS podcast with Adam Argyle
not only are you both kind of like
really fun to listen to him the like
it's actually been really interesting to
what you kind of go through step by step
and kind of teach us the fundamentals
there was a lot that I didn't really
know about yeah honestly we're learning
so much as we are going through the
fundamentals and we're having a lot of
fun making these episodes so if you
haven't seen it yet check out the CSS
podcast absolutely so thanks so much for
joining us Yuna and we'll see you later
on the stream bye now there are a few
more dev tools features I'm really keen
to show you and no one's better to show
off a bit all-in than the ever
supercharged Paul Lewis
hey how you doing not too bad how you
doing mate yep pretty good thanks
alright so one of the things that we've
noticed is that dev tools puts out these
console warnings as you can see on
screen and if you're anything like me
after a while you start to ignore them
and the reason is that that just could
be quite a lot of them so we've been
thinking about that and what we decided
to do is to bring in the issues tab now
if we detect issues on your page you'll
see this bar across the top with a
button in the top right hand corner
there that says go to issues if you
click on that it'll take you through to
the issues tab now you might offer you
the opportunity to reload the page to
get more information if you click on one
of these items it'll expand and you can
see more information there as well as
potentially some links to content for
you to read up on what you could do to
fix the issue so that's the issues tab
the other thing we've been looking at is
Web vitals so if you go to web dev slash
metrics you'll see a whole list of
metrics here that affect the UX and
things that we would like to optimize as
web developers and we've been looking at
ways of exposing this information to you
inside of the dev tools UI so things
like first content full paint or largest
content for paint for example so if you
go to the performance tab in dev tools
and you take a recording in the
performance tab you'll see something
that looks like this now there is a
timings tab there what time use row
sorry I should say across which you'll
see these blocks and these relate to
some of those metrics so you can see
P&L CP first contact 4p largest contact
for patrons so on so you can start to
get information there on some of your
metrics the other thing we started doing
is to add candy striping to your
long-running tasks and you can see that
here I have one task on my main thread
that is 17 milliseconds long and what
we're looking for is we're looking for
tasks to remain under 50 milliseconds
this means that the main thread stays
responsive and hopefully we can respond
to user interactions quickly so as you
look around your performance recording
if you see this can't distracting effect
and the red triangle in the corner you
know that you've got a task that's
running longer than 50 milliseconds what
we've also added as well is we've added
a tons of blocking time footer at the
bottom what this tells you is if you
like the amount of candy striping that
you would see across the whole recording
so as you're looking around if you see
that that numbers going up you might
want to take a look and see if you have
a lot of long running tasks on your main
thread bringing that down should
hopefully help your user experience
another thing that we've added is this
experience track and what's contained
within this is layout shift information
so for example when you've got buttons
and so on on your page and they're
perhaps moving around this can cause you
X discomfort so what we want to do is we
want to minimize the amount of moving
elements on the page and so the layout
shift here is going to tell you what
elements are moving on the page and
where and so on and the size that they
were when they did it so if I look at
this I have a warning here which tells
me that qtip layouts can result in poor
user experiences and that's a link to
more information as well as information
on where is moved from and - and if I
roll over that I get an overlay on my
screen which shows me exactly where on
my page the shift took place you can
also get live information about layout
shifts by going to the rendering tab and
choosing layout shift regions here in
the options now I should say that for
people prone to photosensitive epilepsy
this might be a less suitable option
because it can cause flushing or
overlays on the screen but it is there
as an option if it's suitable for you
the next thing I want to talk about is
web assembly debugging and it's an
experiment so if you go into your dev
tool settings go to these parents tab
and click on web assembly debugging you
can switch it on there well this allows
you to
is allows you to do things like setting
breakpoints in your web assembly code so
here I've compiled a C program it's just
a hello world program but what I've done
is I've added a breakpoint on the line
that says hello world so when this code
executes and it hits that line inside of
the web assembly it pauses execution
just like it would inside the JavaScript
and you can see here in the call stack
that I can actually take a look at
what's going on in that particular frame
and I can go between my JavaScript and
the C and so on and so forth so that's
something that's coming down and it's
currently in canary so take a look at
that now the last thing I want to show
you is color vision deficiency emulation
inside of dev tools and there's no
better way to do that than to actually
give you a demo ok so here I am in
Chrome Canary and I have a video here
running of me and server doing
supercharged yesteryear but you see I
have the rendering tab open in dev tools
and I can emulate various vision
deficiencies such as blurred vision or I
can do protanopia I can do deuteron Opia
protanopia I will straight right in Opa
a chroma top to you as well so you can
see the live effect that it has on the
page so these are physiologically
accurate emulations of various vision
deficiencies now a vision deficiency
isn't an on/off thing let me see here
but rather it's a spectrum so a person
could have a milder form of a vision
deficiency or a more acute form what
we've chosen to implement inside of the
dev tools UI is the most acute form the
theory being that as you're optimizing
your app for accessibility in terms of
color and contrast if you make it work
for the most acute form then you'll
include everything up to and including
that as well
so that's color vision deficiency
emulation inside of dev tools thanks
Paul I'm really looking forward to
seeing more later today
now one thing I've noticed as we work
from home is how seriously people are
taking their home setups whether it be
playing with mics and cameras or virtual
backgrounds and recently I saw a demo
that would make you invisible on your
video feed using tensorflow j/s so I've
really wanted to learn more
so please welcome Jason maze from the
tensorflow Jas team
hi there I'm Jason and thank you for the
introduction there it's pleasure to be
invited to the show and yes I have
created an invisibility cloak
so maybe you would learn more about that
yeah Jason invisibility cloaks are
pretty cool and so maybe you can show us
how web developers can create
superpowers like that with tensive law
sure definitely
so if I switch to my slides for just a
second you can see what the invisibility
cloak was that Zeon was referring to you
and in this demonstration on the right
hand side you can see as I get on the
bed the bed is deforming in real time
and I'm being removed from the bottom
frame at the same time and this is
running all in the web browser now this
is pretty cool because privacy is
preserved as none of these images are
being sent to the server site and that's
super powerful especially in today's
climate where privacy is top of mind now
this was created in just under a day in
fact so it's quite easy to get started
with machine learning in the web browser
and we'll see some more demos in just a
second so on that note I also created a
Chrome extension that allows me to use
the same stuff we saw before as I using
body pics to create that which gives me
this image segmentation of my body in
real time and I can now join a Google
meet meeting as you can see shown on the
side right now and this can be combined
with my previous demo so I can remove
that second person who comes into frame
halfway through the gif and then it
would appear as if it never actually
happened cool so can you give us a few
more details on how this all works so
essentially all this is using body
segmentation and this is running
intensive projects in the web browser
and this can distinguish 24 unique body
areas across multiple bodies in real
time you can see
on the right-hand side that this works
pretty well when it all those settings
are bumped up too high and you can even
get the pose estimation showing on the
bodies to which estimated where the
skeleton is these can be used in
delightful ways juts as clothing size
estimation which you can see here this
is not a prototype I created and I don't
know about you Theon but I am terrible
at knowing what size clothing to buy I
mean by once a year clothing purchase so
absolutely yeah totally and here you can
see I just enter my height and in less
than 15 seconds I think an estimate of
my inner leg my chest and waist
measurements which for clothing sight
can then use to estimate what size I am
a small medium or large
now this can even give you superpowers
ACC on this next slide and what about
community members from the USA has
combined this with WebGL shaders to turn
himself into Iron Man of sorts that he
can shoot lasers from its eyes and mouth
using our face mesh model so this is
pretty cool and it runs buttery smooth
at 60 frames per second in the web
browser and you can even go further of
course there's many web technologies out
there but you might want to combine with
machine learning such as web X our WebGL
and use very intensive OGS and if you do
that you can get an example like this
from another one of our community
members in Paris France who can
essentially scan a magazine and if
there's a person in it they can bring
that person into the living room full
size you can walk up to them and inspect
them in more detail pretty cool
technology but of course after seeing
this I thought to go one step further
and if I add web RTC I can bend teleport
myself anywhere in the world in real
time and this is using complete rewrite
using WebRTC a frame 3GS and 10 suppose
yes together to create this demo and it
really does make a big difference when
I'm seeing someone in my room which I
can walk up to and move around
it's a massive difference compared to a
rectangle that's solid on the screen so
this could be the future of video
conferencing who knows but it's great to
play these technologies have pushed the
boundaries of the web that's really cool
from invisibility cloaks to
teleportation that's that's pretty cool
stuff yeah exactly
this changes everything is anything so
how should web developers if we kind of
zoom out a second
how do web developers kind of
generically think about the role of ml
in tensorflow j/s and how it could fit
into their web applications yeah that's
a great question and obviously right now
in fact machine learning in JavaScript
is still a pretty new thing right the
very early stages but that's super
exciting too because there's so much
potential to be unraveled at this time
as well so on that note I had asked web
developers to consider how a machine
learning might fit into their existing
pipelines maybe you're developing a
content management system in that case
you could potentially use something like
automatic image cropping to detect where
a human faces in the image so then you
can make sure that it's cropped nicely
when you're resizing with your CSS or
maybe you want to summarize a blog post
article so you have one paragraph of
text that shows MD search results that's
now possible of machine learning - and
that can be done automatically so I
think only coach people to experiment
and and go outside of the regular box or
thinking and of course on that note on
this side you can see all the different
areas JavaScript can run on the browser
server-side mobile native desktop native
and even Internet of Things and tensor
phones jes supports all of these
environments too so maybe you want to
combine it with hardware if you can
recognize an object maybe you can
trigger something to happen in the
physical world or something on the
surface I if I talk to a third-party
service and on that note tensorflow Jess
can essentially run retrain by transfer
learning or even write allow you to
write your own models from scratch if
you so desire now on that note we have a
ton of pre frame models you can use to
get started such as the body
segmentation you saw just a little bit
ago but also things that pose estimation
speech commands base mesh hand pose and
some cool natural language processing
and just to dive into that a little bit
more you can see how these models work
here so here's the object recognition in
action this class allows you to
recognize 90 pre-trained objects that
cookies dock you can see here and you
get the bounding boxes that come back at
the same time which is pretty neat or
what about this face mesh just three
megabytes in size and you can understand
468 unique landmarks on her face
and this could be cool for making face
masks or some kind of AR experience such
as the one you see on the right Madhi
face which is part of a loyal group has
actually uses for AR makeup try on and
this lady on the right hand side is not
actually wearing any makeup at all in
fact she's selecting the color of makeup
she wants to try on and she can do that
all in real time in the web browser in a
much more hygienic way which is pretty
cool and then finally I just want to
talk about some of the client-side
superpowers you get if we think about
running machine running in the web
browser
the first one is privacy as we hinted at
before essentially because we're running
in the web browser
none of that data is ever being sent to
a server for classification so that
allows you to access for sensor data in
a way that is great for privacy linked
to that of course is lower latency as
there's no server involved that means
there's no hundred milliseconds or so
round-trip time from the mobile device
to the server you cut out completely by
running on the edge and of course lower
costs you might spend tens of thousands
of dollars
hiring beefy GPUs and CPUs to run the
machines any models on your server-side
environments by running on the client
side all of that goes away because
you're using the hardware of the client
to run instead got it so how can people
get started you've definitely piqued my
interest now I want to know when I start
playing ok sounds good so if there's one
slide you want to kind of screenshot
from today's talk it would be this one
here on this site you can find out our
websites our models github code we are
open source or feel free to contribute
there's a Google group for asking more
technical questions and of course some
great boilerplates to get started on
code pen and Glitch and for those of you
want to go really deep we recommend for
deep learning with JavaScript book
that's very comprehensive and even if
you have no background in machine
learning as long as you know some
JavaScript it will walk you through
everything step-by-step so I highly
recommend checking that out and on that
note I would also suggest checking out
teach or machine right after this show
maybe in just two minutes you can use
this website to learn to recognize any
object in your room in just thirty
seconds you just take a few images of
that thing hit train and you'll get a
classifier that can then classify that
object if you like it you can export
this model to a JSON format and then use
it on any website you like to be more
creative and
makes your own creations using that and
then finally I'd ask you to come join
the community we've got this made with
TFG a hashtag that you can use that
allows you to share what you've made so
we can find it and we can invite you to
our future showing tells and of course
that others to get inspired by your
great work too so finally I just want to
leave you with one more inspirational
example this guy from Tokyo in Japan is
actually a dancer
but he's used temps of hojae s to make
this cool hip-hop video so machine
learning really is now for everyone and
I'm super excited to see how creatives
will start using this and not just
academics musicians artists and much
much more so if you do make something do
use a major of TF J's hashtag so we can
find it and share it for you and I look
forward to seeing what you make and with
that feel free to stay in touch using
the following links if you say desire on
Twitter and LinkedIn great thanks so
much for joining us Jason yeah and
thanks to everyone who joined me on the
day to kick off so now let's get to
today's sessions where we focus on
updates across our tools and the web
platform to make developers more
productive as well as the latest in the
world of PW A's
please enjoy the show and remember the
team is here to chat with you on web dev
slash live and via YouTube I'll see you
there today or will be back tomorrow
morning for the day three kickoff
[Music]