[Music]
[Applause]
hello
my name is shu and i work on the
javascript specification as well as the
v8 project
my name is lescheck and i work as a
performance engineer on the v8 vm
so she what's new in javascript these
days
yeah a whole bunch of stuff has happened
since last year and you might recognize
some of the features we're going to talk
about today from some of our colleagues
2019 google i o talk because language
features take a while to be standardized
and to be shipped into browsers the ones
we're going to be talking about today
have shipped
so let's start with the fun stuff like i
said we're about to
we're either shipped or about to ship
quite a few syntax features that should
make web devs lives easier
for this talk we'll be focusing on two
features that'll make dealing with
optional
values easier so leshik have you ever
written code that dealt with
configuration
oh yeah definitely like always using a
hash map for those things
yeah so i'm keeping i'm writing this new
chat app right something of a strength
for google engineers
i made some network parameters
configurable which i keep in this map of
configurations called
config that you see on the screen but
the network configuration
is optional because it isn't always set
by the user and it has
sub configurations like the server and
the port and maybe those aren't set by
the user either handling that kind of
optionality is kind of a pain
currently folks do this with logical and
like you see on the screen
oh that's pretty good place yeah and for
those chains of property accesses
were at any point some property in the
middle could turn out to be
undefined we added this feature called
optional chaining
easier to show you on the screen than to
talk you through it so
the optional chaining feature is the
question mark and the dot
instead of a plain dot oh i see so if
net config is undefined
then netconfig.server is undefined until
address isn't defined and so forth
yeah almost it's a little bit more
relaxed than that it's if it's undefined
or null
and specifically we call the set of
things that are undefined or not
knowledge
so in the in this case if net config is
knowledge the whole optional chain is
undefined
if net config isn't knowledge but net
config.server is knowledge
then again the whole thing is undefined
you get the idea if nothing
is knowledge then eventually you get the
the
whole property the most nested property
access
yeah cool that's a lot easier to read
yeah i think so too
now another common feature while dealing
with configurations
is default values and sometimes folks
use logical or for this like you see on
the screen
oh yeah i've definitely written that
before yeah and it usually works fine
but sometimes it doesn't and is is
really surprising when it doesn't
suppose i add a configuration for
enabling compression
to the to the server do you spot the bug
oh yeah right how would you actually
explicitly disable compression right
if it's false then false or true it's
all going to be true
yeah exactly if enable compression is
false
false or true like you said is true so
what we really want to test here
is not something is truthy which is what
logical or
tests for but actually if something is
absent or present
and we already are familiar with that
concept that's knowledge
so we introduced this new syntax feature
called knowledge coalescing which is the
two question marks
and that does exactly what you want here
for default values it tests for
knowledgeness on the left-hand side
if the left-hand side is knowledge then
it evaluates to the right-hand side
if the hand side is not knowledge then
the whole thing is
undefined so in this case enable
compression is false question mark
question mark true
will still get you false because false
is not null or undefined
but if enable compression wasn't present
if it's undefined
then you get the default value of true
that's pretty cool where can i use it
so you can use both optional chaining
and knowledge coalescing
in chrome stable today now enough
talking for me
this that was just a taste of the new
features you can find more on our
website later we'll show you the link
but you know we add all these new syntax
features and i'm worried that supporting
them all will slow down the parser
v8 is known to be fast and i don't want
to
do anything to make it slower you know
what that's a fair concern to have
uh when we shipped es6 back in 2015
we actually saw a big parsing
performance drop like this is measured
on octane on the code load benchmark
and we had this big drop during this
implementation phase
but actually nowadays parsing speed
doesn't matter as much as you might
think oh really not anymore i thought
parsing was pretty expensive but it's
still not cheap
but in the past year we've worked a lot
to move a lot of parsing off of the main
thread
and be able to pass scripts while
they're still loading so imagine that
chrome sees a script like this
the html parser gets up to it it sees
the script
and then has to pause the html parsing
has to download to the script
pause it execute it and only then can it
continue pausing the html
i know is strictly true because of
optimizations like preloading
no you're absolutely right uh this isn't
actually the whole truth and
the download of the script happens a lot
earlier if there's a link preload or if
the preposit finds the script earlier
and if the download moves off of the
main thread and earlier
in time then pause and execute can move
earlier too but the thing is the parsing
itself
can happen on a separate thread as well
it's only really the execute that has
happened on the main thread
in particular if a script is marked as
async you can keep processing the html
up until uh the parsing of the async
script is actually finished and
it needs to execute and we've had
support for this basically forever but
it's been very limited
we've only been able to concurrently
pass one
script at a time and we've only been
able to do this very soon scripts
yeah how come it's been so limited
honestly just historical technical
reasons which don't really hold anymore
so one of the first things that we did
was move everything from this dedicated
thread
into our global threat pool which meant
that they could happen
at the same time in parallel another
thing that we changed was
to have synchronous script also use this
off-thread pausing functionality
i'm kind of confused you said
synchronous scripts but what's the point
of parsing
synchronous scripts in another thread
isn't the whole point for non-async
scripts that they block the main thread
well that is the point for the execute
but for the parsing
even though we're pausing on a different
thread if the main thread is free that
means it can do other things
it means that the user can scroll it
means that the user can type it means
that we can execute other javascript
like
on click handlers so it's actually very
useful to be
to have this empty space here on the
main thread ah okay i see
this is the difference between improving
interactivity versus just improving the
loading time
right but we can improve loading as well
uh because the parsing is happening on a
separate thread uh we can actually move
it earlier we can start pausing when the
download starts
and then as data comes in from the
network we can feed it into the parser
and then the actual pass time doesn't
matter as much as you might think
all that we need is for the parser to be
faster than the network
really the networks are already pretty
fast not always but usually they are
fair enough and you know caches are even
faster so
we can't completely ignore parser
performance so we have invested a lot
into improving the positive performance
as well single threaded puzzle
performance
starting 2018 we put this big effort in
put some of our best engineers on it
and we've had actually very good results
in improving past performance just
through
programming optimization yeah up and to
the right that's the kind of graph i
like to see
really fascinating stuff the thing i
learned quite a bit in just the past
five minutes about making parsing
compiling faster
and web app performance in general and
you got me thinking about this other big
chunk
of web app performance which is memory i
was doing this thing the other day with
with my chat app
and you know i got it basically working
and i was trying to measure
the performance of the packets that i
was getting from the server i wrote this
little moving average class to compute
the latency moving average
of uh of the packets that i was getting
from the websocket
you see there that i add a message
listener that basically all it does is
it accumulates events into the event
array
and i use that later in this compute
function which i don't show to actually
compute the moving average
and the way i use that is i have this
component that
when i start measuring and i want to see
the live statistics of the
moving average of the latency that i
make a new instance of it
and then when i stop i null it out
because i don't want to keep all the
events i accumulated in memory i know
that
v8 garbage collects memory that can no
longer be reachable
and as long as the moving average is
reachable through the
this.moving average property on the
moving average component
that the garbage collector cannot
collect it which is why no doubt
that makes a lot of sense to me yeah and
i thought this would work fine
but then what happened was you know it's
a chat app i kept it open for a while
and i
opened the memory pane i see every once
in a while that
a gc happens and it moves you know it
it collects some memory the memory goes
down a little bit
but it's pretty clear that the trend is
up and to the right this is one of those
graphs where up into the right is
actually bad
and what this was basically showing me
is that it's a memory leak
right that every g every time gc
happened it wasn't able to collect all
the memory so i just kept accumulating
more and more memory and
eventually if i kept this chat app open
for
another day or so my computer will have
random memory
memory leaks but v8 only collects
objects that you can actually reach
you node out your moving average uh
field
so the garbage collector should be able
to reclaim its memory shouldn't that
yeah so it's a common mistake but it's
still pretty subtle i'm sure the
more seasoned web developer would have
spotted it right away
so what's going on is that the websocket
is holding on to all the event listeners
strongly which means that until they are
explicitly removed
everything that is reachable via the
event listener is also considered
reachable and thus
not collectible by the garbage collector
so you see that use of
this.events.push inside the event
listener
as long as that use is inside there the
whole moving average instance
is reachable from within the event
listener and thus
not garbage collectible so even when i
nulled it out
in the moving average component it was
still considered alive by the garbage
collector
to deal with this folks often use what's
called a disposable pattern where i have
a a method that manually removes the
event listener called dispose
and that's kind of annoying and to use
that the way i would do it is before i
null it out in the moving average
components
i would have to remember to manually
call dot bespoke
what is this c plus plus you have to
manually manage your memory although the
whole point of calculation was that you
don't have to bother with that sort of
stuff
yeah exactly and it's so easy to forget
it too
and this is all because the event
listeners can't be garbage collected
until you manually remove them so what
if there was a way to actually tell the
engine
don't let me keep you from garbage
collecting this thing even though
it's reachable then you don't have to
remember to manually call dispose
or even need the disposable pattern and
it turns out
there's a new standard feature in
javascript that lets you do exactly this
weak rifts all right and before we go
into that i have to give a quick
disclaimer so we graphs are advanced
feature that's hard to use correctly
because garbage collection is
unpredictable and very different from
browser browser
and even from even different from front
to run of the same browser because of
that unpredictability we didn't add weak
drafts to the web for many years
and you hopefully will never run into a
memory leak or a bug that legibility
needs it but on the rare
occasion that you actually legitimately
need a weak graph finally you can use it
and fix your problem at the root all
right back to
the main programming so how am i using
weak refs here to solve the previous
problem
i still have this event listener but now
instead of directly registering that
event listener function
with the socket i wrap it in a weak ref
it is the
what's called the target of the we graph
and inside
the actual event listener i deref the
weak ref
and i call the function and this kind of
indirection basically means that
the function that is actually holding
the moving average component alive via
this.events.push
is no longer kept from being garbage
collected because
it is a weakly held reference inside a
weak ref
okay what is weakcraft.traff return i
see you're using
optional chaining function called syntax
here yeah good eye on that
that that was not an example that we
showed earlier but like
optional chaining for property you can
also optional chain a
function call so if it's undefined then
you don't end up making the call and the
whole thing is undefined but that
also suggests that draft here when the
thing is actually collected
will return undefined to recap here what
it basically means is that
you have to manually call draft because
we're no longer
preventing the garbage collector from
from collecting
the uh the event listener since it's
wrapped up in a weak ref
so every time you want to access it you
have to manually drive
and if the garbage collector has
collected it then dref
will return undefined okay so in this
case
the listener is reachable by this dot
listener and once a particular moving
average instance isn't reachable
then the component and the component
knows it out
then the whole thing can be connected
right exactly because we're no longer
accidentally keeping moving average
alive anymore via the event listener
we can go back to what i naively thought
would work in the first place when i no
longer need
all the data in the moving average
instance i would just null it out and
let the gc do its thing
okay no way but hold on but now you've
got this
strongly held listener uh on the actual
event listener that's calling the weak
graph
yeah that's a it's that's a good point
you know i thought
you wouldn't spot that but that's
exactly right even though
with this weak rift in direction i still
have this event listener remember the
socket still keeps strongly it just
holds on to all the event listeners
until i
register it i still have this extra
event listener
so what do i do there there is a
companion feature to wikraps called
finalization registry that lets me do
the thing that's needed which is i want
the garbage collector to tell me
when it has collected something so that
i can perform some action
at the point that an object has been
collected or in gc parlance
finalized that feature is called
finalization registry
on this slide what you see is that i
make a finalization registry
and when i add the new event listener i
also register with the finalization
registry meaning
when the inner listener the thing that
actually does the this.events.push is
collected and remember it's collectible
now because it's
held in a weak ref when that's collected
it's going to run this
function that i passed the finalization
registry asynchronously
to remove the event listener cleaning up
all the excess memory
now again this is an advanced feature
and hopefully you'll never need it
so it doesn't actually pass the object
itself into the finalizer there's a good
uh
observation there you see that the thing
that actually gets past the finalizer
are some other values the object that
you want to
observe the finalization of that's
already been collected so you don't get
that back
in this case the thing we need to
perform the finalization action to
unregister
are the socket and the wrapper listener
and that's what we pass to the
finalization
registry all right that makes sense yeah
and like i said this is a
this is an advanced feature and this
example here is pretty dense
i recommend that you follow the link on
the screen there to
follow our full explainer on the v8.dev
website for the feature
so with all of that work i opened up the
memory panel again i
kept my chat app on for a while i start
and stop measuring the latency
and now i see that every time a gc does
happen
it's able to reclaim basically all the
memory and then
over a longer period of time i'm no
longer accumulating memory
and yeah it looks like i fixed the leak
looks pretty tricky like i've
collected garbage before and i don't do
it particularly deterministically myself
yes garbage collection is not
predictable it's not it's
non-deterministic don't depend on
always running and that's why we we have
kept saying that
we crafts and finalization registry is
an advanced feature
so and that's a good point too um given
the unpredictability of the garbage
collector are there other things that
the engine does to make apps slimmer
actually yeah basically doing a lot of
work to reduce its memory consumption
there's actually been two major projects
that landed last year which have focused
on this points compression and v8 light
and i can actually talk about both of
them very quickly
so point to compression first of all um
you've probably
heard that machines are 32-bit or 64-bit
on 32-bit machines we have 32-bit
pointers on 64-bit machines we have
64-bit pointers
and the whole point of this pun intended
is that
32-bit pointers can reference up to 4
gigabytes of memory
64-bit pointers can reference up to 18
exabytes of memory which
is quite a lot more and chrome wants to
be able to run
in 64-bit so that it can access more
than four gigabytes of memory
yeah chrome definitely needs more than
four gigs yeah all right
we've all heard we've all seen the same
memes and
you know fair enough if you've got a
hundred times open with a thousand
images and they're playing games and
they're playing music
it's going to use our memory but
not necessarily each individual tab not
necessarily each individual
v8 instance and the key observation of
point compression is that actually
we can probably restrict each va
instance to
be less than four gig and if we can
restrict it to be less than 4 gig
that means we can pre-allocate a 4 gig
area for it and force all objects to be
allocated inside of that area
and now instead of referencing those
objects by a 64-bit pointer
we can reference them by an offset like
this under pointer compression
you can take your 64-bit pointer and
then you can split it in half
you can split it into a base and an
offset the base is the start of that
four giga allocation area and the offset
is the offset within it
and then you only have to store the
offset on objects which means that your
pointers go
half the size they go back to 32-bit
size
guessing it wasn't just easy as that it
definitely wasn't
it was a whole journey and there's a
whole blog post describing that journey
which was very exciting
but as a little spoiler i can tell you
that on typical websites
we reduce memory by about forty percent
yeah that's uh those are some very
impressive numbers forty percent
but what if a web app or an ogs program
really wants to use more than
the four gigs are you constricting apps
to only have four gigs of memory
well kind of but also not really
first of all with points compression
those objects are a lot smaller so you
can fit
a lot more of them into that four
gigabyte allocation area and also
this 4 gig only applies to a single v8
instances
javascript object heap so for example
typed arrays
they have their own external memory
backing so they're not included
wasm instances have their own 4 gigabyte
allocation area so those are separate
even other va instances inside of web
workers
and on other tabs have their own 4gb
location area
so only restricting one v8 instance not
all of them
the other big project last year was v8
light
and this was this was a really
interesting one because we thought to
ourselves
what would happen if we just gave up on
performance
and tried to just improve memory how far
could we actually get
for memory constrained devices where v8
just couldn't run at all without the
memory that it needed
yeah that's an interesting thought
experiment i guess if you run slowly
that's better than not being to run at
all because you're out of memory right
absolutely
the approach that we took was to just
look at typical websites and
look at what kind of things arctic
actually taking up memory there
48 was user data there's not
really much we can do about that uh
projects like point compression are
going to reduce that by a lot
but we can't really have any targeted
optimizations that reduce the amount of
data that users
create and there's this big bucket of
other because there's always a big
bucket called other and we couldn't
reduce that either with targeted
optimizations
but we did look at some of the top users
of memory and we decided to
try and target those right so right off
the bat if you're not worried about
performance at all you don't need to
optimize code
that makes sense to me absolutely um and
if you don't need to optimize code you
don't need to really collect type
feedback either because that's just
storing the data that we need for
optimization and it's only used for
performance
even the bike agent that we generate you
don't have to store that you can just
compile it on the fly whenever you need
it and get rid of it afterwards sounds a
little
different to me though by code is
unoptimized code and if you're even
getting rid of that that sounds like
you're giving up more than just a little
bit of performance
yeah the first prototypes of v8 light
were pretty slow
but then we realized that we could get a
lot of these gains without actually
sacrificing performance at all just by
being a little bit lazier
yeah i'm something of an expert being
lazy myself yeah i'm pretty good at
being lazy myself too
but as an expert in laziness you know
right
that being lazy doesn't just mean not
doing anything at all
it means not doing anything until you
you're really required to
so we took the same approach with va
let's talk about those
feedback factors that i mentioned
previously the type feedback
you're not going to make get much
benefit from type feedback if you only
run a function once or twice
it's only where you can start benefiting
you after you run it tens or hundreds of
times
so we can delay creating this type
feedback until
we've already had a couple of runs of
this function taking off some of those
feedback vectors
but not all of them same thing with
source positions we only need those
for printing line numbers when we print
exception stack traces or for printing
uh stack traces in devtools so if we can
delay calculating those two later then
we save a lot of space as well
even by code we have this capability of
getting rid of a bicode that we don't
need
so we can just get rid of old bytecode
keep around by code that we're still
using
and save a little bit of memory there
and there were a bunch of tiny projects
targeting these top memory users which
are described in this blog post in a lot
more detail
but again spoiler alert they reduce
memory by 10
to 30 on typical websites nice so
there's actually been a lot more going
on in v8
in the last year we only had time to
talk about a couple of projects
i recommend you visit our blog where we
post about new versions of v8 we talk
about
exciting new things that we just like to
talk about
it's a great read and we look forward to
seeing you there thank you very much for
all the viewers who joined us for this
whirlwind tour of
the java what's new in the javascript
language and the new developments in the
engine itself that makes learning
javascript both faster and to use less
memory
we definitely didn't have time to go
into all the new features that were
added to javascript so please give our
blog
a read thank you very much thanks
everyone
[Applause]
[Music]