If you are building website today
chances are, you are using some sort of build tools
[Mariko]  all right so one question
when you are starting a new project or
you are giving brand new repo and then
like, "Hey Surma, please start this project"
where do you start
what tools do you choose like tell me
about your, like, setup.
[Surma] ah, this has evolved
so much over time
[Jason] I I take a long time to decide
and I usually start out without a bundler
[Adam] my preferred starting place is
I just want to write latest JS
latest CSS and the rest of it is out
of my way until I'm gonna solve it.
It really depends on what the project is
I've been building a lot of static sites
lately and 11ty is a recently I guess a
relatively new tool for static site
generation and I've been converting some
Jekyll sites into that and it's just
felt so nice and not super robust which
is what you sort of need for a static
site,  but then if I am building a more
dynamic project I'll either go with like
NextJS or Gatsby if I want like react
with a static site because they like how
it parses out to just HTML CSS and
JavaScript but there's a thousand tools
and it really just depends
that's the answer it depends
So I was a webpack
user and I use webpack because at the
time it was the only one that supported
code splitting
because like I knew I just needed to add this tag in the head
but like the HTML plug-in had went
no this is mine now you may not touch
and then other things like
in the earlier days of Service Worker
I wanted to... I just wanted like a list of the output files
I want like you know let me know what the
the hash is going to be for these files
but reading the webpack plug-in Docs
I just, I was getting so frustrated
I couldn't figure it out
I used to use gulp or Grunt a lot
because at least I understood what's
happening and then with webpack
I really didn't understand what's happening
Now over time I have kind of
fallen in love with Rollup
So I have my own build system
that I've been managing
it's probably my sixth build system I've made
if you go look at my Github history, I have
a Grunt one, I have a Make one, I have gulp one
I I've been following all these build tools for
a long time
Here's how I feel about Web projects is complexity is inevitable
There's no way to get around it and
you're either injecting complexity from
the beginning and making it worse
or you're waiting until you're
complexity confronts you.
[Marko] Yes even if you start simple complexity is inevitable
Idea of making website in principle is straightforward
You make HTML document
add style to it
and add some functionality to it too
but in practice
web development gets a lot more complex
Your application code may depend on
outside libraries or different modules
you might be importing web fonts
or you might be pre-rendering a portion of a
page as a static site so that it can get
delivered faster to the users
and chances are you're probably using build tools to manage all of these complexities
but because tools expects
certain set up sometimes seemingly
simple tasks like add a line to HTML
gets harder to accomplish there are many
challenges like this in web development
so let's look at how we manage JavaScript
In the past we've written
everything in independent file or
different script tags and carefully
combine them or add it to HTML by ourselves
The way we write JavaScript we
used to like have this like massive file
the humans needed to know which one goes
first and which one goes after
Yeah and even like you're you're making me
remember where I started with bundling
which was a PHP script that concatenated
all my JavaScript files together which
now feels wrong but at the time felt
very powerful
[Mariko] but now we have modules
which means dependency of each modules
are specified in the code which means a
build tool can analyze a file and create
bundle for us
even better, some tool like webpack
analyze which part of the code
is actually being used
and extracted it to make smaller
bundles
[Mariko] when we started writing JavaScript this way
I feel like webpack
came in the scene as a tool of choice
with you know things that has a lot of bells and whistles and do things
like tree shaking and scope hosting so
could you explain how webpack handles
this module javascript field
[Jason] Yeah so webpack supports like a huge number of module formats
like some of the common ones obviously ES modules,  CommonJS, everybody knows about
but it actually
supports parsing and understanding the
structure of SystemJS modules and AMD
modules and even Wasm imports and so
it takes all that information and in its
in-memory graph representation
it attaches that and can use it to you know
if you only imported one thing from a
module it can essentially delete the
export from that module that you didn't
use and that way that code path won't
end up in your bundle and when you take
that your fragment it out you know maybe
that export was using another import
from another module and now that's
unused you can see how flowing that
information through the graph eventually
you could end up removing a fair bit of code
So webpack doesn't actually convert
modules to an internal source format it
is more focused on understanding them
and their structure as they exist on disk
[Mariko] Our JavaScript file does not have
to be a single file so tools like Rollup
will split them up into smaller
chunks
Can you explain why Rollup is really good at it?
[Jake] Yeah so webpack has its own loader and so does Parcel
whereas Rollup by default is ECMAScript modules
like that's where it lives it lives in that world so the
output it generates is like way simpler
than the other tools
in terms of code splitting Rollup's implementation is very
pure, I would say
It will create the smallest number of chunks that it can
but it will create a small chunk
like maybe your chunk just containing one function
if that's the only bit shared by two
entry points
and that's something that webpack and Parcel don't do
They will duplicate that module in both of their bundles
whereas Rollup will always just create a separate chunk
it's very pure it'll never duplicate code
[Mariko] and different script runs in different thread
ideally common dependencies are exported as one chunk
but some tools doesn't understand it so it creates duplicate
[Mariko] What was interesting to me was that the Parcel supports
worker and main thread splitting out of the box
Is there any backstory for that
[Surma] There is and I think I can take a little, tiny bit of credit for Parcel supporting that
because it was I think like February 2018
you me and some others were working
on Squoosh and Squoosh made heavy use of
WebAssembly and put the WebAssembly in
the Web Worker and then
use Comlink to use those Web Workers
and we built Squoosh using webpack
and we figured out over time
but actually the way webpack
built that project
it put a copy of Comlink into the worker
and into the main thread
so the user ended up loading that code twice
now comm leak isn't that big
so it's not that big of a deal but with
bigger dependencies that could actually
become a significant problem and so I
filed a fairly long bug on webpack like
with a graph and everything explaining
why that should change and it hasn't
been fixed yet but it's been discussed a
lot and I think Sean Larkin told me that
webpack 5 will finally be able to
address a problem but shortly after I
opened that bug on webpack
Devon Govett who is the maintainer of Parcel
actually opened an issue himself on Parcel for himself
saying "I think we can do this I
think Parcel can fix this problem" and so
I don't know how long it took him but I
guess a couple months later the bug was closed
and suddenly Parcel now supported this
code splitting across worker boundaries
and that was just really really cool to see
[Mariko] Beyond making JavaScript bundles
build tools help us manage assets too
sometimes separately and sometimes
through JavaScript
So I think that as CSS has evolved
the tooling around it has grown as well
and I think the first like really big instance of CSS tooling
came about with Sass, Less and Stylus
and all of those preprocessor tools
That was when Ruby was like really big
and they were written in Ruby and was
sort of clunky and slow because then you
had to wait for your CSS to process
before it was spit out
from Sass to CSS for example
and then Node came around and that
became a lot faster and Sass was rewritten
and people were still using a lot of
the benefits from that language
the Sass language and then
PostCSS sort of replaced a lot of that need
because it allowed for you to do some of
these same things but instead of
pre-processing and waiting for the
developer to see their CSS file be exported
you could then run through the
CSS file after you had already written it
and then apply transformations and
changes with PostCSS and
that also enabled you to have pluggable very small
bits of code that was way less robust
and just large in terms of developer
fingerprint in your dev files in your
architecture by enabling like these
small plugins like a autoprefixer plugin
or something like for size where if you
wanted to use a size keyword you could
use that you could even write your own
so that was really cool
and I think that that has continued to
the state people use PostCSS all the
time and now you're seeing a lot of
additional CSS tools that allow for
things like tree shaking and some of
these optimizations that are beyond just
minification and that is really
coincided with the switch to framework
based JavaScript as being so prevalent
in the way we architect our projects now
You know naturally I think CSS in JS
happens or maybe it's JS in your CSS
but it's sort of like inevitably what
will happen is you'll find a moment
where you needed something that was just
so richly dynamic that some you know
declarative static styles might not work
for so I've been putting you know CSS in
my JS for a long time but if we're
talking about the new CSS in JS libraries
sort of take your object notation or let
you do extending and abstracting in
different ways at the client side
those are great too they all all options
for writing styles still have foot guns
so you just need to be careful and you'll
learn your tool the more you use it
[Mariko] okay so what's the quarks when
dealing with assets
Yeah, so...
I mean webpack has like a super long history
with various techniques for doing this
at its simplest there are tools for
essentially you can take a loader which
is a transform you apply to a module and
you can apply that to something that
isn't JavaScript to turn it into a
string in a JavaScript file
and so like historically the way that assets have
worked in in webpack has tended to
center around turning them into a
JavaScript thing even for assets where
the asset itself might have dependencies
either on JavaScript or on other assets
it will turn that into a JavaScript
module with a string and turn the
dependencies, you know the CSS import
statements, into JavaScript require calls
and so it will sort of inject them
into the graph by converting them to the
equivalent JavaScript code
[Mariko] Now this is changing in webpack 5 but for other
tools like Parcel assets has been a
center of it from the beginning
One thing it sets parcel apart for many
others that they actually don't use
JavaScript as the entry point but HTML
so what is considered an asset and many
other build tools is their main entry
points for in Parcel land and that makes
sense because on the web that is the
thing we go to we go to HTML pages and
from there on we reference assets so
whether you're reference an image from
JavaScript or from within HTML, Parcel
will understand that and that's actually
really cool and it does this to many
many layers so if your reference a CSS
file from HTML and that CSS file
references in images all of these things
are tracked by Parcel and there will be
hashed and they will get a version
number and whatnot so it actually builds
an entire asset graph
[Marko] What Surma just explained
is called asset hash cascading
if one file in a graph is updated, then the
file hash changes
and because of that, hash of the file that used the updated asset should also change
this is important so that we can control cache for better performance
let's see how Rollup handles it
Yeah so right now
hashing is Rollup's weakness
and it's something they know about and it's
something
they are going to be working on fixing very very soon
so when you generate the hash for a file you know
that little bit of the file names to
go at the end, all of the hex letters and numbers
you need to do that as late
in the process as possible and you want
it to just be based on the contents of
the file like not the directory it's in
not your config settings anything like
that
if you've got JavaScript which imports JavaScript which imports JavaScript
it does the right thing with hashing
you know you change a leaf one
and it changes all of the other ones in the chain
because you know all the URLs have updated
whereas with assets you use a magic string in Rollup to
to...and Rollup will change that to be the assets URL but it does that after hashing
so you update your asset it changes hash
it updates the JavaScript file fine
but it doesn't update the hash of that JavaScript
so, it's a weakness but they are fixing it
[Mariko] these differences and gotchas in our build tools are constant source of frustration
as Una said, the best tool for the job
really depends on your project
And so, we wanted to make it easier for you to navigate this landscape
tooling.report is a new website that gives developers like you
an overview of various features supported by different build tools
we built this website so you can evaluate and choose the right tools for your next project
or maybe you are in the middle of migrating frontend infrastructure
and hitting a road block
tooling.report should help you answer your questions
we've essentially written a test suite for different tools
based on common web development practices
so you can read why those tests are relevant
and see how each tool handles it
and when you are ready to implement it yourself
you can look at our test code to see how you might integrate certain features into your build setup
we also welcome your contributions so if you think
certain features should get tested
please raise an issue on the repo