[Music]
hey there welcome to web dev live
I'm deal now man and I work on the web
developer ecosystem at Google and I'm
delighted to kick off our online event
first though I want to acknowledge the
times we're in we're dealing with a
global pandemic that has taken a huge
toll on us all and most recently we
witnessed two events which have once
again surfaced the systemic racism in
our society that we must do everything
we can to eradicate you know these
events have been really humbling they're
showing us how much work we have ahead
of us but they also show us the power of
community so we join you today and over
the next three days in the spirit of
being together and helping each other
because we're upset when we had to
cancel Google i/o and I kept thinking
about an empty Shoreline Amphitheatre on
the days that some of us would have
congregated a web developers reached out
showing these same feelings wishing we
could be discussing ideas and enjoying
the hallway track whether you're joining
us from your couch kitchen or hammock we
hope you're safe and ready to kick web
dev live into gear now we'll be coming
to you in different time zones each day
reaching you no matter where you are on
the globe will be bringing you content
from across our teams as well as members
from their web community at large now
each day you'll have Googlers on standby
to answer your questions in real-time so
as you're watching the session simply
head over to the live chat on web dev
slash live or on YouTube and just ask
away
now when coronavirus became global we
really felt the need to stabilize this
resulted in a spawning chrome releases
and temporarily rolling back the same
site cookie changes now we wanted to
track chrome usage and see what changed
to make sure that we could be on top of
any ecosystem changes - you probably
won't be surprised that we saw surges
and usage of meteor api's as video chat
and streaming really soared now also
some types of content so large traffic
surges
such as food commerce entertainment
health science etc and many developers
will focus in on making sure these sites
were as resilient as possible that's
when we gathered our best practices and
made them available on web dev slash
Kovac 19 we saw a lot of developers
scramble to make changes to their web
sites and many created new ones
governments had to jump on this to make
sure the people had all of the critical
information that was changing rapidly
I remember seeing Alex Russell tweet
about one of these government sites from
the state of California we were really
inspired with their work and wanted to
ask them about their experience and they
kindly agreed to join us so let's
welcome Aaron Hines the engineering tech
lead on the project thank you great to
be here so Aaron I'm really curious
about how this site even all came
together the alpha dot ca.gov team was
formed in December of 2019 by an
helicopter Arte to bring human centered
design processes to the state of
California and improve their online
services we built a lot of prototypes
for things like how to help people
review the safety of their tap water and
see if they're eligible for subsidized
phone services and to prepare for
wildfires and then when the pandemic at
the state were asked to stand up the
public response site Connie so when a
government team has to build something
like this like how do you go about it
what do you all call principals the
number one goal is to make something
that works well for everybody and the
technical considerations they're passing
accessibility audits making sure it
works with keyboard navigation with
screen readers and that it has a smooth
experience on low-end hardware we use
the cheapest phone which we get from the
local Cricket Wireless as our test
device and the non-technical
considerations are the readability
what's the grade level of all the
content and are we really building
something that users need and iterating
based on their feedback got it now I've
been trying to picture the time pressure
that you had to get this sight out he
tell us a little bit about how you
actually built the sign and how you
manage the trade-offs between quality
and that time line sure it's definitely
an accelerated time
and put the site up in four days then
the governor announced a statewide
lockdown and we had millions of visitors
really happy that we chose a static site
generator for that because it helped us
whether the traffic smoothly
we chose the Lebanese or the state
static site generator and we augment
that with web components and
surveillance API is built on nodejs got
it we're actually fans of eleventy too
we use it on web dev and really like it
was this kind of a new set up for the
team to build a web site like this or
have you been doing this for a while
I remember reading the article about how
web dev was built and being really happy
that we were using some of the same
tools we started using 11d at the end of
last year just to use it for a blog on
new Alfred on CA gov and when we used it
for the koban 19 site it's built on
content authored in the WordPress
environment and then we consume it with
the word best API and use github actions
for the eleventy production build got it
so you know now you've got the site out
there now I'm curious what's next fate
for you and the team next things for the
team are continuing to respond to the
pandemic we're going to be getting back
to helping improve other online services
and we're hiring check us out at news
dot alpha dot ca.gov if you want to help
out we're talking about eleven E and the
other tools that we're using I wanted to
mention that lighthouse is an incredibly
important tool for us because
performance is such a paramount concern
and I love the way that it came affiance
my development you can get the rest of
your teammates challenged each other and
say who can put up some more points
today we really need to get that score
up and I some I'm curious who who's
winning on the points race and I've been
really impressed and how you know you
think of like performance being a key
part of the accessibility story in
general Warren it's been really
inspiring to see the work that the U and
the team did here again at an incredibly
stressful time thank you so much for
coming on and sharing the story with us
thank you
now it's been great to see developers
like Aaron focus on accessibility
resilience and performance and we've
made some announcements over the last
month about a program that brings us all
together under the umbrella of web
vitals to hit more let's welcome
Elizabeth a p.m. on the chrome team to
explain thanks Dan yeah there have been
a lot of product updates and releases
and I'm really excited to go over them
with you yeah it's been particularly
busy here over the past couple of months
so be great to have you get us up to
speed on webb vitals and what developers
should be really considering here yep
that's great let's dive in first off
what our core web vitals they are a set
of user centric metrics and thresholds
that apply to all web pages across all
industry verticals and all types of
experiences on the web they are signals
to developers and business stakeholders
about the basic health of your site and
as such they should be measured by
everybody but okay I jumped straight
into definitions let's take a step back
why did we introduce core what vitals as
a thing there are already tons of
metrics lots of guidance about how to
measure your site's performance
how do core web vitals help us well
let's go back to our foundational goal
we want to create outlandishly
phenomenal experience for all of our
users and it's not just out of the
goodness of our hearts either we know
that every time we have a rage clicker
on our site we lose out on a reader a
customer or a client also we want a
money bug so there is this mythical
absolutely fabulous experience that
we've set our sights on creating it
seems easy until you realize that the
unicorn horn requires both loading and
interactivity performance measurement
and the rainbow well the rainbow
requires an entire rum setup for each
color so there you are watching your
flying unison unicorn dachshund and you
realize that you have this it's gorged
on a bit too much JavaScript it doesn't
respond when you're issuing it commands
and that's upsetting but it's going to
take quite a bit to get this to this so
the question is where do you start well
in order to know if you've improved we
need to know what to measure to know
what to measure we need to define our
goals so put another way what makes a
web experience shine this is where the
core dimensions of quality come in there
are foundational elements of a user
experience that make
and shine above the competition content
needs to load quickly we've all been
there
the longer we have to wait the more
likely we are to bail so your pages have
to load fast interactivity is just as
important you're clicking and nothing is
happening no fun you don't just need
content to be visible you need it to be
available for use lastly we want a page
to be stable and predictable just a few
pixels moving around can make a huge
difference these core dimensions of
quality reflect user centric signals
that have long been mission-critical for
you and your site's success so we are
closer to defining quality but how do we
measure these quality dimensions and
that's where representative metrics come
in to represent fast-loading we have
largest contentful paint or LCP it
provides insight into how quickly a user
is able to see the meat of what they are
expecting and wanting out of a page for
responsive interactivity we have first
input delay or fit this metric has been
a critical signal for developers for
some time to understand how long a page
takes to respond to a user's initial
input and finally to represent visual
stability we have cumulative layout
shift CLS CLS measures the amount that
the elements within the viewport move
around during load time ok so we know
how to measure our core quality
dimensions and let's say my LCP is three
seconds do I celebrate wait I don't
actually have any idea whether or not
that's good so I need to evaluate my
performance on a spectrum for each
metric which is where the final element
of Korowai vitals comes in our
thresholds for each representative
metric we have clear goal posts around
what constitutes a good experience one
that needs improvement and one that's
poor so for instance for LCP anything
that is 2.5 seconds or less is on its
way to being a unison anything between
2.5 and four seconds needs some work and
anything above four seconds is needing
quite a bit of love so to finish up our
definition of what our core web vitals
the initiative is a combination of three
things first is user centric quality
dimensions then we have represented
of metrics of those dimensions and
finally thresholds to help you evaluate
whether or not your performance is good
or not against any given metric but
there is one more piece of really
important information we need to know
how many page loads need to hit the
thresholds for the core web vitals
metrics to constitute a good experience
so say we have a hundred users if only
one of them has an LCP below 2.5 seconds
do I pass Korowai vitals the answer is
no core web vitals uses the 75th
percentile value of all pageviews in the
field to evaluate against the thresholds
in other words if at least 75% of page
views to a site meet the good threshold
the site is classified as having a good
performance for that metric and this
applies to all three metrics LCP FID and
CLS the 75th percentile is used to
evaluate all three core Web vitals is a
holistic package of everything you need
to create the foundation of a healthy
site they are valuable because they show
you exactly where to start to set
yourself up for success if 75% of your
users are getting fast interactive
stable content its cause for celebration
but as we know there are other
dimensions of quality that are extremely
important accessibility security mobile
friendliness there are a lot of
dimensions that make a basic unison even
more fabulous and are important to your
site's success so don't stop measuring
these if you already are and if you
aren't already
once you've optimized your core web
idols you can begin to venturing into
measuring and benchmarking against other
important vitals that are relevant to
your business and your users core Web
vitals are just as the name indicates
they are core and provide you with a
solid foundation upon which to further
optimize given how important it is to
quantify a user's experience accurately
in order to be successful on the web we
are constantly working to find ways to
better measure all quality dimensions
what this evolution has often meant in
the past is a stream of new metrics
tweaks to existing metrics and new
guidance many times at an unpredictable
cadence we know how difficult this can
be when trying to set goals aligned
roadmaps and good organizational
because of this we want to set a
predictable cadence of updates to Cora
vitals they will be refreshed once a
year around the time of Google i/o to
ensure that they reflect the latest in
our learnings and this includes
adjustments to the set of metrics as
well as the thresholds looking ahead
towards 2021 we will be providing
regular updates on future metric
candidates motivations and
implementation status okay so this is
all fine and good but how do I get
started to know whats optimized you have
to measure first and Korowai vitals are
now in all of your favorite developer
tools and there are more than what is
listed here including a new web vitals
library and a bunch of ecosystem tools
that have already adopted them as you
can see core web vitals are available
across the board you're able to measure
them for a specific page for your origin
locally in the lab and from real users
in the field remember that first input
delay is only measurable in the field so
you have to have a real user clicking on
your page in order to measure it but
that doesn't mean you can't use lab
tools to help you improve it total
blocking time TBT is a proxy lab metric
for FID that allows you to debug and
improve your interactivity in the lab
before you users ever have to experience
a bad vid the next obvious question is
again this is great but where do I start
what tool should I use I'm so glad you
asked each tool has its own strengths
for example psi is one of the only
places you can see your lab and field
data in one place and search console is
critical for identifying page types that
need improvement as I mentioned earlier
we're seeing so many great ecosystem
players and production monitoring
solutions already implementing support
for core what vitals and we're really
delighted but again you ask you've shown
me the magical unison and now you've
given me a pallet of tools to choose
from that's amazing but tell me what to
do first okay two things first go to
PageSpeed insights that will give you a
pulse of your core with vitals
performance in both the field and the
lab from crux you'll be able to see
whether or not 75% of your loads are
hitting the core with vitals thresholds
for both your page and your origin in
the field then you can take a look at
your lab data from lighthouse to see
whether or not you are hitting the core
web vitals thresholds for each metric in
a synthetic testing environment this
helps to guide you towards
noble opportunities to improve your
pages performance second check out some
more in-depth talks later today that go
into detail about measuring and
optimising against your core weigh
vitals and with that I'm gonna pass it
back to Dion thank you so much
great yeah thanks for showing us the
context and all of the information
across the whole slew of tools there
Elizabeth my pleasure
one of the critical steps in modern web
development with a lot of influence over
your vitals is your build step that's
where your CSS modules are turned into
real CSS your bundler analyzes your
module graph and optimizations can
really kick in we wanted to go deeper
here to understand the popular bundlers
how they work what they can and cannot
do and how to set them up for success
let's welcome Surma to tell us more hey
Surma
hey Dion so there are many best
practices to follow in web development
knowing them is one thing began in your
build system to follow them as well it's
kind of another beast so do you have
anything - maybe report on that front so
there's two bits on this side of things
on the one hand there are many
developers who want to know what build
tool they should learn and use for the
next project and on the other hand there
are many project that already have a
build tool set up but are looking to
improve their output to tackle both of
these problems we build tooling report
tooling report is a website that you can
actually go to right now tooling report
we create an extensive list of best
practices in web development took what
we think are the four most popular build
tools and checked for each build tool if
it allows you to follow that best
practice and each tool gets a point for
each test and it passes we chose to
start this project with browserify
parcel roll-up and web pack now browser
if I might be surprising to some but the
data indicates that there are still many
sites out there that use browserify
and we want to help those projects
improve their sites as well of course we
have been working with the core teams of
all these tools to make sure that we're
not only used a tool correctly but also
represent them fairly the tests are
subdivided into categories and in the
overview you can get a quick sense of
which tool is excelling at what category
you can get more information on the
tests in the overview and learn more
about it and now this is where I think
tooling report gets really interests
each test has a dedicated page where you
can compare how the tool score on this
specific test there is an in-depth
explanation on why this test is
important and how it relates to best
practices and web development we also
explain how we codify the best practice
and what the expected outcome is and
finally at the bottom you can find an
explanation for each tool and writers
past or why it might have failed this
test if a tool is not passing a test we
will also link to back reports on the
tools issue tracker many of them we have
actually filed ourselves while building
tooling report we also link to a minimal
NPM project that we use to determine the
tools behavior this way tooling report
not only tells you what a tool can and
cannot do but you can also look at the
configuration files and plugins to see
how you can follow a best practice with
this tool this way the site double
functions as a source of documentation
the entire site is open source on github
and we'd love the community to help us
come up with more tests and help us add
modules over time so you can check this
out now on tooling dot report thanks for
joining me soma Cheers now we're all
becoming more aware of the importance of
security and privacy chrome believes in
an open web that's respectful of users
privacy and maintains key use cases that
keeps the web working for everyone
I'd love to welcome Rowan to have a chat
and kind of share some of what's new
here hey there thanks Deon my name is
Ryan and I look after web dev rel for
security privacy payments and identity
or spy for now wow that's a cute
internal name we are part of the wider
trust and safety team with Ingram great
so why don't we start with same site
cookies and the temporary rollback that
that kind of kicked into gear for us
when kovat kind of really started to hit
globally can you kind of share whether
what the latest news is there sure yeah
so hopefully as a lot of you are aware
there's an update to the cookie standard
that's being adopted across Chrome
Firefox edge and others to restrict
cookies to first party by default
along with requiring explicitly marking
cookies for third party contexts now
that's all configured via the same site
attribute
hence same-side cookies we were rolling
this out to staple chrome but decided to
reverse this at the start of April
because the kovat situation saw a huge
jump in demand for online services but
also a huge shift in developers being at
home without their equipment or looking
after their families we made the call
that it was important to prioritize
stability at that moment now these
changes are intended to make the web a
safer place protecting against
cross-site request forgery and trying to
minimize the surface for covert tracking
sadly during a crisis when people are
most vulnerable you see these kind of
scams in the tax jump too so with the
Chrome 84 stable release which is
mid-july or about two weeks from now if
you're watching the stream we are gonna
start rolling this out again across all
chrome versions got it so what I'm
hearing here is that if you haven't
tested your site yet if you haven't made
changes to kind of make sure that
everything works well now is actually
the time to get going absolutely so we
have documentation in examples and
samples out there right now for same
site on web dev as well as on
chromium.org and we'll be covering
implementation and debugging in our
segment on day three okey doke so we all
love cookies but I'm assuming there's
going to be a few more things that we're
going to be talking about in the kind of
general view of trust and safety I'll be
honest with you I am gonna talk about
cookies a lot but the rest of the team
does have a healthier range of interests
okay sounds good so we're gonna cover
things like you know back in 2018
Specter kind of raised its head and we
as a web community started to really
look at what can we do to help make sure
that our users are secure are they gonna
be kind of those type of aspects that
we'll be covering two for sure yeah so
age is gonna be taking us through some
of the new cross-origin opener and
embedder policies or a coop and co-op
for short so like you were saying
Specter was a vulnerability that in a
super short summary meant that malicious
code running in one browser process
might be able to read any data
associated with that process even if
it's from
in origin and that is super bad now one
of the mitigations for that is sight
isolation or putting each sight into a
separate process AG's going to be
running through how the headers allow
sites to opt into that along with a
bunch of other benefits that it brings
as well
got it got it got it okay so we've got
restricting cross-site cookies and then
we've got isolating sites to individual
processes we got this interest in
evolution so I'm sensing there's kind of
a bit of a theme here yeah there is
definitely a theme so we've also got
salmon mod on the team and they're gonna
kick off our little segment to explain
the link between these and really comes
down to the Web today is seeing this
evolution of expectations regarding
privacy that includes users expecting
more transparency and control over their
online data and new regulations
impacting how data can be used and
collected now Google we believe in an
open web that's respectful of the users
privacy whilst also maintaining a
healthy ecosystem so under the banner of
the privacy sandbox we're introducing a
number of standards proposals that aim
to support the use cases that let people
make their living off creating web
content but do that in a way that better
respects user privacy we're also
actively seeking feedback on these
proposals we're participating in all the
open forums the w3c to discuss our
proposals as well as those submitted by
other parties to okay so the web's
evolving and we're getting new
privacy-preserving api's coming in and
we're getting rid of the old cross-site
data leaking API so they're kind of
moving out exactly and one of the ways I
like to think about it with our team as
well is that we're kind of all about the
places where you create relationships on
the web so people should feel in control
of their data when they browse around
the web with a clear choice about what
and where they share things and when
they do want to create a relationship
like signing in to a site or making a
purchase that should be simple secure
and only share what's needed awesome
thanks so much for the brain dump on
what we're thinking about here in the
realm of trust and safety row and I'm
really excited to see the content that's
coming later
on the stream from the team where we can
kind of go into more of a deep dive cool
thanks and I'll see you around now the
web has a great history as a Content
platform with its roots in hyperlinked
documents but digital content has gotten
richer and richer we think the web has a
great role to play here too I'd like to
invite Paul Backhouse to talk about a
new content type that we're really
excited about called web stories
hey Dion hey Paul so what are these web
stories and why are we working on them
my team and I have been hard at work
working on web stories and I'm very
excited to share some updates with you
and yes I'm talking about these kind of
stories you know fullscreen portray
tapped advanced swipe to move on and if
you like wait a second and you do late
to the show then you'd be right but
these are not your standup ward Garden
stories current implementations focus on
ephemerality and ultra low barrier to
creation but our bet is a destroys
format works beyond the ephemeral use
case and can become its own pillar in
the open web media landscape and that's
because they're really cheaper to make
them video and more engaging in a text
article and really important web stories
are different to ward off stories in
many important ways just like a regular
web page you own them you host them and
very important you get the money from
the ads not the platform serving stories
because stories are really a visual
format my friends at Google search and
discover showcasing them in really cool
ways telling me that many more
integrations are coming later this year
we think this can be a great net new
traffic source for web creators these
stories look visually really compelling
but how hard is it actually to create
them if you want the web to be able to
compete with the closed platforms out
there story creation needs to be as
intuitive and fast for all content
creators now lots of people are working
on making web stores a thing but one of
the things my own team is doing is
bringing story creation to WordPress the
most used CMS in the world in the form
of a visual editor coming to you very
soon kind of more about the beta at goog
le slash story editor you'll hopefully
see all the basic editing features you
would expect like smooth image and B
you're handling text controls shape
masking and so on but we're also working
on some you might not expect like this
one we call text magic running in real
time against images from the unsplash
api here target on this feature make
so that the editor always ensures Texas
readable making dynamic decisions about
the background line height and so on I
hope you like it as much as I do yeah it
looks really cool you know I can't wait
to read some of these stories on the web
thanks so much for for sharing their
pool and and thanks again to Paul and
everyone who took the time to join me as
we kick off the event today you know I'm
really excited about the upcoming
sessions starting with the focus on how
to make your website hit its vitals and
discovery through search now please
enjoy the show
remember the whole team is here to chat
with you on web dev slash live and via
YouTube I will see you there today and
I'll be back tomorrow morning for the
day to kick off
[Music]