Hi, everyone. I'm Eiji and today I'm going to talk about
COOP and COEP.
COOP and COEP are names of HTTP headers that let
your web page opt-in to a special state called
'Cross-origin isolated' and gain access to powerful
features such as SharedArrayBuffers acrros platforms,
performance.measureMemory(), JS
Self Profiling API.
If you are interested in using a powerful feature from this
growing list, you will need to opt-in to COOP and COEP.
Also, if you own on a CDN or provide
ads, fonts, images, or other resources that get
loaded in different origins across the web, you
should also watch this video.
I will discuss one HTTP header you can add to ensure
all your customers can properly load your resources.
With that in mind, let's get started.
Composability is a super power of the web.
You can enhance your website's capabilities by simply
adding resources from different sources.
Commonly used services include ads,
web fonts, images, videos, maps,
identity federation, payment solutions, and so
on. These services are quite handy and powerful,
but their cross-origin nature contributes to increased
risk of information leakage.
Malicious parties could take advantage of the situation
and exfiltrate information about your users.
But browsers do a good job at preventing such scenarios.
They keep cross-origin resources separated within a
browsing context group when the web page allows that.
Browsing context group is a group of tabs, windows, and
iframes that share the same context.
The same-origin policy is a security feature that restricts
how documents and scripts can interact with
resources from another origin so that users'
information won't accidentally leak.
The same-origin policy has been doing a good job keeping
the web a safe place... until Spectre
was discovered. Spectre is a vulnerability
found in CPUs that enables malicious web
sites to read memory and the contents across the origin
boundaries. This vulnerability can be exploited
via features that can act as high-precision timers.
This leaves cross-origin resources that are shared
in a single browsing context group at risk.
Even if they are protected by the same-origin policy,
Spectre attacks can bypass that border.
As a quick response, browser vendors decided
to turn off features that could be used to construct
high precision timers.
For example, SharedArrayBuffer.
To mitigate the risk of Spectre and make powerful features
available on the web page, its origin needs
to be isolated from others.
By isolating origins into separate browsing context groups,
Spectre and other exploits that grant permission
to read arbitrary memory in the same process
are no longer able to read cross-origin contents.
This, in turn, allows browsers to bring back
the powerful features on pages that are properly
isolated.
Chrome on desktop enabled 'Site Isolation'.
This allowed us to turn SharedArrayBuffer
back on on desktops. To achieve more robust
isolation, the browser needs an explicit
signal from the web site that they want to be isolated
from cross-origin resources.
That is what COOP and COEP are about.
To enable cross-origin isolation, you need to do three
things. First, set 'Cross-Origin-Opener-Policy:
same-origin' for the main document.
Second, make sure cross-origin resources use
'Cross-Origin-Resource-Policy: cross-origin', or
cross-origin resource sharing.
Third, set 'Cross-Origin-Embedder-Policy: require-corp'
for the main document.
Let's walk through each step to see how they work.
When 'Cross-Origin-Opener-Policy: same-origin' is set,
any cross-origin window opened from the document
will have no access to the opener's DOM - so
'window.opener' will will return null.
This is how the document achieves isolation from
the cross origin window.
To create a cross-origin isolated page, you need to
make sure all cross-origin resources embedded in the
document explicitly allow it to be loaded.
There are two ways to achieve this.
By setting 'Cross-Origin-Resource-Policy: cross-origin'
or applying cross-origin resource sharing.
If you serve resources from a different subdomain that you
have control of, you can simply apply the
'Cross-Origin-Resource-Policy' header.
But what about resources you don't have control of?
If the resource already supports cross-origin resource
sharing, you don't need to do much.
Just append the 'crossorigin' attribute where it's needed.
For resources that don't support it, you should ask the
resource provider to enable the
'Cross-Origin-Resource-Policy' header.
So here's the action item for owners of CDNs
or providers of ads, fonts, images
or other resources embedded across the web: please be
prepared to serve your contents with
'Cross-Origin-Resource-Policy: cross-origin'.
Without supporting it, your resources will be blocked
in the browser and harm your customer's experience at
some point.
With 'Cross-Origin-Embedder-Policy: require-corp'
you can let the web page only load resources that
are explicitly marked as sharable unless
they are served from the same origin.
For example, an image served from
cross-origin without a 'Cross-Origin-Resource-Policy'
header will be blocked like this.
By setting 'Cross-Origin-Resource-Policy: cross-origin'
this image can be displayed.
Note that if you use report-only mode of
Cross Origin Embedder Policy, you can send reports
to a specifed URL without actually blocking
those resources.
I recommend deploying Cross Origin Embedder Policy,
starting with the report-only mode.
That way you can confirm that cross-origin isolation is
in effect without affecting the end users.
Once your page is loaded with COOP and COEP, it
should be in the 'cross-origin isolated' state.
You can verify 'cross-origin isolated' is in effect
by checking
'self.crossOriginIsolated' boolean flag in JavaScript. This
flag
is not available in Chrome yet, but it's coming soon.
Let's recap.
Start testing with COOP and COEP and opt-in to cross-origin
isolation today.
You can learn how that works and why they are needed
in more details at web.dev/coop-coep and
web.dev/why-coop-coep.
If you're an owner of a CDN or provider
of ads, fonts, images or other resources,
please start adopting cross-origin resource policy.
You can learn more at
resourcepolicy.fyi
Additionally, Sam is covering this topic by showing you
how DevTools can help you with a variety of issues,
which includes new functionality for COOP and COEP.