Welcome back to web.dev LIVE - APAC edition.
Now, it's been great to be together over the last two days.
And now let's finish strong on day three.
We've spoken about the role the Web has played with you
building websites that share COVID data online, allowing
work and learning to happen from home, much needed
entertainment, and keeping up with world news.
One of the big shifts we've seen is around retail and
commerce. Now online retail has nearly doubled
its share of credit card spending, and e-commerce is now
30% of retail, growing 15%
in just 6 weeks.
There's been a flood of activity as businesses rush to get
online.
Pedro Freitas, head of Loja Integrada, which is part
of the VTEX platform, shared how they saw the doubling
of sites being created every single day.
When they saw this, they kindly offered unlimited plans
for healthcare clients.
When it comes to food we're back to 1992 levels
of share between groceries and restaurant orders.
My omelets are certainly looking a lot better.
And then there's the story of Foodleh.
A couple of university students quickly built a site
to allow people to order directly from the local street
hawkers in Singapore, bridging the online-offline
gap. And then there's Sebastian Carbonero,
a high school student from San Marcos, California,
who jumped into action to create FoodBanks, a website
that helps you find, well, local food banks.
Now, we continue to be impressed with the ingenuity that
some of you are displaying as you help people in need right
now.
And speaking of being impressed, we're really fortunate to
have a really healthy framework ecosystem on the web where
different approaches can be explored in different ways.
Now, Vue is a popular and well-loved framework with
particularly large usage in the APAC region.
So we wanted to invite Evan You, the creator of Vue, for a
chat.
Hi Dion, nice to be here.
Hey, Evan, thanks so much for joining us.
Now, I'd kinda love to start at the beginning of the
history of Vue and the story as you've gone through
different evolutions from version 1 to 2, and now
what you're working on with version 3.
Sure. Vue started out as a personal
experimental project back in 2013
and was first made public in February 2014.
The initial goal was really just to create something
that I would enjoy using myself.
It was a very small library combining the data
binding that was inspired by Angular 1 with
a ES5 getter/setter based reactivity
system.
Because we used getter/setters, it was not a IE8
compatible when it came out, which a lot of people took
issues with, but I'm kinda glad we made that decision
in the early days.
Later on we released version 2 and started
adding more and more supporting
libraries to it.
So, for example, we added a router, we added a CLI.
So as we added more parts, it started to become more like
a framework.
But we still kinda loosely
followed the concept that it should be incrementally
adoptable so it's not as
monolithic as some other solutions,
but also it's no longer just a single
library that does only one thing.
The major change in version 2 was the introduction of
the virtual DOM as the underlying rendering layer which
opened up a few interesting capabilities at the time.
For example, server-side rendering or rendering to
other platforms.
Right now we are hard at work in finishing up version 3,
which is a major rewrite and it brings up
a lot of new interesting features and
changes.
There are so many things, so I'll just mention a few
highlights here.
We added the composition API, which exposes the
lower level reactivity API's inside view
for advanced larger composition and reduce
large applications.
We rewrote the reactivity system using ES2015
proxies, which greatly improved performance.
The rendering layer rewrite is also seeing
great performance improvements.
The bundler, the library
itself is now fully tree-shaking compatible, so you will
see smaller bundles.
We added first class TypeScript support, more modular
internal architecture for better maintenance
and tooling integration.
So there is a lot more we are
shipping in Vue 3.
We are still hard at work, ironing out some
of the rough edges, but it's going to be ready very soon.
quite a while with 2013 being the birth of Vue
and obviously you worked on the Web before then.
I'm curious, as you've seen the evolutions and
seen what's going on right now, how do you feel about
Web development in 2020?
What are the most pressing issues?
What are you focusing on?
What are the problems that you see that Web developers
have, and how do you feel you and Vue can help there?
Sure.
I think the ecosystem right now is at a transition
period where we are seeing a lot of
these new language standards features,
new platform capabilities are
finally stable and consistent and shipped
in all these evergreen browsers.
So all these mainstream browsers
in their latest version now have very consistent support
for these latest features.
And IE11 is finally on the way of phasing
out. So that presents an opportunity
for new stacks or new
tooling to break free of the shackles of these legacy
problems and rethink how we can
best take advantage of these new features that we
can finally use for the large majority
of our users. So I think,
for example, most
of these major browsers now support native ES module
imports, which present some interesting
technical possibilities that we can leverage to
build something - to rethink
our development workflow.
Got it. Yeah, I've actually been watching you in your
Twitter feed explore some of these things.
I've seen you working on Vite and VitePress.
I was wondering if you could explain a little bit more on
what these are doing.
Sure.
Vite is
a web development build tool that combines a dev
server with a build step.
Now, the interesting part is in the dev server, we are
leveraging the browsers native ES module import
handling to provide a bundle free development experience.
So instead of bundling your whole app, Vite
lets the browser import your modules as needed,
using native imports and only processing them on-demand
when the browser actually requests them.
So this has a few advantages over the traditional
bundling-based dev servers.
The first thing is when you have
a large app you may have a lot of modules
in your application but when you are working
on a specific part of your application, maybe
you only need to import a subset of these modules.
So on-demand import compilation
using Vite's approach allows you to only compile
the necessary modules for the part that you're
actually working on. So this results in a much faster
server startup time in large applications.
The second part is Vite also supports Hot Module
Replacement on top of native ES module imports.
Now, with native use module imports,
because we don't have to do the whole bundling scope
crawling when handling Hot Module Replacement,
the implementation is actually much simpler and much more
efficient.
So it will stay blazing fast even
as your app grows which keeps the
development feedback loop fast no matter how big
your app is.
So I believe this really presents an
interesting option because the development experience is so
close to the old days where we first got into
web development, where you just have an index.html
page and you import some scripts to
get things going. Vite tries to
simplify the whole development setup
and present a development experience as close to
the original vanilla web development experience as
possible, but without giving up all the modern
new tooling capabilities that we are used to.
So it's still
kind of experimental at this stage, but we're getting
a lot of good feedback from users already.
Got it. That's really exciting.
I love this new trend towards
dev time not having to deal with bundling
and the like and production. We can still obviously do a
lot of that, push out all of the optimizations we can.
Obviously, everything we can do to help users makes sense.
So that's Vite. What about VitePress?
Well, how does that tie into this?
Oh yeah.
If you don't know VitePress, VitePress is a remake
of VuePress and VuePress is a static side
generator built on top of Vue, which allows
you to write markdown, use Vue components
in your markdown, and write custom themes using
Vue as a Vue application.
Now VuePress was based on webpack,
so VitePress is essentially a remake of VuePress, but using
Vite as the underlying
build tool.
So first of all, that provides obviously a much faster
development experience, a faster server startup, and faster
updates when you edit a page.
Another aspect of it is we are baking a lot of
performance best practices into VitePress.
We see a lot of static side generators based on
universal JavaScript frameworks.
For example, we have Next.js, which is
nuxt.js for Vue, which are both excellent projects, but
when we are using services to
send static content to the client we often face
the problem of the double payload issue, where
you're sending the static content as HTML, but you're also
sending a lot of JavaScript which was used to render the
same content, which is
useless when it's on a client.
And then we're spending time on the client to hydrate those
content using JavaScript.
So there's a lot of room for improvement here and VuePress
tries to tackle that.
It takes advantage of Vue 3's compiler to
do static analysis and we automatically
detect all the static parts that won't change
in your page.
Then we concatenate them - stringify
them - into static strings and eventually
safely remove them during the production build.
So that decouples the current page JavaScript
payload of your page from the content.
So you're only paying for the dynamic
bits inside your page and all the static
content will have no impact on
the JavaScript payload size and have no impact on the
client side hydration performance.
So I think that's a pretty significant improvement
to how VuePress was handling things.
When we finish it, we're excited to see how much of
a performance improvement this can bring to our users
across the board.
Got it. I have a feeling we're going to be hitting some
core web vital thresholds here.
That sounds great. Thank you.
Now we're going live to livestream right
now to an APAC-friendly time zone
and we talked about how Vue is a particularly
popular in APAC, and I was curious on
what you think caused that and what we can learn from that?
I think Vue's popularity in APAC
definitely has a lot to do with me
being Asian.
Personally, I am very active in the Chinese developer
community as well, and a
lot of people probably heard about Vue through me.
But at the same time, a more
important aspect is good localization of our
documentation.
So when we first worked on the documentation,
because I am a native Chinese speaker and I know a lot of
Chinese developers sort of struggle when
they see really dense technical text written in English.
It's not that they cannot attempt to read it.
It's just when you are reading something
that's not in your native tongue, it takes so much longer.
It makes it so much less efficient to learn.
It takes much longer to get the click when you're learning
something new with the language that you're
not used to. So
I wrote the first draft, the first version of
the Vue documentation in Chinese.
Later on, when we had a bigger community, community members
started to contribute more and more to these translations.
They started taking over the maintenance of the Chinese
docs and we're seeing a lot of contributions
to translate Vue docs into other languages as well.
So I think this good
internationalization, localization effort is
definitely critical in helping Vue's
adoption in these areas.
From my personal experience,
particularly in areas where English is not the first
language, you typically see that the
channel for local developers to keep up to
date with the latest information, to keep
up to date with the new things
happening in the front-end world
is they rely
on a few key community leaders who are proficient in
English to translate the content for them.
So it's a great effort by these community leaders, but they
are not obliged to do this.
And when there are not enough of them,
this creates a bottleneck for the content and
information to flow into - to reach
these developers in these areas.
So if, say, a framework
or a tooling or a community
that takes internationalization and localization as a first
class concern, it definitely will help a lot in
reaching these developers in a much
bigger scale.
That makes a ton of sense.
I've seen that on a few developer sites.
I remember one tried to add translations just through
machine translation and they noticed that a lot of the
developers were switching to English, thinking that it was
just that they were familiar with English and the like.
And then it was only when they went through a lot of it was
the community actually taking the time to build
a really high quality translations like you're talking
about. And then everyone kind of flipped back to that.
So that that makes a ton of sense.
Now, before we go, I happened to notice that you're a
karaoke fan, as am I.
And I just wanted to ask if you have a go-to song?
Yeah. Don't stop me now by Queen.
Nice. Nice. Yeah, mine is Sweet Child of Mine.
So now on that note, before we start singing, I'm already
getting ready to jump to the mic.
We'll have to have a karaoke session sometime.
But thank you so much for joining us, Evan.
Thanks for all that you do and all that the Vue community
does for the Web.
Thanks for having me.
Evan just spoke about his experimentation with a
bundle-free developer experience.
And on day one, we spoke about the work we've been doing to
understand bundlers with Tooling.Report.
Now, understanding what's going on in these bundles is
really important and is one area that we're looking to
explore in Lighthouse.
So please welcome Paul Irish to tell us more.
Thanks, Dion. So we have all spent a good amount of
time configuring our bundles and our
approach to bundling strategies.
But ultimately, there is a lack of transparency when it
comes to the JavaScript getting all bundled up and shipped
into production.
They're just these big files and it's easy for us to treat
them as black boxes.
And some of us on the Lighthouse team have worked on
community tools like Source Map Explorer,
Source Map Visualization to help us
understand what's happening inside of these files.
And we've long wanted to bring some of that inspection
into Lighthouse itself. So I want to show you a little
sneak peek of some upcoming Lighthouse features that
we hope are going to help a little bit.
The first one is a new audit called
'Remove Unused JavaScript'.
Now, this is actually in Lighthouse 6.0, and it is listing
all - by file -
the top JavaScript files that are unused and is giving you
an idea of what percentage of them - how many bytes of them
- are actually unused.
This is great, and it's actually just like what you see in
the coverage panel in Chrome DevTools.
But we can improve this. If we know a little bit more about
the actual JavaScript bundles, we can actually explore them
and see OK for each bundle file, what are all of the
original modules that were on disk source
files and understand how much of them
were unused and used?
And this really helps us understand a bit more
about the kind of code that is not actually being
run.
Another new audit that we're introducing is one that
identifies duplicate modules across JavaScript
bundles. So in this case, you actually see that lodash
is in two separate JavaScript bundles.
But we are really happy that this helps you
see exactly cases where
you probably could reconsider your chunking strategy
to make for something a little bit more optimized.
Another new audit is called 'Legacy JavaScript'.
What we're doing here is we're trying to find all the cases
where you're shipping JavaScript to production -
and specifically to modern browsers - where you're
including things like polyfills and you're compiling
down to a level
where the modern browsers don't really need them.
Modern browsers understand a lot of modern JavaScript, and
so we want to make sure that you're not over compiling.
Legacy JavaScript identifies polyfills and transforms
and tells you what exactly it found in each file so that
you can re-optimize your deployment strategy.
Got it, and is this all powered by source maps?
Yeah. Yeah, exactly.
Source maps are are super useful and they
enable this really powerful analysis.
And actually, if I can,
we're working on a interactive UI for
exploring this stuff in more detail.
And so I want to show this - these are early mocks -
but we wanted to
provide that kind of rich interactive tree
map experience inside the tool as
well. So this UI might look
a little familiar to you if you use some of these tools
before. But giving you a view of across
all your JavaScript files, and if there's a bundle and if
we can understand what's inside of it, we'll show it.
And you can explore that more detail.
We're really excited to provide
a bunch more information around here and augment it with
data around code coverage so that you can see
exactly what's happening at a table view
to help prioritize all of the major things you should be
paying attention to, and let you explore it in detail
so you can really find out what's happening and what you
could change.
So, again, it's early.
This will all change quite a bit.
But we're really excited about bringing this experience to
you.
It's all coming soon to a Lighthouse near you.
Got it. I'm always - I always love kind of opening
up some of the old bundles and seeing all of the mistakes
I've made in the past. I'm excited to play around with
this. Now, a few weeks ago, we also shipped
Lighthouse 6.0 and I bet that's the version where we
now started to include Core Web Vitals.
Is that right?
Yeah, that's right. All right. So Core Web Vitals, we got
these three metrics, Largest Contentful Paint, First Input
Delay,
and Cumulative Layout Shift, though it's worth pointing out
that FID, First Input Delay, is
a field metric.
And since Lighthouse is a lab tool, in
its place we have another metric TBT, total
blocking time. We like to think of this as FIDs
lab companion.
So they're not measuring exactly the same thing, but
they're all about interactivity, they're all about long
tasks on the main thread, and heavily influenced by them.
So it really works well.
So in Lighthouse 6.0, you'll see these three metrics up
top.
And if you're looking at it and your report looks like this
one, then you're like, wow, OK, well, these metrics
are - they're not great.
Looks like I can make some improvements here.
All right. But what's the next step?
We've added some new audits to
help point you in the right direction.
So I'll go right through them right now.
First one I'll show is this,
Avoid long main thread tasks.
So here we're just listing the longest tasks
on the main thread that you have, how long they took, and
what URL we can attribute them to.
And then two more. We have the largest contentful paint
element. The metric itself is telling
you at what time that paint happened, but that paint was
associated with a particular DOM element, and here, this
will just tell you. And similarly for cumulative layout
shift, you want to know what the actual shifts were?
Well, these were the DOM elements that shifted.
And these ones contributed most to your total
CLS value.
So you could just read this,
and so you'll see this content container.
OK, yeah, I know what that is. But then if you're looking
at these other two items and you're like, OK, but
which actual DOM element is this?
If you run Lighthouse through DevTools, we actually have
a nice little surprise for you. So there, we kind
of upgrade these element references.
So if you hover over them, we'll actually just
apply that element inspection hover tooltip
that you normally get in DevTools.
And if you click through, you'll see it in the DOM tree
elements panel.
So that's kind of integration to help you understand
exactly what thing you're looking at.
This is just a small slice of the new stuff in 6.0, please
check out our blog posts for all the rest of the fun stuff.
Got it. I'm always a sucker for these audits.
It's great to be able to kind of just go from the metrics
themselves in the scores and really go deeper to understand
what's affecting them. Thanks so much, Paul.
I love how we're making sure to open up as much data
as we can with the Chrome User Experience Report.
And I keep seeing great mashups and analysis from the
community, such as the Onely Map, which lets you
kind of zoom around the world and kind of explore the
performance characteristics for a different device types
and obviously different locations.
Now, Lighthouse is a great tool to help you audit your web
apps, and it helps you not only with just performance
of course, but really across the board.
And we want you to be free to create the highest quality
web apps that give you the biggest reach to users across
whatever device they're using.
Now to hear more about the latest in PWAs and advanced
capabilities, let's welcome Pete LePage.
Awesome. Thanks, Dion.
We believe that you should be able to build and deliver
any kind of app on the Web.
Web apps should be able to deliver the same kinds of
experiences with the same capabilities as
native apps.
Combining the installability and reliability of progressive
web apps with our capabilities project, we're
working to close the gap, and help you build
and deliver great experiences.
To do that, we've been focusing on three things.
First, we've been working hard to give you and
users more control over the install experience,
removing the mini infobar, adding an install promotion
to the omnibox, and more.
But one of my favorite things about the Web is how
ubiquitous it is.
We know that for some businesses, it's really important
to have your app in the store.
At Chrome Dev Summit we previewed a library and CLI
called Bubble Wrap, then called Llama-Pack.
It makes it trivial to get your PWA into the
Play Store. In fact PWAbuilder.com
now uses Bubble Wrap under the hood.
In just a few mouse clicks.
I can generate an APK that I can upload to the Play
Store. Second, we're providing tighter
integration with the operating system.
Like the ability to share a photo, song, or
whatever else by invoking the system-level
share service.
Or the other way around - being able to receive content
when shared from other installed apps.
You can keep users up to date or subtly
notify them of new activity with app badging.
And make it easy for users
to quickly start an action using app shortcuts which
will land in Chrome 84.
And finally, we're working to enable new capabilities
that enable new scenarios that weren't possible before.
Like editors that read and write files on the user's
local file system, or getting a list of locally
installed fonts so that users can use them in their design.
Of course, there's plenty more.
So stay tuned. But I hear, Dion, you've been
playing with the TikTok PWA.
That's right. That is my 10-year-old son, Josh, who started
to create some really fun TikTok content, even though
he was pretty restricted these days to the house and
the pets and the like.
And he kept bugging me to join in and play
myself.
And yeah, I was a little bit gun shy,
so to speak, on that side. But it actually gave me a great
excuse to play with a really well built PWA
that the TikTok Web team put together that I didn't even
know about. It Is really, really a nice, rich
experience there.
That's really cool.
And all of these things that we've been working on - things
like the app shortcuts - are gonna be a great
addition to them. The idea that you can push and hold
on the app icon and be able to quickly jump in and
create a new TikTok.
Or push and hold and say, hey, I want to see my friends
TikToks. Or the ability to be able to show app badges
when a friend has posted something new or something like
that. So there's plenty of great stuff coming that they
can take advantage of. And so can you.
That's excellent. Thanks again, Pete.
Thank you.
Now with that, it's time to close out the last opener.
It's been a great pleasure being with you over the last
three days, but we're not quite done yet.
We've got a great set of content coming up today.
Next, you're going to hear from Google engineers who hope
you improve the reliability of your experience with
advanced patterns for building PWAs.
Then, how you can get them into the Play Store, and how to
help you increase your conversion rate for notifications,
and so much more.
Now, if you're watching live, we'll be on the chat to
answer your questions at web.dev/live.
And, of course, on YouTube.
But the fun isn't going to end today.
Thanks to our amazing Google developer groups all across
the world, we've got a set of follow-up events in the weeks
to come. Where we'll have Googlers, Google developer
experts, as well as experts from across the local
communities joining you to share more insights and
guidance. Just check out the regional events section
on web.dev/live starting tomorrow to find
the event that's in your time zone.