Hi everyone. My name is Mathias and I’m
here to tell you what’s new in Puppeteer!
But before we can do that, we should
probably talk about what Puppeteer is in
the first place. Puppeteer is a browser
automation library for Node.js. It lets you
control a browser using a simple and
modern JavaScript API. After installing
it using `npm install puppeteer` you can
`require('puppeteer')` in your Node.js script
and start automating. The first step to
browser automation is… to launch an
actual browser and with Puppeteer, that’s
just one line of code. Next, we open a new
page. This is equivalent to opening a new
tab in your browser. Now let’s navigate
to a URL. This line of code ensures that
the page has finished loading before
continuing with the rest of the script.
Then we take a screenshot and save it to
a file before finally closing the
browser. And that’s it — that’s the entire
script! We did all of that with just a
few lines of code. And Puppeteer can do
much more: you can generate PDFs, evaluate
JavaScript in pages, enter text in input
fields, click on elements… Almost anything
you would manually do when using a
browser can be automated using Puppeteer.
The Puppeteer project is fully open source
and has received contributions from
individual contributors all around the
world as well as from companies like
Mozilla, Sauce Labs, and Microsoft. At
Google, the Puppeteer team consists of
Chrome engineers who also work on DevTools.
This might sound a little
strange at first, but it actually makes
sense, because Puppeteer is built on top
of the same underlying protocol that DevTools
also uses to communicate with the
Chromium back-end. Because of this,
Puppeteer also gives you access to
advanced browser functionality that is
usually only available through DevTools.
For example, you might know that DevTools
lets you emulate print media so that you
can easily debug print styles.
Well, Puppeteer lets you do the same
thing in an automated script. Here we
call `page.emulateMediaType` to force
print styles and then we save the result
as a PDF. Okay, now that you know what
Puppeteer is, what it can do, and who is
working on it, let’s take a look at some
recent feature additions. Similar to
emulating print styles, we recently added
DevTools support for emulating light and
dark mode as well as other so-called “CSS
media features”. We then shipped a new
Puppeteer API that lets you perform the
same emulation programmatically. This
Puppeteer script takes two screenshots
of your web app: one in light mode, and
one in dark mode. It works independently
of your operating system settings. One of
my favorite features on web.dev/live
is the schedule which adapts to your
local timezone. I live in Germany, so when
I view the schedule I see something like
this. Today’s event started at 2:00 PM
for me, but someone in Tokyo for example
would see a different time — for them the
event started at 9:00 PM. I love that
the website just tells me what I need to
know in my local time. Nobody likes doing
timezone math! To make it easier to
test this kind of timezone-aware
functionality, we added DevTools support
for emulating arbitrary time zones.
Yesterday’s event started on June 30th
at 6 PM for me, but for someone in
Tokyo it was already 1 AM on July 1st.
In addition to the new DevTools
functionality, we also added a new API to
Puppeteer to let you change time zones
programmatically. This script emulates
various time zones and then executes
some timezone-dependent JavaScript in the
page context. We’re logging the same date
but in two different time zones, and that
produces different output. Here’s another
example. This Puppeteer script forces the
Tokyo time zone, then loads the web.dev LIVE
page, and finally takes a screenshot
of just the schedule, similar to the
side-by-side screenshots we saw earlier.
DevTools recently gained support for
simulating the effect of various vision
deficiencies, including blurred vision
and color vision deficiencies.
This can help you identify accessibility
issues related to color, such as bad
contrast. And guess what? We added a
corresponding Puppeteer API that lets
you apply these simulations
programmatically! This script takes a
screenshot of the web app after
simulating blurred vision, achromatopsia
(or full color blindness), and deuteranopia
which is red-green color blindness.
One feature we’re still experimenting
with is the ability to register and use
custom selector query handlers. Many
Puppeteer APIs deal with selector
strings, which by default use querySelector
or querySelectorAll to find
elements in the page. We’ve heard from
users that they want to be able to
provide their own selector query
handlers with custom logic, and this new
feature now makes that possible. You can
imagine providing a custom `hasText`
handler which looks for DOM nodes
containing a string of text. Or maybe you
want to select elements across shadow
DOM boundaries, which querySelector
doesn’t let you do. There’s one more
feature I want to talk about, and it’s a
little different from all these API
additions we’ve been covering until now.
Let’s go back to our very first example:
launching a browser, navigating to a URL,
and taking a screenshot. Puppeteer was
originally built for Chrome so when you
call `puppeteer.launch` it launches a
Chromium browser by default. You can now
also specify this explicitly by using
the `product` option. Okay, so we added a
new `product` option… by itself that’s
probably not very interesting. But here
comes the exciting part! Instead of
Chrome you can now specify Firefox and
then use the same Puppeteer API to test
a real Firefox browser. By changing just
this one line we are now automating
Firefox instead of Chrome. Firefox
support for Puppeteer is the result of an
ongoing collaboration with Mozilla. Part
of this effort involves patching
Puppeteer itself, but a big chunk of the
work happens in the Firefox codebase. The
Puppeteer Firefox implementation is
still experimental and so not all the
Puppeteer APIs
are yet compatible with Firefox, but
Mozilla has been making great progress
here. In fact, as of mid-May, exactly 319
out of the 638
tests in Puppeteer’s test suite are
passing on Firefox —
that’s exactly 50%! We’re
hoping to ship Puppeteer with more
complete Firefox support soon.
Longer-term we would love to support
Safari as well, and we’re actively working
on making that happen in collaboration
with other browser vendors. We believe
the right way to get to a fully
cross-browser Puppeteer is by
standardizing a protocol that all
browsers can implement, instead of
building on top of the proprietary
Chrome DevTools Protocol. In addition to
all those new features, a lot of work has
been going on behind the scenes of
Puppeteer. We recently finished migrating
the code base to TypeScript, we
simplified our test runner, we
considerably improve the robustness of
our continuous integration setup, and our
documentation keeps getting better and
better. This work is often less user-
visible, but it’s crucially important
because it enables us to iterate more
quickly and more confidently. I hope you
enjoyed this overview of what’s new in