Hi, everyone.
This is Eiji. Today.
I'm going to talk about Web Payments.
Web Payments is the name of the W3C Working Group and a set
of standard APIs that brings dedicated payment
functionalities to the browsers for the first time in the
history of the web.
There are several specifications under Web Payments, but
the two most important ones are Payment Request API
and Payment Handler API.
The Payment Request API provides a standardized way to
invoke a browser-mediated low friction payment flow
on the web, similar to what users might already be
familiar with in many native apps.
The Payment Handler API allows payment apps to plug
into the Payment Request API to enable form-free
payments on the Web.
Here's how a web payment flow starts.
A website invokes a Payment Request API.
Customer's preferred payment app is launched inside a
special modal window.
The customer interacts with a payment app to confirm and
authorize the transaction.
The payment app returns a payment credential that can be
verified and processed.
There has been some confusion between Web Payments APIs,
and wallet-specific JavaScript APIs.
To clarify, Web Payments APIs are low-level web platform
primitives that are W3C standard proposals.
Digital wallets such as Google Pay provide
JavaScript APIs that can be built on top of
the Web Payments APIs.
Support for Web Payments APIs across browsers is
progressing slowly but steadily.
Today, outside of Chrome, limited support is available
in Safari, Samsung Internet, Edge,
Opera, and Brave.
Mozilla is working on adding support to Firefox
as well.
There are two ways an existing payment app can integrate
with Payment Request API.
The best option for a payment app with an existing
web-based flow is to implement the Payment Handler
API by adding a service worker to their
existing payment experience.
A payment app that is primarily a native app
can integrate with Chrome on Android using the Pay
intent.
It's been a few years since Web Payments was announced.
Some of you might be curious what's been going on in the
meantime.
The short answer is that we've been actively working on it.
Recently, our focus has moved from trying to figure out
how Payment Request API can be directly valuable to
merchants, to how the APIs can enable
better payment app experiences on the web.
Let me tell you a bit more about it.
We started by focusing on making the Payment Request API
directly valuable to the end merchants by including
a payment method called 'basic card,' which was designed
to give merchants a direct alternative to
form-based credit card payments.
With 'basic card,' customers can just select a credit card
stored in the browser to make payments.
We've learned that building a compelling payment flow
requires much more than just returning a credit card
number.
That's why we are switching gears to focus on enabling
payment apps through the Web Payments APIs.
This means freezing future development on Chrome's built-in
basic-card support for now except bug fixes, and
eventually deprecating the support for basic card.
Today, to complete a payment on the Web, a user often
has to fill a long form and follow multiple steps
through pop-ups and redirects.
Web Payments APIs enable a much more streamlined flow where
a user can complete all payment steps without leaving
the context of the checkout page.
For developers, building an equivalent payment flow
requires intricate cross-site coordination using
iframes, cookies, and postMessages.
Some of these mechanisms are being phased out by
browser vendors as they are also easily abused
by trackers that invade users' privacy.
The Web Payments APIs provide a consistent and robust
alternative for managing such coordinations, and we are
working hard to ensure compatibility with the evolving
Web Privacy landscape.
Until browser interoperatbility is improved, we recommend
that most merchants integrate with payment apps using
their recommended approach.
The payment apps will take care of leveraging the Web
Payments APIs where available and appropriate,
and gracefully falling back to alternatives elsewhere.
Now, what's new in the Web Payments?
Let me cover four exciting new functionalities today.
Skip-the-sheet is a UX optimization
that allows the user to skip directly to a payment
app if there is only one eligible choice.
This provides a more streamlined flow for payment apps
that are launched from branded buttons.
Delegation is a new feature in the Payment Handler API
that allows a payment app to provide all the information
requested by the merchant, including shipping and contact
information.
Previously, this information used to always come from the
browser.
This enhances the capability for a payment app to handle
the entirety of a payment flow.
Together, delegation and skip-the-sheet enable payment
apps to more easily transition their existing
flows to the Payment Handler API.
Another experimental feature that I'm excited about
is a Digital Goods API.
It is designed to be used together with the Payment Request
API to allow web apps to invoke billing
flows provided by native app stores to provide
in-app-purchase experiences that are difficult
to achieve on the web today.
For example, the Digital Goods API can be used
to enable payments for apps in the Play Store that
use Trusted Web Activities.
Last, but not least, we have made WebAuthn available in
the Payment Handler UI so that payment apps can use
a biometric sensor to let users sign-in or authorize
payments.
We also believe WebAuthn is a critical technology to
enable low-friction payment authorization on the
web and eventually replace today's browser
fingerprinting based solutions.
We are actively exploring a tighter integration
between WebAuthn and Web Payments.
In this video, we have looked back at what is Web Payments,
why has the focus shifted to payment apps, and what's
coming next.
If you're interested to learn more we have recently
published a new set of documents at web.dev/payments.
OK. That's everything today from our team.
I hope it's been helpful for all of you learning a bit
about cookies. COOP and COEP, DevTools.
User-Agent, Referer, sign-in, and
payments!
That's a lot and we will continue to share more with you.