[Music]
[Applause]
hey folks my name is addy osmani and
welcome to optimizing for core web
vitals so today we're going to talk
about optimizing user experiences on the
web with a case study on French luxury
fashion house Chloe Chloe we've recently
been taking a fresh look at web
performance and I'm really excited to
share their learnings with you now you
may have seen Google search announced an
upcoming search ranking change recently
that incorporates page experience
metrics now these metrics include the
core web vitals which together with a
few other signals paint a pretty
holistic picture about the quality of
user experiences on a page but what are
the core Web vitals and how do you go
about optimizing for them well or web
vitals are a set of metrics related to
speed responsiveness and visual
stability now these three aspects of
user experience are measured using three
metrics so first of all we have largest
content full paint which measures
loading performance next up we have
first input delay which measures
interactivity and last we've got
cumulative layout shift which measures
layout stability let's kick things off
by talking about cumulative layout shift
or CLS now CLS is a pretty important
metric for measuring visual stability
because it helps quantify all those
times when we see really surprising
shifts in the content on page it helps
make sure that the page is as delightful
as possible have you ever been reading
like an article online when all of a
sudden something suddenly changes on the
page and without warning the text moves
and you've lost your place
that's literally what happens a giant
chicken kicks your content away and he
has no regrets look at him he's
basically CLS so what causes poor CLS
well first of all we've got images
without dimension
adds embeds or iframes without
dimensions dynamically injected content
and web fonts that might cause a flash
of unstyled content now as I mentioned
Chloe is a French luxury fashion house
and it's become a bit of a go-to brand
not just for like luxury apparel but
also handbags and fragrances and things
like that and they have recently been
focused on improving cumulative layout
shift on all their like main pages so
their home page their product listings
page and their product details page
through a bunch of work they've been
able to reduce their CLS all the way
down to zero which is about as perfect
as you can get so how did they get here
this is the before view of the Cloe
homepage where we can observe a number
of surprising layout shifts due to
elements on the page not following CLS
best practices so let's dive into a few
tips that worked well here first off
always include width and height size
attributes on your images and video
elements alternatively you can always do
things like reserve the required space
with CSS aspect ratio boxes but in
general this approach just make sure
that the browser can allocate the
correct amount of space in the document
while the image is loading so here's a
demo of this in action these are some
images that don't have width and height
specified and what you see happening is
that they're pushing content in the page
all the way down this is something
that's reflected in our tools like
lighthouse and I've got a little bit of
a clip out here you can see the
lighthouse report where CLS is in the
red and not quite where we want it to be
so how do we address this well in the
early days of the web developers would
add width and height attributes all over
the place they'd add them to their image
tags they make sure that they kept
enough space allocated on the page
before browsers would start fetching
images that was great because it would
minimize reflow and relay out
now when responsive web design was
introduced developers began to omit
these width and height attributes and
they started to use CSS to resize their
images instead
one of the downsides to this approach is
that space could only be allocated for
an image once it began to download and
you know at that point the browser could
determine its dimensions as images load
in in that old world you know the page
would reflow was each image appears on
the screen and a lot of us got used to
you know our text suddenly popping down
the screen which wasn't a very great
user experience and this is where your
aspect ratio comes in so the aspect
ratio of an image is the ratio of its
width to its height it's pretty common
to see this expressed as two numbers
separated by a colon so for example 16
colon 9 or 4 colon 3 for an x colon y
aspect ratio the image is X units wide
and Y units hide what that means is that
if we know one of the dimensions the
other one can be determined so for a 16
to 9 aspect ratio if dress jpg has got a
360 PX height the width is 360
multiplied by 16 over 9 which gives us
640 PX
I'm not very good at math so hopefully
that was helpful
now modern browsers now set the default
aspect ratio of images based on an
images width and height attributes so
it's really valuable to set them if you
want to avoid those layout shifts this
is a change in modern browsers and it's
all thanks to the CSS working group
they've done some work that basically
allows us to just set width and height
as normal and this calculates an aspect
ratio based on the width and height the
attributes before the image is loaded so
what we're seeing on screen here this is
something that's added to the default
style sheet of all browsers and it
calculates aspect ratio based on the
elements width and height attributes so
as long as you're providing width and
height the aspect ratio can be
calculated and everything will will
hopefully avoid layout shifts so this is
a great best practice to be following
this is also something that works well
with responsive images so with
set your generally defining images that
you want to allow the browser to select
between you need to find sizes for those
images to make sure that your image
width and height attributes can be set
just make sure that each image is using
the same aspect ratio and here's that
demo once again width width and height
attributes added notice that in a modern
browser you won't see any layout shifts
there and the user will get a much more
pleasant experience
so another reminder set those width and
height attributes as much as you can
here's the impact that this change has
on lighthouse as we can see before we
went from a CLS of 0.36 so we're in the
red all the way back to something that's
a little bit better there one or two
other things in this page that could
have been improved but on the whole
we've had a relatively significant
impact on reducing layout shift you
might be wondering how can I figure out
what elements on my page are
contributing to CLS
we've got you covered so in lighthouse
we have an avoid large layout shifts
audit that highlights the top Dom
elements contributing most of the CLS to
the page so check out that audit in dev
tools we also have a good story here so
if you're using the dev tools
performance panel it has an experience
section that can help you detect
unexpected layout shifts super helpful
for finding and fixing visual
instability issues they highlighted in
this experience section with some kind
of reddish pinkish layout shift records
and if you click on one of those records
we'll be able to get more details about
you know what was the score where did
this element move to and from really
great diagnostics to help you nail down
how to fix your CLS so khloe's approach
to image loading is that they use a
skeleton pattern with a SAS CSS mixin
called bruschetta
loading bruschetta is one of those
things that are a little bit of a luxury
term ager in quarantine they're they're
right up there with toilet paper and
antibacterial soap but let's stick with
bruschetta loading so this is Chloe's
approach to image loading they have a
parent container with a color similar to
the final image that's being loaded now
lo that Lisa
strategies like this where you have a
little bit of a preview of what's
finally gonna be shown are sometimes
referred to as low quality image
placeholders you can use a you know a
predominant color from the final image
you can use a low resolution image
sometimes people will use like a 1 pixel
by 1 pixel image or something like 10
pixels by 10 pixel something very low
resolution that just gives you a preview
of what's finally going to be displayed
now lazy loading strategies like this
which either use a color or that kind of
placeholder they don't strictly improve
largest content full paint but they do
improve perceived performance so they
can still be pretty good for the user
experience now
what Chloe did here in addition to using
this skeleton loading approach was that
they do use responsive images and they
do make sure that they're setting
dimensions on their images as well to
avoid CLS let's shift up and things up
chef things up let's go on to the next
tip so reserve enough space for any of
your dynamic content things like ads or
promos ideally you want to make sure
that you were giving any of that content
a container that it's not going to just
you know bounce out of and suddenly
cause shifts in the page a related tip
to this one is avoid inserting new
content above existing content unless
it's in reaction to a user interaction
you want to make sure that any layout
shifts in your page are ones that you
are making a conscious decision around
and like occur as as expected so let's
try to visualize this here's an example
of a promo where we're dynamically
injected into the page
we haven't reserved space and it's just
pushed everything all the way down we
can see this reflected in our lighthouse
call-out at the bottom of the screen now
this is something that very typically
happens with ads Ifrah iframes
promos and these types of assets can
sometimes be the largest contributors to
layout shifts on the web now many ad
networks and publishers will often
support dynamic ad sizes and ad sizes
that are you know dynamic or something
that can sometimes increase
in you because you're giving people a
lot of flexibility around you know what
can go inside there your ad slots but it
can also be something that can
potentially negatively impact the user
experience by pushing things down so
that's something that you want to avoid
so how do we approach this well one
solution to the problem is statically
reserving space for the slot so you can
make sure that you're defining a
container for these ads or embed frames
so that regardless of what goes inside
you're not shifting the content of the
page around so here I've got a container
where I set my width and my height I've
set a background color but I've also set
it to overflow:hidden just in case
anything dynamic is a little bit you
know a little bit taller than the
container I don't I still don't want it
to be able to break out of it
ideally the content fits inside of our
container like our iframes or whatever
else we might inject in there and what
you can do if you're in the you know if
you're somebody that has lots of dynamic
content that gets injected into your
page you can take a look at your your
data look at what are the medians or the
95th percentile widths and Heights for
this dynamic content and size your
container accordingly that'll just mean
that you have the best chance at still
being able to present that content users
without negatively impacting the rest of
the user experience so here's what it
looks with with my pattern in place a
reserved enough space and that content
pops in but there are no layout shifts
in the page so I'm really happy about
that slightly better is my baseline for
everything in life at the moment so yeah
this is the lighthouse 6 dotto impact we
can see that we reduced our layout
shifts from zero point two four all the
way down to about zero I'm gonna give
myself about zero it's in the green so
that's great so let's talk about a
production example of something like
this on Chloe so Chloe had a promotion
banner for shipping at the top of their
product listings page and you'll see
this like free standard shipping
promotion listed the very top but this
wasn't always there there was a time
when this product listings page
a CLS of 0.4 which is like really not
great because of two things the first
was the way they approached their
dynamic promo banner and the way that
they approached filters let's talk about
the banner first now this banner used to
be positioned in line underneath the
main page header and as you can see here
it looks it looks kind of harmless but
what's the impact of having a
dynamically sized banner on the user
experience well we have a video here
let's take a look as we can see here
once the content is fetched and rendered
for this banner it pushes the content
for the rest of the page all the way
down and that's not very ideal so how
did Chloe go about fixing this well they
reserved space for this banner the
content for this banner was also coming
from a client-side request
therefore messages were causing a pretty
visual layout shift occurring a few
seconds into page load now they moved
this API call Street to the server and
they made sure to reserve enough space
for the banner with a simple height
setting as a part of this work they
moved the position of the banner up a
little bit but altogether like moving
more work to the server always a good
idea and just making sure that they're
reserving space these things made a bit
of a difference so here's here's the
after view here we can see the impact to
their product listings pages after these
pages after the changes have been made
it's uh it's a lot less shifty some I'm
happy about that
so we talked about their promo banner
the other big CLS issue for product
listing pages was that Chloe had a
filters widget for filtering products
now this would rehydrate to become
dynamic once it booted up and so on the
client it was pending xha our calls for
data was waiting on session state based
on filter choices in order to be able to
like finally render this thing on the
screen so this is what this basically
looked like we wait for kind of contest
to be sent down for the filter widget we
wait for Hydra
it would still push content on the
screen all the way down now what they
ended up doing here was that they
adapted this widget to contain more of
the information needed to render the
filter widget server-side
they'd rendered it with better defaults
this helped avoid those layout shifts
and I just wanted to give a call out
here to the right of the screen we can
see the web vitals Chrome extension this
gives you a real-time view of all of
your vitals metrics and can just be
helpful as you were building your site's
locally or you're just browsing the web
and want to get a sense for the
performance of different sites that you
you check out on the regular and here's
what things look like after their
rehydration fix for filters as you can
see CLS reduced by a decent amount
looking at the before and after and it
was just another case of like pay
attention to the little things in your
pages that might be in aggregate causing
lots of things to be pushed down every
little CLS fix helps and here's the
overall impact of these changes on
desktop we can see that the above the
full content is relatively stable and
offers a much better user experience on
the whole and this is also reflected in
lighthouse work on my house got to give
got a give lighthouse shut up as we can
see here cumulative layout shift is in
the green we've hit zero so it's in a
really solid place so to improve CLS
Chloe acted on a number of different
elements it wasn't just one thing they
reserved space for the promo content in
terms of its ratio they made sure to set
width and height dimensions on their
images and they adopted a skeleton
pattern with improved perceived
performance they reserved space for
their promo banners requests before
receiving messages and they also
reserved space for the filters dynamic
component as well as making a few other
optimizations to just help with
rendering so on the whole it was it was
definitely worth it alright so I have a
big surprise for you
we've got more metrics to talk about put
a lot of work into this light
historically it's been a bit of a
challenge for web
developers to measure just how quickly
the main content of the webpage loads
and is visible to users thankfully we
now have metrics like largest content
full paint that are able to report the
render time of the largest content
element that's visible within the
viewport now you might be wondering what
causes a poor LCP well there are there
are lots of things slow server response
times or a big one this could be your
back-end infrastructure it could be
unoptimized database queries API
responses that are just taking a while
to resolve it could be render blocking
JavaScript and CSS slow resource times
are another big one you could have an
optimized images slowing down your LCP
and then there's client-side rendering
there's a whole class of problems where
those of us who love working in
JavaScript and using modern libraries
and frameworks and bumblers can
sometimes get into a place where we have
our requests for assets like images in
particular hero images behind JavaScript
fetches so the browser first of all has
to fetch your JavaScript then it has to
parse and process that JavaScript to
fetch your image and that whole process
can take so long that you delay showing
meaningful content to your user so it's
just things like that you should keep an
eye on there are plenty of tools that
can help diagnose these issues so let's
take a look at a at some real-world
production challenges around LCP and how
to work around them
Chloe started off with an L CP of about
10 or 11 seconds in this view here we
can see that their primary hero image
content wasn't wasn't getting fetched
and rendered until about 11 seconds in
to our trace their home page suffers
from in this case it suffered from a few
different things it had heavy
full-screen image downloads poorly
optimized images some images that were
requested late in the network chain and
these are very common issues there's
nothing here that's just like that
they're doing crazy wrong it's just very
common issues and it's useful to be
aware of some of the things that impacts
LCP so things that impact LCP are image
elements image elements the
be inside of an SVG element video
elements block level elements containing
text nodes and so let's let's talk about
images first because they're there
they're pretty often a cause for poor
LCP so for many sites images are the
largest element in view when the page is
finished loading especially as UX
patterns have shifted towards us using
more hero images in our pages so it's
very very important to optimize our
images especially anything that's
visible within the initial viewport now
there are a few techniques that you can
use here you can consider not having you
know an image in the first place if it's
if it's not that relevant maybe you
remove it compress those images use you
know love letters are plenty of image
optimization tools out there compress
your images maybe consider converting
them to more efficient modern formats
use responsive images and you can also
consider using an image CDN I'm seeing
an increasing number of sites leveraging
image CDNs just to help them get control
over a ability to just tweak parameters
in a URL for an image and change what
format gets served down or what quality
you have and it's just using an image
CDN can be a really good way of staying
on top of modern best practices because
even even us like that are you know web
pursues iasts sometimes I have a hard
time staying on top of all everything
happening in the image optimization
world now you might be wondering how can
I identify the element that is my like
LCP thankfully we've got some solutions
here in dev tools in the performance
panel if you record a trace and you go
to timings you should find a record for
LCP click on that record and you'll get
the summary pane showing up that
includes things like the size of the
image and more importantly the related
note so if you hover over that related
node it will highlight what in your page
was considered LCP I personally find
this really valuable as kind of a
stepping stone to where
I'd be spending my time optimizing so
check that out if you use the
performance panel this is also something
that we try to capture in lighthouse so
lighthouse has got a largest content
full paint element audit and we try to
highlight what element was responsible
here too so if you use lighthouse check
that out so back to Chloe
so Chloe discovered that they were
delivering very high resolution images
even to even very high resolution for
retina screens because there is a bit of
a cutoff point where if you're serving
kind of two by three by images the human
eye is is not going to be able to
perceive large amounts of difference
there and there are kind of you know you
have diminishing values that you get out
of just serving very very very high
resolution images now in this case we're
in Ren dev tools were in the elements
panel we're looking at a specific image
and what we see is that the maximum
width of image is being served down is
1920 pixels it's pretty it's pretty
large so one of the things that Co we
actually decided to do was change things
up here they resized their images to not
be more than two times the image
viewport size so they removed source of
sizes over 828 width to keep an image
maximum size that they were comfortable
with and that actually ended up being
pretty fine on retina devices as well so
is this nice trade-off of how do we
deliver rich imagery without negatively
impacting the user experience now by
doing this work on an iPhone X or a
pixel to excel that was previously
seeing any were up to 245 kilobytes
worth an image bytes being downloaded
they were able to reduce it down to 125
that's that's huge that's like a 51
percent decrease in image bytes being
served down with no noticeable
difference so optimize your images
people the next thing we're going to
talk about is some of the other image
optimizations that they performed so on
the product listings page Chloe
use image lazy loading which
you know it's a relatively popular
pattern what they discovered was that
there were four primary images being
loaded above the fold however there was
one off-screen image that seemed to be
tripping up their lazy loading
heuristics and was still being fetched
now this particular image happened to be
248 kilobytes in size about 200 plus
kilobytes in size and this was this was
negatively impacting the user experience
so they wanted to try improving this now
on the whole there were a number of
things Chloe did they were able to bring
down their above-the-fold image download
size all the way to 14 and a half
kilobytes they were able able to tune
their lazy loading heuristics so that
off-screen images like the one I was
just talking about were no longer a
problem
they adopted an image CDN they adopted
wet pee by defaults improved their image
resizing strategy and the results of
this outside of just having a nice like
lighthouse report with lots of greens is
that each product page now weighs 57%
less than it did before which is a
really nice outcome to have as a result
of like optimizing your images taking a
step back here's what the homepage LCP
look like after these changes we can see
that again previously those hero images
were not rendering in a total about 11
seconds in now LCP happens at about 4
seconds into the process and it's
complete just a few seconds later the
request time for our LCP related note
for kind of our hero images is about 1.3
seconds in so on the whole this is this
is really great there's still work they
could do here but on the whole this is
like fantastic to see so let's switch
things up to our next tip defer any
non-critical JavaScript and CSS to speed
up loading the main content of your page
now this is guidance that is it's not
new it's been around for a few years but
for anyone that's not familiar with this
guidance I'll give you a very quick
recap of it now before a browser can
render any content it needs to parse
HTML markup into a Dom tree the
Arthur needs to pause if it encounters
any external stylesheets your
synchronous script and scripts and
stylesheets can both you know render
bbbb render blocking resources which can
delay your first content full paint
consequently your largest content will
paint as well and so what we tell people
to do is defer any of your non-critical
scripts and stylesheets the speed upload
so let's take a look once again at the
product listings page for Chloe as we
can see this is a trace independent of
their image optimizations and as we can
see here light house highlights that
there are a few render blocking style
sheets that are delaying early paints on
the product listings page now this is
this is kind of manifested in terms of
like just how much white we're seeing in
our film strip so one approach to
addressing this problem is by inlining
your critical CSS and deferring the load
of non-critical styles we often call
this technique critical CSS so critical
CSS is all about extracting CSS for
above-the-fold content
ideally across a number of different
breakpoints and making sure that you can
render the above-the-fold content as
quickly as possible in the first few our
TTS
and deferring the load of the rest of
your style sheets for the page you know
for things below the fold as soon as
possible otherwise so how did Chloe do
this well they built some tooling they
implemented critical CSS in their sass
build process and they constructed a
syntax allowing their developers to
specify for each widget what part of the
CSS code goes into their critical CSS
this is highlighted using the critical
keywords you see on the screen right now
now at Build time they're able to build
both the critical CSS and the
non-critical CSS so that every single
build is consistent with both there are
many ways that you can approach critical
CSS I've contributed to some tooling on
this topic in the past and you can you
can automate it you can go very custom I
see some teams that will just have a
critical dot CSS file
that they manually curate and regardless
of the the approach that you take what's
key is just making sure that you're
delivering important content to the user
as quickly as possible so we talked
about the need for you know loading in
the other style sheets for the page will
quit what Chloe do is their non-critical
CSS style sheets are stored in an array
so they point to references to them on
their servers and that's injected with a
deferred script so that it's hopefully
not render blocking but it's still
loaded with a relatively high priority
that isn't going to interfere with the
HTML parser so what was the impact of
optimizing their critical CSS Leanne the
answer is pretty large they were able to
bring down their first content full
paint from 2.1 seconds to about 1.1 and
their LCP from 2.9 seconds to about 1.5
now this is this is really great work
optimizing your critical CSS can be a
bit of a time investment but is
something that can just make sure that
your page is getting styled as soon as
possible so let's talk about another tip
I mentioned slow server response times
when we were discussing like what what
impacts LCP now the longer that it takes
a browser to receive content from the
server the longer that it takes to
render anything on the screen
the faster server it can respond that
that's going to improve every single
page load metric including LCP so you
might be wondering how can I tell if I
have a slow server response time
lighthouse has you covered in lighthouse
we have an audit called reduce initial
server response time and if you if you
see this it's a good hint to spend more
time diagnosing the problem and causes
of the problem as I mentioned earlier it
can be plenty of things on your back-end
and we're trying to optimize our server
response times there's plenty that we
can do in terms of optimizing you know
our DNS our pre connects all of those
types of things but there are also
things that we can do to optimize
loading priority this is where
techniques like
well preload and serverpush can come
into play now if you're new to server
push I'll give you a quick summary of it
to improve latency hb2 introduced this
idea server push which basically allows
a server to push resources to the
browser before they're explicitly
requested now you and I as developers we
can as well as anyone else watching
you're all awesome too we often know
what the most important resources are on
a page and so we can start pushing those
as soon as you know things respond with
the initial requests this allows the
server to fully utilize was otherwise an
idle network to improve page load times
now server push is is not without its
it's nuanced this is one of those
optimizations where you need to be
careful it's possible to over push so
server push is not HTTP cache aware so I
could push something for a particular
page the user could come back to another
related page and the server would push
those exact same resources again the way
to avoid that is by either using cookies
or a serviceworker to avoid those those
refetch is for those types of resources
and track what's in the cache but it
does involve a little bit more work in
general server pushes an optimization
that can have a big impact but just just
be aware of some of that nuance it's not
quite as simple as just like turning it
on sometimes now Chloe use automatic
server push which is an implementation
provided by Akamai it uses data to
decide you know when to push critical
CSS fonts and script and if you're
manually using server push yourself you
might end up looking at syntax that
looks a little bit like this what we see
here is the link HTTP header this is
actually the preload resource hint in
action and it's a separate but distinct
optimization from server push but in
reality most hb2 implementations will
push an asset
specified in a link header containing a
preload resource hint so you can use the
syntax in order to enable server pushes
for for a page so what was the impact of
this optimization without server push
Chloe you're finding in their lab tests
that LCP was closer to four seconds but
with it it was closer to 2.5 seconds
which is like a huge amount of impact on
screen at the moment we've been
verifying that using lighthouse but you
can also tell if individual requests in
you know we're server pushed using
things like dev tools and using things
like webpage tests Network waterfall
view both are very very handy now we're
on to our very last metric right Chloe
didn't optimize her forced input delay
but I did want to very quickly cover it
now first input delay measures the time
from when a user first interacts with a
page so that moment when they start to
click on a button or or tap some UI some
JavaScript powered control so the time
that the browser is actually able to
respond to that interaction now there
are many things that cause a poor first
input delay there can be long tasks on
the main thread heavy JavaScript
execution large JavaScript bundles can
delay how soon script can be processed
by the browser and it can have an impact
here and then you have things like
render blocking script now in general I
would strongly recommend using
lighthouse and using dev tools because
they do try to point out areas where you
might have long tasks or heavy script
execution very often the solution is to
just break up this work serve what the
user needs when they need it and try to
look at opportunities for you know
minimizing main thread work as much as
possible sometimes people will
contextualize this in terms of you know
maybe shift some of that work some of
the logic work to a web worker but
regardless of the path you want to take
there the the end goal is essentially
just making sure that the main thread
isn't busy and that you
interactions are not delayed so we're
almost at the end of our journey with
Chloe here we can take a look at Chloe's
overall web vitals in the lab thanks to
their investments in performance and
user experience they were able to reduce
their cumulative layout shifts down to
zero and their LCP by almost half this
is like this is mind-blowing li awesome
this is like really really cool as
you've seen all of this work is kind of
the culmination of a number of smaller
optimizations that when added up
actually make a pretty significant
impact to your end user experience and
we don't have to just look at data in
the lab we can look at the field as well
here is chrome user experience report
data for Chloe and as we can see our
core web vitals metrics for LCP and CLS
are trending in the right direction
CLS went from 0.85 down to zero in the
latest data set and this is all like on
the whole it's tremendous work it's
really great to see and I know that
Chloe are happy to continue building on
this work in the future as well now if
you're interested in building dashboards
like this for your own team measuring
the core web vitals you might be
interested in checking out the chrome
user experience report dashboard this is
a great solution that just allows you to
drop in a URL and very quickly get
access to field data and distributions
for the different core Web vitals
it also summarizes the metrics so if
you're trying to share around this
report with other people on your team
they'll hopefully be able to also get
some familiarity with the core web
vitals - we also recently shipped a new
chrome user experience report API crux
API this is great for programmatically
being able to build out your own
dashboards very similar to what we were
just taking a look at so check that out
too and that's it I hope that you found
this talk useful go and optimize your
web vitals there are plenty of Doc's
over on web dev that cover the
methodology the tools as well as the
best practices that you can use to get
fast and stay fast
my name is addy osmani I hope this has
been useful thank you
[Music]
[Applause]