[Music]
[Applause]
hey there I'm Ben Morse I'm a developer
advocate working on the web and on amps
and I'm crystal Lambert technically a
writer working for the web on the ant
project we're here to talk about
something we think it's pretty cool
a new way to run javascript in web
workers with amp awesome let's get
started but then what is this slide
JavaScript foe I love JavaScript it lets
me do whatever I want
sure javascript is amazing Ismay the
modern web possible but we both know
that many websites are too slow and
that's partially caused by lots of
JavaScript this one of the reasons like
people like this are staring at their
phones waiting for our sites to load
yeah that's no good
you think the more JavaScript the better
I could write more code to make things
quicker well it's like too much ice
cream or time spent at home you don't
want to overdo it well what about these
web workers I hear you can use them to
get JavaScript off the main thread but
I'm not sure how to get started yeah it
can be pretty intimidating because the
and another thing amp doesn't let me
write my own JavaScript period huh
can we make a video about that - well
conveniently crystal this video can be
about both those things because Anthony
provides an easy way to use workers so
we're going to show JavaScript
developers how amp makes it easy to try
web workers and people are already using
apt I'll show how you can write your own
JavaScript without breaking apps
performance guarantees for everyone is a
nice way to run JavaScript
anyway it's unlikely to harm your web
vital scores oh yeah I'm hearing lots
about this Web vitals that's uh our page
is first input delay largest content
full pay and cumulative layout shift
right those are the three so let's get
going
another slide what is this a guy
knitting yeah it's a transition slide
well it does remind me why is the web
single threaded
I mean every modern OS has multiple
threads why hasn't the web caught it
honestly it's just how browsers and
JavaScript have always been I mean of
course modern browsers can multitask
they can't be more than one thing at a
time
but each browser to have as a single
thread for the UI only one process can
make changes to the screen at a time
that means JavaScript can block the
browser from doing things and vice versa
but wait
javascript is asynchronous right so
whenever an event gets fired doesn't the
event handlers code start running right
away well sure but all the code in a web
page still runs in a single thread this
diagram illustrates JavaScript event
loop so the browser fires an event you
have an event handler that code runs
until it's done as other events fire
they get added to a queue mmm I see so
if my code is handling one event and
another event fires the browser just
can't spin up another thread instead it
has to wait for that event in the queue
right it has to wait until the current
code is done let's say the user taps a
button while your code is running a long
task well a JavaScript can't handle it
any other event until your task
completes so the next bit of code will
be delayed we're still the browser may
be unable to change the UI because it's
waiting for your code I guess if it
weren't that way everything would just
be fighting for control over the dom and
you'd have race conditions and general
cam oh yeah and unfortunately to make
JavaScript thread safe we'd have to
completely rewrite it all right this is
making some sense not only can excessive
JavaScript make your page slow to load
it can also make the page slow to
respond to users interactions I'm
guessing this is where web workers
coming yes javascript in a web worker
runs in a different thread and this is
not a new idea where brokers have been
around for about 10 years okay 10 years
that's longer than I've been working on
the web why am I just learning about
them I think because they're limited
made them harder to use workers can't
cause race conditions with other workers
or the main thread because they lack ax
padam or the global scope instead
auricular communicates with the main
thread by passing messages back and
forth each message contains an object
there are light rays that make this
simpler notably calm linked by Surma and
worker eyes by Jason Miller but workers
can't access the Dom so workers are
great for doing long tasks off the main
thread but what if you want access to
the Dom that's a big obstacle and that's
where I am script comes to the rescue
I knew at some point we were gonna bring
amp into this we did so in 2018 the amp
project released an open source library
called worker Dom worker Dom makes a
copy of the Dom for the workers use
worker Dom also recreates a subset of
the standard Dom API this lets the
worker manipulate the DOM and make
changes on the page using standard
techniques worker Dom keeps the copy of
the DOM and the real Dom in sync so
something changes in the real Dom worker
Dom sends a message to the worker to
make that change and the copy and if
your record changes its copy worker Dom
sends a message over to the real DOM and
the same change gets made there
so I heard you say amp is all this only
true for amp or can I use worker dawn
with a different stack you can import
worker Dhamma to your own project but
worker Dom is super useful for amp since
it provides a way to run JavaScript in a
sandbox where it can't run rampant and
break amps performance guarantees and
encapsulate swagger Dom in a component
called amp script this is a little
abstract can you show me some code code
I understand ok fine let's make a basic
hello world example with Apps Script in
the body we inserted an amp script
components the Dhamma contains gets
passed to the worker so here to the
worker that entire DOM is that h1 tag
next we put our code in a script tag
whoa that's weird
you set the type to plain text instead
of text JavaScript yeah we did that's
what the browser won't see it as
JavaScript and just executed immediately
instead an script finds the coda puts
into a worker so the code in this script
grabs the first h1 tag in the DOM and
appends a comma and the word world
right on page load and does that work
look magic that was pretty quick let's
watch it again I'm overwhelmed well okay
it's not Gmail but that world was really
and truly added by a web worker can you
prove it
if we open dev tools and go to the
sources tab and click over here we can
see our script right under the code
added by M script okay that's kind of
cool here's how that looks in a full web
page I have looked some things out for
simplicity's sake but you can see that
as with all amp pages were loading amps
runtime scripts we're also including the
JavaScript that makes the Emma scripts
work so do you always have to include
your JavaScript in line like that it's
not really a best practice yeah that's a
good point we can also store the
JavaScript in his own file by using am
scripts source attribute like this so
that example works but it's not really
that useful could we say add that world
when the user presses a button okay fine
let's add your HTML a button that says
hello who will write JavaScript that
grabs that button and adds a handler for
the click event when you click the
button it works its magic let's try it
out so there's hello there's our button
and look hello world okay let's go a
little crazy super neato what else can
we do
does am script let us do a fetch does it
ever hears that hello world example
modified to retrieve the word world from
an endpoint workers natively support
fetch XML HTTP requests and even
WebSockets
okay this is getting pretty cool but
this is amp right
how does amp just let me write any
JavaScript I want well that's a good
point
amp tries hard to guarantee you low
cumulative layout shift to keep page
elements from moving around if your code
makes mutations to the page that would
really disturb the page layout and
preserves the right to disallow those
changes or even shut the worker down if
you're on script container can't change
it can't disturb the page as much and
that gives you more freedom that's why I
specified the height and width here in
the HTML and why I didn't choose amps
container layout there's a lot to this
so check the documentation on amp dough
for details hold on can I just use amp
script to inject more scripts into the
DOM nope you're working with virtual Dom
not gonna work
fair enough but I see something about
not allowing more than a hundred and
fifty kilobytes of JavaScript is that on
a page level that's right 150 K is per
page but I could still fit jQuery into
that and up I can just copy in my
favorite image slider and charter
libraries well remember the word Kadam
is recreated um API that supports in its
own JavaScript if we're Kodama supported
the whole Dom API it would be cumbersome
and huge it would slow down pages
enormous ly it's a pretty few
third-party libraries are going to work
right out of the box okay and what's the
best way to use Apps Script well one way
is to use vanilla JavaScript while
keeping an eye on this table of
supported api's there is quite a bit
there
wait react can I use react yes that's
the other way react uses a very specific
subset of the Dom API so the worker Dom
teammates sure that subset is well
supported okay but I've used react
before my react bundle might need to
break that hundred and fifty kilobyte
limit yeah that's why it's probably
better to use pre act instead pre act as
highly compatible with react but it's
only three K minified in gzipped for
projects with more code pre actives
probably the way to go here I've made
the button example using pre act I find
it easier to write the debug the JSX in
a simpler environment and then build it
into my amp page so let's build this
let's start up our server and there's
our page with our button it works
alright that was a lot if only there was
an ant script tutorial out there wait a
minute didn't you and I already make one
of those yeah you want to take the next
slide of course that tutorial is a great
introduction to amp script
head on over to go ant dev slash learned
- script to get started and then keep on
going remember that what Kadam is still
quite new if you have feature requests
or find things that are missing please
get involved on github help improve it
in conclusion web workers can help you
keep JavaScript from slowing down your
web pages amp script is a nice way to
try this technique out you can find all
the code from this talk here on glitch
thanks for listening and let's get to
work on putting workers to work for you
[Music]
[Applause]