[Music]
[Applause]
hi everybody I'm Paul Lewis and I'm
Philip Walton okay so we thought today
what we do is we would talk about the
core web vitals inside of dev tools now
I know about the dev tools side in fact
I implemented some of the core word
vitals in side of dev tools but Phil
you're more of the person that knows
about the actual metrics where they came
from and that kind of stuff right that's
right I know a lot about the metrics I
work on the chrome team working with
some of the people that were helping to
define the metrics and standardized them
in browsers but I don't really know much
about how they work in dev tools so Paul
you're a great person for me to talk to
here let's let's dive in and see what we
can what we can find out okay so I guess
I plan may still have a bit of a
conversation to go back and forth we'll
be diving in and our dev tools having a
bit of a discussion about these metrics
and just trying to kind of explore
understand and share what's kind of
going on there so I guess the first one
that I was kind of thinking about when
we were discussing this was LCP and FCP
so there guess the first thing to kind
of talk about is what are what are they
like where do they come from you know
these are both paint metrics so FCP is
first content for paint it's tan it
represents the first point in time that
the browser is able to paint any content
on the screen and LCP is largest
contentful paint and that represents the
largest single text node or image
element on the page and the idea between
these two is that FCP represents like
the first time the user sees something
and an LCP represents when you know the
main contents of the page has painted I
mean in general whatever the largest
thing on the largest image or text node
on the screen is generally the thing
that the user is going to notice and so
that kind of represents once the page is
really loaded so I guess for a lot of
people then the first thing they're
gonna think of certainly for the largest
content for paint will be something like
a hero element or something
yeah they can a big image at the top of
the page for example absolutely okay
right but it's not always that I'm
guessing because you could be deep
linking into some content like further
down the page and everything else yeah
that's up so I okay I tell you what
we'll do then let's take it I've got a
page here actually I've got this page on
web dev we perform it to tab open inside
of dev tools and I guess the the goal
here is going to be to show FCP and LCP
in context and I have web dev open here
on a page in the performance section
around using image Sirians to optimize
images so if you've not seen this
content definitely worth a look it's a
great art okay and we have yeah we have
I'm DCI can deep link into this section
right with the right and so this I guess
would become our hero image right and an
interesting point to make here is that
the hero image is not necessarily going
to be above the fold like in this case
you're loading a page
halfway down have we scroll down the
page and so LCP is always you know it's
only going to consider elements that are
actually visible to the user on the
screen right great points so this is
what's going to make this brilliant but
interesting so what I'm going to do is
I'm actually gonna going to go to fast
three G so in the performance tab you
can open the capture settings here I'm
going to change just online oh it's a
fast 3d so we're just going to switch to
a slow down on the performance you see
this little exclamation mark shows up
saying Network throttling throttling is
enabled and I'm gonna I'm gonna slow
down the CPU just a little bit and you
doing this just so that we can see
things you're doing this to simulate
maybe a lower powered device or
something like that correct yeah yeah I
am but right now as well what I wanted
to do is if I take a recording with
things just slow down a little bit it
might be easier to just to see what's
going on because I happen to be
somewhere in my house is actually a
really good internet connection so I
don't particularly see network latency
quite as much as you would in other
cases say you know if you're on a mobile
device out and
so I just thought let's just try this
and see what happens so I'm gonna hit
record I'm gonna hit command shift are
to do a reload okay and I'm gonna stop
and we can discuss what we see okay let
me just wrap this up here now the first
thing to notice I suppose would be the
timings row here to have to remind
ourselves what these are Dom content
loaded this has been around forever
hasn't it yeah but there is first paint
first content for paint first meaningful
paint which we could talk about a little
bit I suppose largest content for
painting you can see this actually
highlighted our screenshot here and then
the load event now I can use the keys on
the keyboard to come into a little bit
closer zoom in a little bit on this
particular area of interest and you see
here I suppose the first content for
paint is presumably happening and then
the largest content for paint is
happening slightly later that's right
now I think we can get a little bit more
info about this because first content
for paint is happening and then the
largest content for paper which implies
to me that the image is coming in after
the initial page content so we're
drawing something we're painting
something and then we're painting the
image after the fact so let's just even
do that with screenshots on mm-hm and we
will record again and see what we get
okay I'll stop there and hopefully I
just leave this a little bit and we
might see
okay so roundabout fact I wonder if I
can just bring this in a little bit
further let me just see if I can drag
that down throw this a little bit okay
that might be as clear as this is gonna
get I wonder
yeah it is okay I tell you what we're
gonna do we're going to make this a
little bit clearer because what's
happening is we're actually seeing the
page content before I did the refresh
and then slightly after so I can do I
can if I take this and I go to about
blank mr. sheean
testing way to do this testing if you're
ever curious about it record it from
about blank so that you start without
anything on the page can that can make
it easier to find your screenshot so I'm
gonna go paste in the URL here but not
hit enter not go to that yet okay hit
record okay and now go there okay yeah
hopefully that will make it a little
easier to see what's going on okay so
you see we've gone from here into the
screenshots we see this we see the
original page content the top of the
page and then we're going down to our
deep link just below that so my
assumption is if we if we bring our zoom
in here then around about here in fact
we can just is this here yeah OOP you
see we're just right on this line here
where we go from nothing to something
right nothing to something is exactly
the point where we actually start to see
this this the first read is the context
for paint coming in yeah this is the
first thing that the user sees but it's
not the main thing that they wanted to
see when they were when they were
loading the page yeah in fact is saying
the largest content for paint at this
point is actually this piece of text now
let's try it one more time from her just
a really really dial it in I wasn't
going to go for slow 3G I'm gonna go to
about blank again and I'm gonna hit
record and I'm gonna see what happens I
feel like we're gonna see something
reasonable here let's process that
profile okay there we go
this I think is starting to make more
sense to me over here there we go okay
Wow there we are
first content for paint is here there
okay and then much later Boop there
comes our image okay which is slightly
over to the right here and there so I
can select that area and as from the
based on the screenshots roughly there
and I say that's the first content for
paint and then if I select later on in
the screenshots there thanks Allah
that's the largest content for paint
which is high in me down okay let's nice
that dev tools shows you exactly what
element on the page is the largest
content for paint
absolutely I can't resist I know we're
going to talk about layout shifts next
but why don't just jump the gun a little
bit we actually have a layout shift
showing up between first at content for
paint and largest content for paint and
I think based on this I think the reason
is because we're going from no image to
image it's pushing the content down
their terrain so I think we're seeing
the page content move so my guess is if
we were to go and find this image here
in the elements panel we're gonna see
that it doesn't actually have yeah it
doesn't have width and height attribute
set yeah and I think that's basically
causing this to happen so if you will
come and we'll talk about layout shifts
more in a second but the reason this
page is shifting is because we have an
image here that that loads when it loads
loads asynchronously essentially and it
when it's loaded it pushes the rest of
the page content down if we added width
and height attributes to this image we
wouldn't see we wouldn't see that layout
shift as I said we'll come back to that
more anymore yeah that's a good general
I guess that's practice though just let
everybody know always put width and
height attributes on your images that
way the browser can render the space
that it needs it can it can allocate a
space that it needs to render them
before it actually finished loading
loading the image so then you don't get
that layout shipped exactly the other
thing I think we should talk about
before we move on is how to optimize for
this particular situation so what would
you suggest if somebody said I need to
get first content for paint
largest contentful paint nearer the star
that is taking too long to get to these
numbers these numbers are too high do
you have a do you have a kind of go to
list of things you would say to them
yeah well definitely one thing that you
you don't want to you know ever block I
mean ideally you don't ever block
painting on more than kind of one
network request that initial network
request that you make ticket the page
content you want to be able to paint at
that point if you have additional
requests like request for fonts or style
sheets or other things that are
preventing you know the browser from
painting that will just delay the time
when that paint can happen and so you
know I mean sometimes you know it
depending upon the design you're working
with you don't have a choice but in in
an ideal world you would want to be able
to paint right away and so looks like in
this case on web dev we are able to
paint pretty quickly and then and that's
why first paint is happening you know at
the beginning and then the browser is
loading this image and then larges can
different paint happens as soon as that
image gets loaded in exactly yeah I
think what we're actually also seeing
here is the app CSS which is the main
stylesheet and the fonts as well okay my
guess is that they are going to be
blocking based on the you can see that
when I roll over them the network panel
here saying highest which is the
priority that's been assigned to the CSS
and the reason I guess is because the
CSS is going to be blocking the render
which is what you were saying
so that's why I think some people would
inline that but I guess if we go ahead
and take a quick look in our head and if
we can find we could search for it but
I'm gonna link well link rel there's the
stylesheet yeah you see there's a
stylesheet for the fonts and right below
it up dot CSS and so this would be a
classic case of here's a style sheet
it's gonna block render because the
browser crow is gonna take a look at
that and go well I need to wait and see
what styles are before I render anything
right absolutely so there can be
something that we can sometimes take a
look at say with blocky JavaScript right
yeah we see that one sometimes I guess
gets in the way can you something like
differently
sometimes her here this referred to as
critical CSS where you identify just the
CSS that is needed to layout the page
not necessarily style all the components
on your entire site and so you can
inline just that CSS content in the head
of your document and so then you're not
blocking on an additional Network
request in order to paint something on
the page exactly Yeah right so that that
was FCP and they'll seep in as I say
you'll you will find those on the
timings track here in dev tools okay so
next up
layout shifts now we talked about this
very briefly just now yeah but with
these two down here but where does it
come from what what's the history of the
layout shift and cumulative layout
shifting I think I've also heard it
called yes so the metric name cumulative
layout shift or CLS for short is a
metric that tries to capture the
experience of visual stability on a page
you probably everyone's probably had
this you know experience where you go to
a website and you go to tap on you know
a button or something and right before
you tap on it it shifts out from
underneath you it's a very frustrating
experience even if you're not
interacting with the page you're just
reading it if you know some images late
loading them and just pop in some ads
pop in the content changes like a number
of things gonna happen and you lose your
place as you're reading and it's it's
just not the greatest experience as a
user from the user users point of view
so cumulative layout shift is a metric
that attempts to quantify that
experience and so there's a couple
pieces there but a layout shift is
anytime an element on the page between
one frame and the next frame it's start
position changes and so this will happen
like in this case that we just saw an
image loads in and it pushes the text
below it down and so the image that the
layout shift was not on the image the
layout shift was on the text below the
image that on the previous frame it had
you know an X and y position of
something and then on the next frame it
was pushed lower and so it's position
change so it's a bit you know tough to
explain but the CLS
is a measure of both how much of the
page content moved and also how far it
moved and so if the entire page content
shifts from being fully visible on the
page to not visible at all that would be
a CLS of one if that happened 20 times
throughout the page lifecycle that would
be a CLS of 20 you know and then if it
moves kind of half of the screen
distance and the the image itself is
only filling up half the screen that
would be roughly you know 0.25 CLS you
can go read more about how to calculate
CLS and whether the dev is a little bit
too complicated to explain now but that
gives you a sense it's a measure of kind
of how much visible instability there is
on the page okay so as we talked about
before then we have this one layout
shift here and so on first this is
probably the better one of the two to
actually demonstrate this and when you
click on this and it's in this
experience track if you don't get this
experience track in dev tools it means
that we didn't detect any layout shifts
in that particular recording if you do
find that it's there then you'll see
that it's populated with these kind of
records now you can click on this and it
will take you off to the detailed
information about CLS but what we try
and do is we try and give you a sense of
the score and the cumulative score of
buzzwords about what's going on but we
also try and highlight for you you see
you go going from an image here that's
11 by 11 and we show it as this very
small overlay on the on the left hand
side there to a much bigger 801 by 4 1 4
so one of the the items that I actually
have to do in this area you can see
actually have a few going on here which
are profit probably other images that
are being shifted you know as we as we
make our way through and let me let me
just one of the things I wanted to step
back for a second and just talk about
why somebody would do this I mean
typically you'll you know you'll run
lighthouse on a page or you'll go to
search consoles new corbels report or
the chrome user experience report and
you'll see that you know you have layout
shifting happening on your page and you
might be wondering to yourself ok but I
don't see it when I visit my page so
where is this layout shifting happening
and so then dev tools is a great place
to debug that into
you know figure out which page on your
site has layout shifting and then load
it up in dev tools under the throttling
conditions that you know Paul showed
earlier and then you know look and see
what dev tools was telling you is
shifting because that's how you can
figure out what's causing the layout
shift and then you know you know what
you need to do to fix it yeah and
there's more I have to do here to be
clear I think one of the things that is
missing from this which is actually
available in the data I just need to
plummet through is which elements are we
talking about but I can show you that
we've got these areas but we it does
feel like we're missing a bit of
information about exactly which elements
it is like we do with LCP we highlight
the image that we're actually you know
referring to here we should be able to
do the same here so by the time this
goes out and you're watching this give
it a try in Chrome Canary because I
might have been able to land the feature
by then yeah I'm not making any promises
but that would be good with it and just
um yeah just as a kind of a quick point
there there's often two pieces to a
layout chef there's the there's the
element that shifted and then there's
the element that caused it to shift and
so sometimes you know figuring out one
or the other can be helpful in fixing
because it looks like here that it's
showing the image that came in but
adding images so adding elements of the
Dom doesn't in itself cause layout shift
but if adding an element of the Dom
moves the elements below it then that
would cause a layout shift right because
the the default size of this image looks
to be 11 by 11 pixels to begin with and
then when it when it gets populated with
the actual pixel data it pushes down the
rest of the page content which I guess
justifies be the layout shift there yeah
yeah okay so that's that's that you know
if you've got like we said earlier if
you put width and height on these things
that will help but you can also have I
mean let me show you this other one even
on the Google home page this privacy
reminder down here if I take a recording
here and I just refresh this page we're
gonna see a layout shift here and
similarly we've got this here which is
going from down here and
I presume there's some JavaScript or
something like that that's looking to
see whether the privacy reminders been
seen and if not it pushes that content
on them and so again this is probably
JavaScript based and you're gonna know
in your own apps we know what's going on
what is it third-party content is it
your own JavaScript is your own Styles
right and it's a case of so digging into
the specifics of your application to try
and figure out exactly you know what's
triggering now like what could be
happening there in order to figure it
out so that's just you know a couple of
examples of the layout shifting that you
can see
yeah and just you know right what one
thing to keep in mind is that in an
ideal world you would have no layout
shifts on your page but sometimes it's
unavoidable
and so the you know the threshold that
we recommend you know folks stay below
is is 0.1 and so it looks here that you
know this layout shift is is quite a bit
below that and so even though you know
you still want to be at at at 0 if you
can as long as you're below 0.14 you
know 75% of your users you're usually in
good shape so you say 0.1 I guess that's
like for page load because that's where
a lot of these all of these metrics are
aimed at page load right now right yeah
so that's actually a really good point
I'm glad to have it up
CLS measures layout ships that happen
during the entire lifecycle of the page
from when you load the page until when
you unload the page even if you leave
the page open for you know days or weeks
it does measure that entire time whereas
here in dev tools you ran a trace and
you got you saw the layout shift that
happened during that trace and so in
this particular case CLS was only
measuring shifts for a small period of
time it's important that developers keep
that in mind because you know the layout
the the actual metric definition is for
the entire lifespan of the page so if
you run a lighthouse trace or a web page
test trace or even in dev tools and you
see a certain value and it's below 0.1
the threshold it just mentioned just
keep in mind that you have to actually
be measuring it the entire time you know
that that's that's the
the the metric the measure that counts
is the entire lifecycle of the page also
I think in this area we should talk
about perhaps the the metrics themselves
as a bit of an evolving art I mean we
have for example first meaningful paint
up here but this isn't one of the
metrics that we would mention and say
something like core web vitals and
there's also no metric as far as I'm
aware for something like animation
performance so that's true I guess my
question to you is what's going on there
why have we got a metric here that we
wouldn't refer to and why do we not yet
have a metric for something that we
might be interested in tracking what's
the kind of history and story there yeah
that's a good question
so FMP our first meaningful paint if you
remember from a previous you know trace
that that you did Paul FOP was right
next to FP FCP and then LCP was Lena
later in the page load so what actually
ended up happening was that oh yeah and
it looks like that's that's the case
here
so yeah after a bunch of testing I mean
F and P is essentially it's a different
metric it has a different meaning than
LCP and after a bunch of research we
found out that FMP actually wasn't as
accurate at predicting when the main you
know what most people consider to be the
most important content of the page you
know the most meaningful part of the
page the metric itself has the word
meaningful in the name but it turns out
that LCP is actually a better predictor
and so as we come up with metrics that
are better at capturing the user
experience will you know kind of
deprecated older metrics and replace
them with with newer metrics but you
know we do recognize that that's
happened a bunch over the years and I'm
sure developers are getting tired of
hearing new metrics announced all the
time and so one of the things that we
did with core web vitals with the web
files initiative and specifically with
core web idols is we're committing to
you know only introducing metrics at
most once a year for the the core set of
web vitals and so developers are
following along they can bring you know
gives them a little bit of stability if
they're building a business on these
metrics or you know predictability if
they just kind of don't want to have to
you know always be following along with
the latest and so
you know recently we announced LCP was
one of the core wet vitals and an FMP
was not one of the core Mon vitals and
like over time that will probably be
deprecated so you also bet also asked
about animation performance this is
definitely a metric that we're looking
at for the future maybe you know in 2021
or 2022 so we know that the set of core
web vitals doesn't capture the entire
you know the entire story of user
experience and we're hoping that over
time we can improve it and animation
performance is definitely a metric that
are a definitely an area of performance
that we're exploring I think the last
one that we talked about talking about
if I gather right yep I think I did it
was first input first input delay which
is not directly shown in dev tools so
what is it's not sometimes called fi D
right what is that and and why yes so
first input delay or fit or F ID for
short represents the time from when the
user you know interacts with the page of
taps on the screen or you know clicks a
key a keyboard key to the point when the
browser is able to respond to that input
event so this can you might think that
it's always going to be instantaneous
like you you know you click on the
screen and then something will happen
but as users we kind of know that that's
not the case oftentimes you know we've
all had the experience of clicking on
something or tapping on something and
not having an instant response and so
this can happen if you know there's a
bunch of JavaScript running on the page
maybe you have a large JavaScript file
that the browser is currently parsing
and executing and then so if at that
exact time a user taps on the screen
then the browser has to wait a little
bit of time before it can respond to
that input event and so f ID quantifies
like that duration of of time and you
mentioned they it's not exposed directly
in dev tools and the reason is because
I'm assuming you know here you're the
one who helped implement this but first
input delay requires an input it
requires a user and so you know
in many lab scenarios there is no user
and so you can't always measure first
input delay that way but we have another
metric called total blocking time that
quantifies just that we do have yeah
that's great and that quantifies how
often the main thread how much of the
main like how much time the main thread
is blocked and a block main thread as I
just mentioned contributes to you know
the likelihood that a user will interact
with a page but the browser won't be
able to respond right away so you said
that total blocking time is in dev tools
can you show me where that is yes oh I
see their screen I have I have long
tests over here and I yeah it is down
there and it's currently says it's
unavailable and I'll talk about that
more a little bit I've been working on
that feature in fact today so I can tell
you a little bit more about what's going
on there too so what others I've come to
web dev and I've cleared it and I'm just
going to record and I'm gonna hit
refresh and I don't expect here that I'm
gonna see any particular blocking time
because I've got a first machine I'm on
a good connection and yeah you can see
right down at the bottom here we have
total blocking time and it's currently
set to zero millisecond right
so what that roughly translates to over
here is when we zoom in on these
top-level tasks which are on the main
thread
we have no task that goes over 50
milliseconds so 50 milliseconds is our
threshold for hey this task is long and
it's it's gonna contribute to the the
blocking time right because what we want
to do is we want to keep a track on on
tasks that that go over 50 milliseconds
because they're the ones that are most
likely were the user to interact they're
the ones that are most likely to prevent
the browser from being able to respond
in in an adequate amount of time right
so we currently have no tasks block to
blocking time is defined as any time
greater than 50 milliseconds in a task
so if a task is right forty nine
milliseconds there's zero blocking time
and if a task is 51 milliseconds there's
one millisecond of blocking time and
just out of curiosity some people asked
why you know why 50 milliseconds what's
the thinking behind that yes
the answer is that the idea you might
have heard of rail the rail performance
model and you've heard often times
people say you should always respond
within 100 milliseconds of user input
and so the question is why is 50
milliseconds to the blocking time and
the idea there is that if you ever have
if you keep all of your tasks below 50
milliseconds then there's never
situation where two tasks can't both run
within the 100 millisecond threshold and
so that's kind of if people are
wondering why that 50 millisecond time
exists and why we chose that for the the
magic number with total blocking time
exactly and of course if you were doing
an animation then your task time really
should be under like 10 or - that's
irregular seconds so so we'd sort of it
you got to be context aware the 50
milliseconds number is a it's a great
number to have in mind especially for
load performance but it does change
depending on the context and whether
you'll say animating or not now what as
I said we have no tasks here that are
running long and now and if I got a
trace like this from somebody I would be
very happy perfect I would say listen oh
yeah I wouldn't complain at this at all
but what I can do is I can least
simulate a slower device like I did
before over my capture settings I'm
going to go to like a six time slowdown
and I'm expecting that this 25
milliseconds here is gonna run long so
this is some JavaScript that's being
evaluated so I'm going 6 times slow down
I'm gonna hit record and I'm gonna
refresh again okay I want to do two
things I'm gonna stop the recording a
little bit earlier than I did last time
but the first thing to notice here is
our tasks are now longer because of the
slowdown
and if i zoom in on this task it's a
hundred and seventy-six mm 0.5 five
milliseconds and you said it's qualified
for being a long task goodbye what's a
hundred and twenty six point five five
milliseconds okay so what we do is after
the 50 millisecond point on this task we
do this candy striping here and we also
pop a red triangle up into the top right
hand corner so that when you're looking
at a glance like zoomed out you get a
sense of just how many of your tasks are
running a bit long
I think almost universally here the ones
that are running
javascript-based yeah so if you if you
again you know are looking at the chrome
user experience report or search
consoles core web files report and you
see that you have a first input delay
that's higher than you would have
expected for a certain page I think this
is a great example of how you would go
about debugging that so like you might
you know be on your fast MacBook Pro
laptop or something and not see any long
tasks but if you go into dev tools and
you throttle the CPU and then you start
seeing a bunch of long tests like shown
here and that would help explain why
because if a user tried to interact with
the page during one of these long tests
the browser would not be able to respond
it would have to wait until the task
completed before it could run those
event handlers
yes supporting and sing unavailable
there in the bottom in dev tools what
does what does that mean yeah so
sometimes we do say unavailable the
reason is we wait for blink to tell us
when it's happy for us to declare the
page interactive and at that point it
tells us how much blocking time it
measured and so sometimes if the trace
isn't long enough we don't actually get
that information so what I've been
working on actually recently is adding
in an estimate which is essentially
counting up the amount of candy striping
that we're getting right in those
top-level records so that we can at
least give you an estimate even if blink
hasn't given us the kind of official
answer so hopefully you should see that
in Chrome Canary them soon yeah that
makes sense
because yeah total blocking time is
technically the definition is the amount
of blocking time between first content
for paint and time to interactive and so
it makes sense that dev tools would wait
until the browser is interactive but
yeah that doesn't seem like a good
feature to just give like in an
unofficial total when it's not
interactive yeah exactly so now we've
talked about FCP LCP layout shifting and
long tasks and if ID or fit uh yeah if I
was a developer who wanted to know more
about these things as well as playing
within dev tools where would I go and
get more information
that's a great question you can go to
web dev slash vitals and that will have
you know all the information about the
definitions of the metrics links to
guides and how to optimize for them you
know links to more information about all
the tools that's
work them and everything like that so
definitely the best place is to go to
web dev slash vitals
[Music]
[Applause]