[Music]
[Applause]
hello again everybody for those of you
who don't know me yet my name is
Elizabeth Sweeney and I'm a product
manager on the web platform team in
Chrome I'm excited to talk with you all
today about the latest and greatest in
our speed tooling I'll be sharing some
updates as far as how we think about
measuring user experience including
metrics updates and our new core web
idols initiative as well as making sure
that we're privy to you know all of the
newest features products and updates to
our developer tooling as far as speed
measurement is concerned so let's dive
in well I know we've heard it before it
is worth reiterating why metrics change
well ultimately it's because our
understanding of how to best measure
user experience evolves over time as we
learn more and work through technical
hurdles we need to make sure that our
metrics and tooling are updated to
reflect the latest in our learnings
fundamentally we view it as
mission-critical to give you the most
accurate and effective mechanisms by
which to optimize your site's experience
and help you achieve your goals
and that doesn't just mean for one of
you users or a few we want to make sure
that as many users as possible
regardless of what network they are on
or what hardware they're using are in
the bucket of users that want to come
back to your site again and again and
that brings us to the impetus behind
court what vitals we have long been
espousing performance and user
experience quality because we believe
that good site performance leads to
better outcomes for users businesses
developers and for the web in general
the core vitals initiative aims to bring
together a more cohesive picture of web
performance so that there is a better
shared understanding of what should be
prioritized first let's take a moment to
review the metrics themselves
largest contentful paint LCP is a
measurement of perceived loading
experience it marks the point during
page load when the primary or largest
content element has loaded and is
visible to the user within the viewport
it's an important complement to first
contentful paint FCP which only captures
the very beginning of the loading
experience LCP provides a signal about
how quickly a user is actually able to
see the content of the page to provide a
good user experience sites should strive
to have largest contentful paint occur
within the first 2.5 seconds of the page
starting to load to ensure you're
hitting this target for most of your
users a good threshold to measure is the
75th percentile of page floats segmented
across mobile and desktop devices first
input delay fi D measures the time from
when a user first interact with the page
so they're clicking on something tapping
a button that kind of thing - the time
when the browser is actually able to
respond to that interaction to provide a
good user experience for fid sites
should strive to have a first input
delay of less than 100 milliseconds to
ensure you're hitting this target for
most of your users a good threshold to
measure again is the 75th percentile of
page loads
given that FID can only be measured in
the field with real users we want to
make sure that you have a way to locally
debug and optimize fit in the lab that's
where total blocking time TBT comes in
TBT quantifies load responsiveness
measuring the total amount of time when
the main thread is blocked long enough
to prevent input responsiveness so TVT
measures the total amount of time
between first contentful paint and time
to interactive so in short you should
definitely make sure that you're
leveraging the signals that you're
getting from TBT in the lab to optimize
for F ID in the field cumulative layout
shift CLS is a measurement of visual
stability it quantifies how much of
pages content visually shifts around a
low CLS score is a signal to developers
that their users aren't experiencing
undue content shifts a CLS score below
point 1 is considered good CLS in a lab
environment is measured through the end
of a page load whereas in the field you
can measure CLS up to the first user
interaction or including all user input
so that was a quick overview but it's
important to remember that our goal is
to have the vast majority of our users
served with fast interactive stable
experiences to that end core web vilas
uses the 75th percentile value of all
page views in the field to evaluate
against these thresholds so in other
words if at least 75% of page views into
a site meet the good threshold then the
site is classified as having a good
performance for that metric and this
applies to all three of the Korowai
vitals LCP fit and CLS the 75th
percentile is used to evaluate all of
them
as I mentioned before our ability to
measure user experience quality is
always improving we expect to update
core web idols on an annual basis and
provide regular updates on the future
candidates motivation and implementation
status looking ahead toward 2021 the
core Web vitals will be refreshed to
ensure that it reflects the latest in
our learnings and this includes
adjustments to the set of metrics as
well as the thresholds
let's do a quick refresher on the value
of combining both lab and field signals
together to diagnose optimize and
monitor your site's performance lab data
which is synthetically collected in a
testing environment is critical for
tracking down bugs and diagnosing issues
because it is reproducible and has an
immediate feedback loop field data
allows you to understand what real-world
users are experiencing conditions that
are impossible to simulate in the lab
the real world's messy you mean there's
permutations of devices there's Network
configurations cache conditions the list
is long either set of metrics taken in
isolation
aren't nearly as powerful as when
they're combined
and that's why we try to provide you
with ample coverage for both lab and
field tools we have the tools that focus
on providing you with what you know
information about what real users are
experiencing field tools such as the
chrome user experience report search
console and the new Web vitals extension
and then we have our lab tools as well
coming in to provide you with mechanisms
to see what needs improvement before a
user ever even sees your page and it
gives you a reproducible environment to
debug and optimize those are tools like
the chrome dev tools and lighthouse
PageSpeed insights is a great place to
start to give you a pulse on your core
web idles performance in both the field
and in the lab because it leverages
crooks and lighthouse under the hood
given that the Korowai vitals initiative
aims to help folks know what should be
prioritized first we wanted to make sure
you had full support and tooling
coverage for LCP FID and CLS core what
vitals are now in all of your favorite
developer tools and there are more than
the what is even listed here and that
includes a new web vitals library and a
bunch of ecosystem tools that have
already adopted them you're able to
measure your Korra vitals for a specific
page for your origin locally in the lab
and from real users in the field and as
I mentioned before total blocking time
TBT it's a proxy metric for FID that
allows you to debug and improve your
interactivity in the lab which is why
it's listed here in the fit column
before we go over all of the latest
updates in each tool I wanted to make
sure that you had all of our tools
mapped in a workflow for core web idols
which tools do what where do I go first
as I said before a good place to start
to get a general pulse is PageSpeed
insights but all of our tools have a
really critical role to play using
search console allows you to see across
your entire site and identify which
types of pages need improvement then you
can diagnose and optimize locally with
lighthouse and chrome dev tools we have
some really new capabilities by the way
I'm excited to share with you in a
moment and then you can prevent
regressions with lighthouse CI and
create a custom dashboard to monitor
your site with crux along the entire
journey you can turn to web dev for
guidance all right let's get into the
tool updates themselves lighthouse just
announced v6 last month which has new
metrics including Cora vitals new audits
and a new performance score let's start
with the updates to the perf score
on a high level we want to make sure
that you can get a sense of your loading
performance interactivity and layout
predictability the metrics and the
weights of those metrics that formulate
the top level score are intended to give
you a balanced view of your user
experience against critical dimensions
of quality while three new metrics have
been added the core way vitals metrics
three old ones have been removed first
meaningful paint for CPU idle and maths
potential fit these removals are due to
considerations like metric variability
as well as simply having newer metrics
that offer better reflections of the
part of the user experience that we're
trying to measure with that metric
there are also improvements to the
weights based on user feedback for
instance reduction of time to
interactive suite in the final scoring
calculation is in direct response to
user feedback about variability and
inconsistencies in metric optimizations
correlating with improvements to the
user experience however it is still a
valuable signal to understand when a
page is fully interactive and that's why
we still keep it TBT serves as a nice
complement to TTI so that together
you're able to more effectively optimize
for user interactivity
there's also a super nifty scoring
calculator to help explore the
performance score the calculator gives
you a comparison between v5 and v6
scores as well it's not shown here but
it's in the tool and when you run an
audit with lighthouse 600 the report
comes with a link to the calculator with
your results pre-populated so I highly
recommend you check it out
lighthouse v6 also offers quite a few
new audits these are with a focus on
JavaScript analysis and accessibility
you can now easily trace how much unused
code is being shipped with your
application as well as making sure that
you're providing audits to check that
screen readers and other assistive
technologies have all of the information
they need about the behavior and purpose
of controls on your web page to serve
users well
all of the products that lighthouse
powers are updated to reflect the latest
version including lighthouse CI which
now enables you to easily measure your
core web idols on pull requests before
they're merged and deployed PageSpeed
insights psi reports on the lab and
field performance of a page on both
mobile and desktop devices the tool
provides an overview of how real-world
users are experiencing the page that's
powered by crooks and a set of
actionable recommendations on how a site
owner can improve page experience that's
provided by lighthouse
PageSpeed insights and the psi API have
also been upgraded to use lighthouse
Excel under the hood and now support
measuring core web vitals in both the
lab and field sections of the report so
core web vitals are annotated with the
blue ribbon that you see here from the
crux data set you'll be able to see
whether or not 75% of your loads are
hitting the core web idles thresholds
for each metric in the field for both
your page and for your origin then you
can take a look at your lab data from
lighthouse to see whether or not you are
hitting the core web vinyls thresholds
for each metric in a synthetic testing
environment this helps to guide you
towards actionable opportunities to
improve your pages performance now the
new core web idles report in search
console helps you to identify groups of
pages across your site that require
attention and this is also based on
real-world field data from crux
URL performance is grouped by status
metric type and URL group which is
basically groups of similar webpages the
report is based on the three core web
vitals metrics and it's a great way to
identify pages that need attention on
your site
there are many many cool new things and
dev tools but I'm going to focus on just
two of them right now that are related
to core what vinyls support
first is the capacity to now debug
interaction readiness with total
blocking time in the footer the total
blocking time TBT metric again the proxy
for first input delay is now shown in
the footer of the chrome dev tools
performance panel when you measure page
performance the performance panel has a
new experience section that can help you
detect unexpected layout shifts this is
helpful for finding and fixing visuals
instability issues on your page that
contribute to cumulative layout shift so
you select the layout shift to view it's
details in the summary tab and to
visualize where the shift itself
occurred
hover over the moved from and move to
fields and for more information on
everything that's new in dev tools um
see that what's new in dev tools chrome
84 link that's here the chrome UX report
crux is a public data set of real user
experience data on millions of websites
we just hit over 7 million so that's
awesome it measures field versions of
all of the court web idols even if you
don't have room on your site crux can
provide a quick and easy way to assess
your core web idols the newly redesigned
crux dashboard allows you to easily
track an origins performance over time
and now you can use it to monitor the
distributions of all of your core web
idols metrics to get started with the
dashboard you can check out the tutorial
on web dev we've also introduced this
new core web idols landing page to make
it even easier to see how your site is
performing at a glance there is also a
new crux API for you to use build from
the ground up to provide developers with
simple fast and comprehensive access to
field based experience data developers
can query for an origin or a URL and
segment results based on different form
factors the API updates daily and
summarizes the previous 28 days worth of
data including your core web idols
performance we're excited to integrate
more features over time to enable new
ways to explore the data and discover
insights about the state of user
experiences
webdev is your go-to place for guidance
on web development it also now sports
the canonical page for information about
load vitals
the webdive measure tool also allows you
to measure the performance of your page
over time and it provides a prioritized
list of guides and code labs on how to
improve its measurement is powered by
PageSpeed insights which has lighthouse
6.0 under the hood and fully supports
the core with vitals metrics as you can
see here there are also a slew of other
amazing tools to help you with measuring
optimizing and monitoring your core
while vitals the Web vinyls extension
measures the three core web idles
metrics in real time for desktop in
Google Chrome this is helpful for
caching issues early on during your
development workflow and as a diagnostic
tool to assess performance of core web
vinyls as you browse the web the
extension is now available to install
from the Chrome Web Store the web vinyls
library is a tiny modular library for
measuring web vitals metrics on real
users in a way that accurately matches
how they're measured from chrome and
reported to other Google tools the
library supports all of the core Web
vitals as well as other field vitals
site kit Google's official WordPress
plugin allows you to get insights about
how people find and use your site how to
improve monetize your content directly
in your WordPress dashboard they've also
just updated to ensure that you know how
you're performing against core web idols
as I mentioned earlier - we're so
excited to have so many amazing
ecosystem players and production
monitoring solutions already
implementing support for Korowai vitals
honestly we're delighted and thank you
so much for your amazing work it's
really cool and this is a long list of
links but I'll make sure to tweet them
as well so that you can click through
them more easily there are a bunch of
goodies in here and with that I'm just
going to give you a huge thank you
really appreciate your time
[Music]
[Applause]