[Music]
hi everyone thanks for joining me my
name is Rick disco me I'm an engineer
and developer advocate on web
transparency projects at Google
including the chrome user experience
support or crux for short as you may
know crux is a powerful data set
containing insights about how real users
experience the web and this data set
goes all the way back to late 2017 and
includes data from over 18 million
websites this will be a somewhat
advanced presentation so if you want to
brush up on the basics you can visit the
crux docks at bitly slash chrome UX
report to learn about things like
metrics dimensions best practices and
more what I'll be sharing with you today
are a few pro tips for mining the
low-level data set on bigquery for
insights about how users are
experiencing the web so by now I'm sure
you've heard of core web vitals there
are the most important UX metrics we
think you should be looking at in 2020
the list includes LCP FID and CLS in
fact Kruk supports all three of these
metrics and has months of data across
millions of websites so let's head over
to bigquery to see what we can find here
I'm querying the metrics summary table
which is a really quick and easy way to
get high-level stats about a website's
core web vitals you can see here that
we're extracting the percent of user
experiences that meet the good
thresholds for LCP FID and CLS as well
as metrics 75th percentiles all of these
stats are pre computed for you so you
can spend more time finding insights and
less time writing queries this summary
table is also much smaller and more
efficient you can see it processes only
about a hundred megabytes so you
shouldn't have any concerns about
exceeding your one terabyte of free
monthly quota the raw data still exists
if you need access to specific histogram
bins but almost everything you need is
here in the materialized data set if
you've ever queried the raw data you'll
know that there are several useful
dimensions that you can drill down on
like month device type and country so
let's look at a few examples of doing
that efficiently with the summary table
the first thing we'll do is modify this
query to see how the core web vitals
have changed in recent months to do that
we need to change our where clause to
include all releases in 2020 by setting
the condition to date greater than 20
2001 oh 1 or January 2020 next we
include the year and month of the
release and the select clause so we can
see it in the output the difference
between year month and date is that the
tables are partitioned by date while the
yeren month corresponds to the table
names in the raw data set and finally we
can sort the results chronologically and
run the query you can see from the
results that web dev has had relatively
stable and good user experience this
year but what if we want to break this
down by desktop and phone experiences
for that all we need to do is change
over to the device summary table will
restrict the results to only desktop in
phone results now tablet is available
but it's less interesting
next we'll add the device name to the
select clause and secondary sort by it
to keep the ordering of the results
consistent I'm going to run this query
but there's one thing I wanted to show
you in the results these percentages are
out of all user experiences on the
origin not just the percent of desktop
experiences or the percent of phone
experiences for boring technical reasons
so one less thing we need to do is
normalize these distributions so it
doesn't matter that desktop is more
popular than phone to do that we just
divide the metric by the total
now we have comparable results between
devices and we can see that desktop
actually trends slightly better than
phone and finally what if we want to
break this down even further by users
countries for that we can change over to
the country summary table for
demonstration purposes let's restrict
the results to two countries with very
different experiences Korea and Nigeria
and focus only on desktop now we could
write the country code to the results
but I wanted to show you one other cool
trick the crux data set includes an
experimental function to map country
codes to full names
and the last thing we'll do before
running the query is to sort by country
rather than device the results tell a
really interesting story about the
disparity and user experience by country
and bakery was able to analyze this in
only a couple of seconds and using only
about a gigabyte of data so that's it
these are just a few quick examples of
the power of the bigquery data set and
it doesn't have to be mysterious or
expensive I hope you start exploring the
data set and finding insights about the
state of the web you can find links to
all the resources and queries we
discussed in the description and
comments of this YouTube video if you
have any questions at all we have a
whole support network set up for you you
can find me on twitter at rick Viscomi
and i also tweet from a chrome UX report
we have announcement and discussion
groups for important product updates and
support we have the crux cookbook on
github where you can find example
queries for common problems and finally
we have crux office hours where we can
meet virtually and get your questions
answered I hope you found this useful
please hit the thumbs up if you did
thanks for watching everyone
you